[
  {
    "id": "0x00f7b46fe79cbfc90dd0abe00016500aa14e70fee31911cb0d155dbb1dec7c20",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728303842,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x041a23"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa690fdca02418a248404ff6ebf1ad18ca3bb08a6b2f75329f6167934bae9f32f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmesR4PMqamyqND8pXFRUUJg5i2fNvGtEGZLsaCp4h7fGT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We conducted 2 researches that served as a reference for measuring participation in Governance:\n\nToken House Participation and Incentives: Season 5 (Cycles 16-19), captures essential data on delegate participation and provides a condensed overview of governance during Season 5. It analyzes the Collective's evolution, highlighting significant findings such as a increase in mission proposals and a rise in active delegate participation, while noting a decline in mission approval rates, which may suggest a more rigorous selection process. \n\nBig Picture: The Grants Council, documents the evolution of the Grants Council, emphasizing its transition from a governance experiment to a vital structure within Optimism. This report details the Council's efforts to streamline grant distribution, enhance transparency, and improve fund management, offering a chronological and quantifiable perspective on its activities, structure, budget allocations, and results over the seasons. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Token House Participation and Incentives served as a guide for the Foundation to determine the Retro Delegate Rewards for Season 5. While the Grants Council report was included as part of the govNERDs contribution path. \n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x020d9b09e71d07f84bac367b85dca1b1cdc9852410a47a3167db038998b53051",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728647892,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04bc"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa7c869cda294fb3ab1cfe0e1776f54233aa04bef61381e9ddb8b4744cfe0623e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNnYyNfpTnpbGnuAYcG8rAYdQdH7Y3byM6daTtdPWyJT8",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "CharmVerse powered the end to end grants process of the Grants Council, servicing a total of 1,171 applications across Season 5 and 6. The process includes application intake, Council evaluation, communication & notifications, and milestone tracking. \n\nOver the past 12 months, monthly active users ranged from ~1k to 4.4k. In Cycle 19, NPS from finalist was 9/10, exceeding target of 7/10, indicating high satisfaction levels among applicants with the grants process. \n\n\"Special acknowledgment is due to the Charmverse team for their instrumental role in providing the necessary tools to facilitate the review process. Leveraging the rubric, workflow, and form tools for the first time, we achieved an impressive success rate of 97.2% out of 314 applications without errors and solved any issues on a 12-hour gap\" - Gonna, Grants Council Lead"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "We work closely with the Grants Council and constantly evolve the platform to meet their specific needs and ensure great grantee experience in a timely manner. Both the Grants Council and grant applicants benefit from a transparent and efficient grants process. \n\n\"We are delighted to announce that rubric comments are now integrated directly into your applications. Simply navigate to your application and check the sidebar to find scores for each rubric section, along with comments from reviewers. A huge thanks to the Charmverse team for implementing this feature so quickly.\" - Gonna, Grants Council Lead"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x032f475d61add5a715e219f6ebf004d22351e79bd9eb9385fdb42cd83f3fdc40",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727957057,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04af44"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x3a635ed87d589f52c9a174114c1c2d1f3424a54cecf3c08979cbde055161d46a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmdvKQUZKFm3LSgSxNRX29b8NtvAsqhtYK1RhvgTTNKPsC",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Our DAO has 159 unique members who have provided us with 131k OP votes. We follow new proposals every day and have participated in almost every vote.\n\nIn order to attract this number of users, we held various events and engaged in media outreach. We have also done a lot of work with CIS Influencers, so the number of participants and the amount has increased several times since PRGF3. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The number of active DAO participants increased from 93 to 159 and the amount from 38k to 131k OP. So we can confidently say that we have done a great job in increasing the decentralization of the network over the last year. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x04767507c68b942ad2994b737d7d2274bae182d9cf3f71a38428553b767b4e6c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728305888,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0597fb"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x243ebd69b4b92360b4c338bc80c5087a755989b0a7ad271607211990e9f974d4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNQzHzFuPXZ9VQGhsJA7PaSFjVW7g7d771mAVWP4doSbg",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Lighthouse native mobile app makes it easy for Citizens and Delegates to participate in Optimism governance. We built support for Optimism's custom Governor contract, which enabled us to add multiple powerful new features:\n\n1. We've added real time push notifications of new proposal and voting activity. \n\n2. We've added the ability to vote on proposals, on-chain, natively from within the Lighthouse app. \n\n3. We also pulled in on-chain comments and displayed them within the app, to surface community sentiment around proposals for users.\n\n4. Our interactive Farcaster Frames integration enables on-chain proposals and comments to be shared, further increasing awareness and participation in the social media space.\n\nThis all works together to provide a powerful and feature-complete alternative client for users who wish to vote on the go."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Token holders, delegates and followers benefit by Optimism being on Lighthouse. Even users who do not hold Optimism tokens are able to follow core Optimism proposal activity, making Optimism governance more accessible throughout the ecosystem."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x095c89a70e86e99dc9a73b887de51a6400d9b359b9a9b8754105cefeac9b0bb8",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728379157,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02eaec"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0971cd089d681dec089e25333fc77be8572e18b4074f6946c3ae5cce6c1bd1b0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmd3EXxAUXpeZHLJhwje5D1jgp3WLaPh27voXSj3civDP5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "THIs is a test\nTHIs is a test\nTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a test"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "THIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a test"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x0f2f550f2493f001272f3066ce18d8000b7dbc688eca9237b241564dd8d8f853",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728570228,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xef23b3d8ea6aaae8b1ca6a7c70f6976780def081d37ac6a45c80afa1e76dc341",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNuWiTBzH2SJM9gbKMEVNQfsDw6bFnoUrbmBNafi5QT1v",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the council. In Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where the Foundation multisig was removed from the Upgrade multisig, and the Security Council became the sole signer. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x159b96ce2773095fd7f1c3cc7d0b5c8302fb474b589a36590bd06ba0b336c5cf",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727871280,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04af44"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x3a635ed87d589f52c9a174114c1c2d1f3424a54cecf3c08979cbde055161d46a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmdvKQUZKFm3LSgSxNRX29b8NtvAsqhtYK1RhvgTTNKPsC",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Our DAO has 159 unique members who have provided us with 131k OP votes. We follow new proposals every day and have participated in almost every vote.\n\nIn order to attract this number of users, we held various events and engaged in media outreach. We have also done a lot of work with CIS Influencers, so the number of participants and the amount has increased several times since PRGF3. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The number of active DAO participants increased from 93 to 159 and the amount from 38k to 131k OP. So we can confidently say that we have done a great job in increasing the decentralization of the network over the last year. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x16a5bbfbc6581bfb6b2dd30a81d098700e1a5157553a999f999a94a01dfc95d0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727979665,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x041a23"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0c5e252f2270b46b84fcc7b90aaf3afbf70d18a6e82af79cb189e4a100b4d2bb",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmesR4PMqamyqND8pXFRUUJg5i2fNvGtEGZLsaCp4h7fGT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We conducted 2 researches that served as a reference for measuring participation in Governance:\n\nToken House Participation and Incentives: Season 5 (Cycles 16-19), captures essential data on delegate participation and provides a condensed overview of governance during Season 5. It analyzes the Collective's evolution, highlighting significant findings such as a increase in mission proposals and a rise in active delegate participation, while noting a decline in mission approval rates, which may suggest a more rigorous selection process. \n\nBig Picture: The Grants Council, documents the evolution of the Grants Council, emphasizing its transition from a governance experiment to a vital structure within Optimism. This report details the Council's efforts to streamline grant distribution, enhance transparency, and improve fund management, offering a chronological and quantifiable perspective on its activities, structure, budget allocations, and results over the seasons. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Token House Participation and Incentives served as a guide for the Foundation to determine the Retro Delegate Rewards for Season 5. While the Grants Council report was included as part of the govNERDs contribution path. \n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x183766e346b3d36aa8586f3aa6260f7bd8c2d232e1e68f3ecf44e8ec1ab25a6c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728650614,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04bc"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x71ab640641b9c11726f5ad4f492ef9a8923a5ed16405588990c530c42956e0cc",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXvkM8XwYLM3sJDRP9cCLYVDbRRJTmbGqC5qfK5Aq2F96",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Retro Funding Review Tool enables application reviewers to ensure that all Retro Funding applications voted on by badge holders met eligibility criteria, prior to voting. The tool facilitated Retro Funding Round 4 & 5's application review process. Prior to CharmVerse, reviews were coordinated using complicated excel sheets where the core team spent countless hours in an error-prone process.  "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "All badge holder reviews for Retro Funding 4 and 5 were conducted on CharmVerse. The processes supported 416 applications with 271 applications approved. 46 Reviewers leveraged the platform to conduct their reviews. \n\nThe tool saved the core team countless hours. It streamline the process and save time for the 46 reviewers. Finally, all applicants benefited from the result of a better run process with higher transparency and reduced bias and errors. \n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1907793738701cfa13d170f95b0cb89785813d9f7691bed3b7ef46fa890a0a26",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728308730,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04af44"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x802a9e75b95414a35bf1e4a4196205ec47ef44c09a855a573ad80902a5c0388f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmdvKQUZKFm3LSgSxNRX29b8NtvAsqhtYK1RhvgTTNKPsC",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Our DAO has 159 unique members who have provided us with 131k OP votes. We follow new proposals every day and have participated in almost every vote.\n\nIn order to attract this number of users, we held various events and engaged in media outreach. We have also done a lot of work with CIS Influencers, so the number of participants and the amount has increased several times since PRGF3. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The number of active DAO participants increased from 93 to 159 and the amount from 38k to 131k OP. So we can confidently say that we have done a great job in increasing the decentralization of the network over the last year. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1cf0a9526f881fb5c8a4e7c94c98fbc7218d067716bc2a1b700452cf1514c02e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728379170,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02eaec"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8bc916ebbd65006060733b3689728d42bbbcc1bb686c9f27cc0e9a7553974152",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQzWaJP5jWnF2v8YYtB14GGxEmhLf122g9jLUif9xmkyS",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "This is my council\nThis is my council\nThis is my council\nThis is my council\nThis is my council\nThis is my council\nThis is my council\nv\nThis is my council\nThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my council"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "This is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my councilThis is my council"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1dcd33107f8c3e366fbdf915d3b449928cef01b2d2fae7946ce565e3d5f0b71b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728580866,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x16fa"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x6a83b66ad2dd508f3ec1f1896b0508d14178c002cdb573b91eb11b4870c8604a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZP2N4VFTQaZZaUf78VdFSKEvxdtV23dapnDZu7Qk9Pe",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "There were three goals for the DAB in Season 5, as laid out in the [initial forum post](https://gov.optimism.io/t/developer-advisory-board/6892):\n\n1) Assess and approve Delegate Mission Request 13 drafts based on their technical merits \n2) Aid the Grants Council in assessing approved Delegate Mission Requests and Mission Applications 13 under Intent #1\n3) Advise the Grants Council in assessing the completion of technical milestones\n\nAdditionally, there was one implicit goal:\n\n4) Act as a test run to determine whether the DAB is a useful part of Optimism Governance, explore additional ways to help, and formalize processes for future seasons."
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "On the explicit goals:\n- All Mission Requests were reviewed by multiple DAB members, who provided that input to the community in order to determine the right MRs to fund.\n- All applications to the Grants Council under Intent #1 received feedback from 2+ DAB members to help better allocate funds. \n- Additionally, the DAB expanded our scope to provide input on all requested applications, not just Intent #1, a learning that has carried over to future seasons.\n- The DAB also began to give feedback on the funding amount, which resulted in 100k+ OP being saved by governance due to more appropriate funding.\n\nAdditionally, on the implicit goal, the experiment of having a Developer Advisory Board was a great success. It was renewed for Season 6 with an expanded scope, and has continued to deliver important results."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x236e836bc180258287326907840414e1474703d4c4389662e5c0782c22b1040e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728588584,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02ef50"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x7b133c88d8e14ca916068487ac2c10f41f8c89a3133179f0f6e4d0d61273b02d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTS4DBM46DCZeHPaCKFQkP3AhgG6d6gAmafqHDxmhZP3f",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We have created a comprehensive analysis of Optimism Badgeholder's onchain activity vs a control group of active non-Badgeholders. In particular, we looked at transaction activity across chains, involvement in social apps (Farcaster, Lens, Friendtech), participation in other DAOs (Arbitrum, Uniswap, ENS) and the deployment of smart contracts and NFTs. \n\nSomething to note: although it is true that not all citizens use their Badgeholder address for other onchain activity, we found that a significant amount did and we discuss the implications of this constraint in the report.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Foundation. This work was requested directly by the Foundation in order to get a better understanding of Optimism Badgeholders vs \u201cnormal\u201d Ethereum users. In their own words: \u201cIn order to confidently expand the Citizenry, we need to have a baseline understanding of the current Badgeholder group. Our goal is to get a better understanding of the Badgeholder group based on their onchain activity compared with the onchain activity of other active Optimism/Ethereum users.\u201d\n\nIn addition, the entire Optimism Collective has benefitted from the transparency provided by this publicly available work. It's open source nature sets the stage for others to conduct further research and expand upon our results. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x23f5eed0bdfb5b5e2e7f949ab1c741f2ea0e6c19c9f84d68f16cd8e1a0e895db",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728506662,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x071aa8"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x956f1c88e58cde807ba336ecf18f5888fc3245646a10b7e13844361223d47bb2",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfEEivWp4yTr7CYP6DerRNPCfkDecBW9sFmR7Pcxs69z9",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Optimism Governance related Analytics: Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more.\nResearch or development that introduced features, improvements, or capabilities to the OP Stack.\nSecurity audits specifically on the OP Stack or its components."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Optimism Governance related Analytics: Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more.\nResearch or development that introduced features, improvements, or capabilities to the OP Stack.\nSecurity audits."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x28609269fe0de06d10d8995699fcbce41a20d69811af46b3011628aee5dda62d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727957065,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04af44"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xba1aee8cb7ed1dde4245298cfe10892ec0a4ec8e5a2c2842e6d01a4e8e668b38",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfX4PRL8eBJmvDDAavE35ERFb6U1trcmRLMpBW4QU83YQ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We have created templates for creating frames for delegating tokens. By doing so, we attracted more users from Warpcast and made it easier for delegates. More: https://x.com/zefirium_crypto/status/1795062923720573226 "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The tool is most useful for delegates who are actively creating content on Warpcast. Our tool also attracted good organic growth in Optimism, whose chain we were the first to implement in FrameMaker, and our template was the first to create a delegation pool in OP. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x28f6b6e2af4a07655c245271493bed29cf1b67266b1264f78d631c15a52f50b8",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728620382,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06aef2"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x12de53e1ba15f18f1cc8737bf7453d92b3c32005cc5572526a25a04472b297ff",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPVwApqnbJFdeFJydrPy3jTMCaLMttvo9QAEH9Q8Fn3V7",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We use Soul bound token based on Optimism network, any DAO can use LXDAO's governance mechanism, within LXDAO, every public item needs to go through a proposal to be born, we have designed and implemented a complete set of governance mechanism, so far more than 10 public items have been born in LXDAO!\nWe adopt Optimism-based point system to determine the contribution, LXPoints is based on Optimism's Soul Bound Token, members earn LXPoints through actual contribution, so far more than 138 members have earned LXPoints through contribution."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Optimism Collective, any member who joins LXDAO will get Optimism based Soul Bound Token by contributing, so far more than 138 members have got LXPonts and 94 members have got LXB (Governance Identity), by using this set of Governance Mechanisms, we also spread the At the same time, Optimismcn.eth incubated by LXDAO is currently ranked 52nd in the Optimism Delegate, and is also deeply involved in Optimism governance.\n\n2. other DAO organizations, our governance mechanism and Soul Bound Token are completely open source, any DAO organization can adopt this set to start their own DAO governance\n\n3. Web3 newcomers, any newcomer to LXDAO can learn how DAO works, and also learn about on-chain governance, DAO operation mode, etc. Currently, LXDAO has 542 registered members.\nhttps://lxdao.io/buidlers\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2b66a868125a200bc83845be422c94df1993a2fcc7cff6d8829d3ff8794468f3",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728515996,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x068796"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x36edceddaa3ae211cf41177542c79d6372662761e28bb77409103c0fa3bb13c4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYsocrp8etPaNEyPZD2qN4pG6PZHsVyyGUTUohQVcPg8M",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "It's a bit easy to manage our community we have to be able to give them space and convenience for all community members so that everything can run smoothly,Strategize various forms of NFT so they can continue to grow"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Adequate and suitable facilities for use are things that I can work on and the impact that is obtained will be very good for the progress that will occur one day.We have to be able to grow with the facilities we have and a commitment to governance or my own experiments. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2bd32a9edc6ac2e40dfd7710423d89e32dc30bb56347bd64c93616c24d49896c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728559019,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04cb02"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x76cc8a64ecc27ae75e0801c55f09eb482659e14e002189192715c9a365e22f61",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfG7XdprofgNhwXRWZeBbKykLztVJ5UVENoLgK76PpRYt",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "More participate zora user on chain incentivize new creative active user to zora chain\nUnited community together\nSharing creative idea & nft \nReal life problem consalting sharing travelling experience through nft on chain with describtion/story"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "All community members\nZora enthusiasm user/artist/creator\nNew creative / organic/active artist,creator,nft collector,crypto adventure and newbie user\nwho can create the NFT on Zora chain and get funded by thiers NFTs"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2ea886eca9ea9d49dde40213b983f14c3fe8816dba52dce50a468c892ca8ae3b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728507290,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02ed94"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xabf0f7e4310068057f3d9eb6c9d04efc73c1a97cbb02edd173e8109c4011c845",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUZepxjK7j4CuZvpVBskUvxJeP43dWra6eEczmvevKu8c",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "https://www.coinvise.co/casino-royal and   https://rounds.wtf/gadgets-gizmo/gadgets-round--my-good-value-gadgets-1\nMy channels Use Coinvise to gain channel member by pay OP and other Token\nHere's how I invite members to join my channel using OP tokens:\n- I set up a reward system on Coinvise where new members receive OP tokens for joining.\n- The amount of OP tokens offered is attractive enough to incentivize participation.\n- I create a unique invitation link through Coinvise that includes the token reward.\n- When someone clicks the link and joins, they automatically receive the promised OP tokens.\n- This creates a win-win situation: I gain new channel members, and they receive valuable OP tokens.\nBy using this method, I've seen a significant increase in channel membership and engagement. The OP token incentive has proven to be an effective way to attract and retain members who are interested in cryptocurrency and blockchain technology\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "https://share.airstack.xyz/s/7Sy Fan Token is next step \n\nGrowth from Coinvise \nTotal claimed 50/50\nFARCASTER_JOIN_CHANNEL\t80\nFARCASTER_RECAST\t51\n\nand https://www.castsense.xyz/channel/gadgets-gizmo  performance Please check our Growth rate here"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x301bc775a168dead81f72678fb82a0a4d98a1ef721b9343d1bfd689d69118b38",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728581509,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x16fa"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcd46c604f9a028796b402a5de2a552d2389bc2fa851d92c2e0271fa305d14335",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZP2N4VFTQaZZaUf78VdFSKEvxdtV23dapnDZu7Qk9Pe",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "There were three goals for the DAB in Season 5, as laid out in the [initial forum post](https://gov.optimism.io/t/developer-advisory-board/6892):\n\n1) Assess and approve Delegate Mission Request 13 drafts based on their technical merits \n2) Aid the Grants Council in assessing approved Delegate Mission Requests and Mission Applications 13 under Intent #1\n3) Advise the Grants Council in assessing the completion of technical milestones\n\nAdditionally, there was one implicit goal:\n\n4) Act as a test run to determine whether the DAB is a useful part of Optimism Governance, explore additional ways to help, and formalize processes for future seasons."
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "On the explicit goals:\n- All Mission Requests were reviewed by multiple DAB members, who provided that input to the community in order to determine the right MRs to fund.\n- All applications to the Grants Council under Intent #1 received feedback from 2+ DAB members to help better allocate funds. \n- Additionally, the DAB expanded our scope to provide input on all requested applications, not just Intent #1, a learning that has carried over to future seasons.\n- The DAB also began to give feedback on the funding amount, which resulted in 100k+ OP being saved by governance due to more appropriate funding.\n\nAdditionally, on the implicit goal, the experiment of having a Developer Advisory Board was a great success. It was renewed for Season 6 with an expanded scope, and has continued to deliver important results."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x324d0b95e11764e558a717df15e07fd2a5ba43a2398bc3c7f2ca4bc67aa00f37",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728650602,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04bc"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa7c869cda294fb3ab1cfe0e1776f54233aa04bef61381e9ddb8b4744cfe0623e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNnYyNfpTnpbGnuAYcG8rAYdQdH7Y3byM6daTtdPWyJT8",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "CharmVerse powered the end to end grants process of the Grants Council, servicing a total of 1,171 applications across Season 5 and 6. The process includes application intake, Council evaluation, communication & notifications, and milestone tracking. \n\nOver the past 12 months, monthly active users ranged from ~1k to 4.4k. In Cycle 19, NPS from finalist was 9/10, exceeding target of 7/10, indicating high satisfaction levels among applicants with the grants process. \n\n\"Special acknowledgment is due to the Charmverse team for their instrumental role in providing the necessary tools to facilitate the review process. Leveraging the rubric, workflow, and form tools for the first time, we achieved an impressive success rate of 97.2% out of 314 applications without errors and solved any issues on a 12-hour gap\" - Gonna, Grants Council Lead"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "We work closely with the Grants Council and constantly evolve the platform to meet their specific needs and ensure great grantee experience in a timely manner. Both the Grants Council and grant applicants benefit from a transparent and efficient grants process. \n\n\"We are delighted to announce that rubric comments are now integrated directly into your applications. Simply navigate to your application and check the sidebar to find scores for each rubric section, along with comments from reviewers. A huge thanks to the Charmverse team for implementing this feature so quickly.\" - Gonna, Grants Council Lead"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3351f219689dbf84d1eb2ea357e964127af554464f0e9618a07806bf40af5935",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728644367,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0502ae"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x536f0e168543fafd145c2186906d7116f60a751978aae0530a3759e8c7f82c11",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbDm2LWLqAED8acXn1o5PBDiQoJG8Mf9jXPuXQfXCeov4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Now we\u2019ve analyzed ~200 OP citizens (delegates and projects data is being processed now as well), and their connections over 10 data sources (Farcaster, on-chain attestations, token holdings and community association, more: https://govgraph.fyi/connection-types). The intention was to understand the nature of relations inside of the house, identify the centers of influence, and support matchmaking for the alliances. We\u2019ve identified 9 other potential use cases for the tool: https://govgraph.fyi/use-cases.\n\nSome Insight from the current study:\n- lindaxie.eth (followed by 88 citizens), w.jesse.xyz (86), purple.philm.eth (75), 0x91...5871 (75), vitalik.eth (74) are the most followed accounts on Farcaster\n- Only 19 people (~10%) have no identified connections\n- Potential connections within the Regen movement \u2013 49 people (~25%)\n\nThis work led us also to explore the Sybil algorithms for the Farcaster, where we can reuse some data and insights already."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Here\u2019s some feedback from various users:\n- Emily (OP Citizen House): this is very interesting! looks to me like I can use this to see the most connected people, who maybe also have the most influence... like vitalik and linda\n- Griff (Citizen, Delegate): It\u2019s a fantastic tool for coordination in the Citizen House. Seeing the shared connections can greatly support planning and partnerships, as well as aid in checking for collusion.\n- Kevin Owocki (Citizen): seems like a nice way to get an at-a-glance view of the op political economy\n- Divine Comedian (Citizen): Tried it out, visually it looks cool\n- Luuk (OP Developer): That sounds great, we can add the graph to the Analytics page for sure. We\u2019re also working on a second version of our website, which could have more sections about visualizations and maps\n\nAlso got accepted into\u00a0Token Engineering the Superchain rounds,\u00a0Web3 Grants Ecosystem Advancement,\u00a0CollabTech\u00a0Gitcoin rounds, got donations from 56 contributors."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3537bc7337e50d1dfeee9926990e2b6b5e2279ba68780a1019ca6423fe2650b0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727955622,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02eaec"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2100149343da41b50dd9df1c5d94443920f1903023ea521b9f059ca1f6415c99",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmd3EXxAUXpeZHLJhwje5D1jgp3WLaPh27voXSj3civDP5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "THIs is a test\nTHIs is a test\nTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a test"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "THIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a test"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3b9d0f38e3d53ebc6ec2475148c308ee02d0d3210389889c96a5b8a7132c9e1d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727964490,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2615"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x60b623e9ea847153a5aa8df22a8375b39e9cba1044987455f32c515d0fecd2c5",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTViynzJ3ujBZhHta1XtucZBNvyiBVFHU5kGZxpkEywGb",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "In collaboration with OSO, Passport XYZ's Humanity scores were used to better understand the likelihood of real humans that were interacting with projects over the last year. The goal was to determine which projects were driving spam/bot traffic versus which projects were driving real users to the Optimism ecosystem. \n\nThese metrics and the analysis was used in the RPGF4 voting and review process, improving the understanding and (we believe) the outcome for voters by informing which projects were driving real humans, and organic users to the collective versus which were just bringing short term bots or spam users to the network (often low value and transient)."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our infrastructure and tooling has benefited the Badgeholder community the most, through our support of the RPGF rounds. Although we have made humanity proofs available via Attestations for nearly a year now on Optimism, the real value of this work has come from the inclusion and integration with the badgeholder experience (and collaboration with OSO) when reviewing and voting for projects to receive rewards."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3dc19121ca74318b0365f85292a00a75d209b729d24fad50337bab6e915d4829",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728638498,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06aef2"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x12de53e1ba15f18f1cc8737bf7453d92b3c32005cc5572526a25a04472b297ff",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVUjwv8FJvrLyKYEdvhNyaStBDKe55FZ5Wh3PezzkstaT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We use Soul bound token based on Optimism network, any DAO can use LXDAO's governance mechanism, within LXDAO, every public item needs to go through a proposal to be born, we have designed and implemented a complete set of governance mechanism, so far more than 10 public items have been born in LXDAO!\nWe adopt Optimism-based point system to determine the contribution, LXPoints is based on Optimism's Soul Bound Token, members earn LXPoints through actual contribution, so far more than 138 members have earned LXPoints through contribution."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Optimism Collective, any member who joins LXDAO will get Optimism based Soul Bound Token by contributing, so far more than 138 members have got LXPonts and 94 members have got LXB (Governance Identity), by using this set of Governance Mechanisms, we also spread the At the same time, Optimismcn.eth incubated by LXDAO is currently ranked 52nd in the Optimism Delegate, and is also deeply involved in Optimism governance.\n\n2. Other DAO organizations, our governance mechanism and Soul Bound Token are completely open source, any DAO organization can adopt this set to start their own DAO governance\n\n3. Web3 newcomers, any newcomer to LXDAO can learn how DAO works, and also learn about on-chain governance, DAO operation mode, etc. Currently, LXDAO has 542 registered members.\nhttps://lxdao.io/buidlers\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3e370deb6c0637238d7dd241c764b200833124689e626bbf1cae71d591bd3ee8",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728400062,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04bc"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa7c869cda294fb3ab1cfe0e1776f54233aa04bef61381e9ddb8b4744cfe0623e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNnYyNfpTnpbGnuAYcG8rAYdQdH7Y3byM6daTtdPWyJT8",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "CharmVerse powered the end to end grants process of the Grants Council, servicing a total of 1,171 applications across Season 5 and 6. The process includes application intake, Council evaluation, communication & notifications, and milestone tracking. \n\nOver the past 12 months, monthly active users ranged from ~1k to 4.4k. In Cycle 19, NPS from finalist was 9/10, exceeding target of 7/10, indicating high satisfaction levels among applicants with the grants process. \n\n\"Special acknowledgment is due to the Charmverse team for their instrumental role in providing the necessary tools to facilitate the review process. Leveraging the rubric, workflow, and form tools for the first time, we achieved an impressive success rate of 97.2% out of 314 applications without errors and solved any issues on a 12-hour gap\" - Gonna, Grants Council Lead"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "We work closely with the Grants Council and constantly evolve the platform to meet their specific needs and ensure great grantee experience in a timely manner. Both the Grants Council and grant applicants benefit from a transparent and efficient grants process. \n\n\"We are delighted to announce that rubric comments are now integrated directly into your applications. Simply navigate to your application and check the sidebar to find scores for each rubric section, along with comments from reviewers. A huge thanks to the Charmverse team for implementing this feature so quickly.\" - Gonna, Grants Council Lead"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3fdb193f26dd143d36aafa5b9ea67acc73c3d7c023f800684847909034bb0a73",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728567204,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8f6ef49d32ec02d89e5f1c0c5d88ddbbdf77865b9ccadebb766d1321bd2ad6ea",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQdPhcxChaAq5h4MJR8XScebDysxukQK1t5bCKSfZFGNg",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4048afb350cac65a8418076f47d575362870cee600a3141d08eb422ca6cfa5ef",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728566906,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8f6ef49d32ec02d89e5f1c0c5d88ddbbdf77865b9ccadebb766d1321bd2ad6ea",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQdPhcxChaAq5h4MJR8XScebDysxukQK1t5bCKSfZFGNg",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x429ab782b441d790210d7044013aff0d8441639c7fb2537c9d991e22d6dbec58",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728501935,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02ed94"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x682bc1da5d223e670dae53161d57110873df6dd4c6f2804b058e8c1589ddffaa",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNUh3DphYReWHvXHqoRKr4Mb2H8NrVR6wrisAPnA6ECde",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "https://www.coinvise.co/casino-royal and   https://rounds.wtf/gadgets-gizmo/gadgets-round--my-good-value-gadgets-1\nMy channels Use Coinvise to gain channel member by pay OP and other Token\nHere's how I invite members to join my channel using OP tokens:\n- I set up a reward system on Coinvise where new members receive OP tokens for joining.\n- The amount of OP tokens offered is attractive enough to incentivize participation.\n- I create a unique invitation link through Coinvise that includes the token reward.\n- When someone clicks the link and joins, they automatically receive the promised OP tokens.\n- This creates a win-win situation: I gain new channel members, and they receive valuable OP tokens.\nBy using this method, I've seen a significant increase in channel membership and engagement. The OP token incentive has proven to be an effective way to attract and retain members who are interested in cryptocurrency and blockchain technology.\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "https://share.airstack.xyz/s/7Sy Fan Token is next step \n\nGrowth from Coinvise \nTotal claimed 50/50\nFARCASTER_JOIN_CHANNEL\t80\nFARCASTER_RECAST\t51\n\nand https://www.castsense.xyz/channel/gadgets-gizmo  performance Please check our Growth rate here"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x43b98e1610cf95912aec6dd3c0c532aa7e81f781476b787e70a422b4b8e5bf04",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727878783,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x51eb"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x356f5d658f7b60d6808d6128a1afe12ad7c2b8e00e015f6feebe456dc4266ebd",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPYm9grsPwsiMi7w8JeMoUQL8SuquWoTkVzro2dR1x4y7",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Jonas said this statement in regards to our contribution:\n\"The Impact Calculator tool played a crucial role in experimenting with metrics-based voting, significantly shaping the design of Retro Funding 4. By providing practical insights into the implementation of metrics-based voting, it accelerated the development process and contributed to a more effective and informed design.\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our tool has benefited every participant in the Retro Funding process. It has helped the Optimism Collective by allowing experimentation with metrics based voting, the outcome of which has benefited many projects that apply for Retro Funding in that they are now receiving rewards based on their impact instead of simply being rewarded based on their popularity."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x457a356f70b0ed82b842a7ef42b1ee09b9fa7c4c8f94285566d0e295e257616e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728405473,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x077d3a"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa981402bc2764314da31e85e8089207a1e8d5a22861ff7a65edd595fa9d324d4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXCY9qFvZCd6hwBBqHc7muDE5JSYCJseTuQkvqfNJivLd",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "power of uniz   focuses on analysis of the relationship between personal well-being, optimism about the future. Also  provide further insight into specific concerns that may give rise to optimism or pessimism.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": " uniz hope the work gets well at the potential of bringing more data into the loop. Individual effects\nresearch consistently supports that the overwhelming majority of us exhibit a bias toward optimism."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x49208aca8342cbebecc95ba9a3cd978b2d98f0ae3e78a8533aa4e1dadbb76587",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728562518,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x83f13d2b2236514f5277b41174dba0838393572f053e7ffa0e52a59be85d9c84",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQdPhcxChaAq5h4MJR8XScebDysxukQK1t5bCKSfZFGNg",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x496381914b7bbfcc8d6267741467d260d66e8001f90ad0562a5250573461a461",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728636269,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd305da5eceb8a0e98877e47f5bf3ceda5511fe2d3649c1a57590021df128695c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNuWiTBzH2SJM9gbKMEVNQfsDw6bFnoUrbmBNafi5QT1v",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the council. In Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where the Foundation multisig was removed from the Upgrade multisig, and the Security Council became the sole signer. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4de6981c21343635d158efee1e10a2720300628f45bd159a141caa20ebb331fb",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728572033,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03a0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x635975abaa62dcca8b9838407171c9275cb1ee169caa9e106d3e5018c45afdc6",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbQpDGo3SYvuCWwmvUrxj6HyHBT9gcAQC2Ynow6y17Ffv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Syntra simplifies key governance tasks for OptimismDAO Delegates, improving efficiency and decision-making. It also helps with the onboarding of new participants lowering the barrier to entry.\n\n\"### **A Day in the Life of an OptimismDAO Delegate with Syntra**\n\n- ***Efficient Proposal Creation***\n\t- *Delegates start their day by accessing a user-friendly dashboard and draft manager.*\n\t- *They can quickly draft proposals and use templates, cutting proposal creation time by 50%.*\n- ***Informed Decision Making***\n\t- *Syntra provides an overview of updated resources, ensuring delegates have all necessary context at their disposal.*\n\t- *Integration with OptimismDAO's calendar helping delegates stay up to date with community calls, office hours and seasons timelines.*\n- ***Cross-DAO Management***\n\t- *For delegates involved in multiple DAOs, Syntra provides a unified interface without the need of switching between platforms. This also lower the barrier to entry of external DAO actors*\"\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Syntra contributed to Optimism Governance since its  **private alpha release in late August**  and  **public alpha release in early September**.\n\n## Users:\n### OptimismDAO delegates\n-   **Newcomers**: Syntra lowered barriers to entry by simplifying proposal drafting, commenting, voting, and governance analysis.\n-   **Professional teams**: It streamlined internal coordination with role-based access and tracking features.\n\nAs of October 8th, Syntra has:\n\n-   **209 total logins**\n-   **33 MAU**: 33 active Optimism sessions since Sept (Month to date). \n\t- **Active**: at least 1 Draft created.\n-   OP delegates from  **5 different countries** to date.\n-   Currently also being used by SEEDGov for drafting.\n\nMore information regarding activity is available in the [Google Drive link](https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1TZWtb_Q67hwqBHNGpgT4V7HocAs1LNKT?usp=sharing)."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x529754b8b4e1a25c76b3b601abcf201ea50d50580575203945bdf5c919ec80a0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728569899,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0582bf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xc0d6e396c57622fa6dbe18c8aa892c10c6f5b7ad92f441df62ec0ea2bdaa2fdf",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTyw26nW2raPVBqAZRKPJ3jZmbz5ShfdyRvJ9iqfWoEiT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "In the past year, we deployed our stack on Base, resulting in the creation of nearly 2,000 DAOs on that chain. More recently, we\u2019ve collaborated with Mode to develop their DAO with novel tokenomics aspects built into their governance model.\n\nBesides that we've been working closely with relevant OP stakeholders like the Foundation and the grants council to develop a cutting edge cross-chain voting module that is desigend to be highly modular and adaptable. This allows other projects on Optimism to easily integrate with it or build on top of it. And thanks to Optimism\u2019s ground-breaking work adopting EIP-4844 blobs into the OP blocks, we\u2019ll be able to remove any trusted component and directly use Ethereum\u2019s merkelized roots."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Protocols and their token holders that are build on Base are currently the ones who are benefitting the most from our free-to-use and open source governance tooling.\nWith Mode's launch we've been rapidly expanding already and we would like to include more projects on the superchain in the near future. \n\nOur unique value proposition is that the governance logic is programmed into plugins, making custom and granular governance designs easier, faster, and safer to build. It allows organizations to build multi-body, multi-process, and multichain governance, tailored to their unique needs. Plugins can be installed, upgraded, and uninstalled, allowing DAOs to evolve over time, onchain, via their governance process. As we expand to Optimism's Superchain, projects will instantly benefit from open-source plugins that have been battle-tested (with actual Lindy build on the plug-ins) and adopted by others.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x55cbd5a5f790bc69754fef7ad319582937e8649fdf1102135599bc4b1411b328",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728390581,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x077495"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb106bf42180e5dac3dd47cacee5626f2922021420311346f0949e3243a6af6b0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPZ5R7FJo59owwAzkGn9Z4GWRrbHiP4fseiouZm9h4pZ2",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We developed Pairwise for RF3, and introduced categories to make the impact measurement in the Retro Funding more organic and manageable.\nIn RF3, 185 users engaged, 27 badgeholders using their key\nIn RF4, we expanded into a community-wide experiment using pseudonymous voting with zk-tech. This allowed all stakeholders\u2014badgeholders, token holders, recipients, and delegates\u2014to participate freely without pressure and promote project discovery. Here you can find the final results, and our blog conclusions for more details on our outcomes.\nThe feedback from RF4 was very positive, leading to our invitation to build together with Optimism for RF5. For this round, we developed a star rating system, enabling participants to assign stars to projects before comparing them. This system grouped projects into tiers, significantly reducing the number of comparisons required.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main target when developing the product were badgeholders, who now can use Pairwise, to rank the Retro Funding projects in a fun way that promotes project discovery. However, the entire Optimism community, including delegates, token holders, and recipients, also gained through their participation in the Pairwise Retro Funding experiment, offering them the chance to discover impactful projects and bring more visibility to emerging initiatives. Projects benefited from increased exposure to potential users. Pairwise also sparks discussions  by comparing its results to official ones, fostering deeper insights and driving more meaningful participation and progress to decentralization.\nTo incentivize engagement, we distributed 4,000 OP as rewards giving a 100OP to 40 lucky winners, 10 on each stakeholder group participating in Pairwise."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5679a8d7b8efccdb8b6e94a9db2abbf5e093fbbd66de5490e5d2b323c3a48842",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728636751,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4efa19fb904485120b596e1346ed90435e790b4d52dc4d5c2f2d68fce227ba46",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcX4Pot1Hhr3ZbbWe1Louw7Si4H4zab2myVHzo48wDTPs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5ab31944909cfbcf4a1052d86305186639f93193b11d23a87cd1fd2a4621d975",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728559668,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x046a41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x14efe58273fb2e2c53cec0e30c293aed48be721d1cfc967146973f977f3a591a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmWMV1Nci9Ytp8MThXMdCr2ExxyDaEbA2qke2PvdwJw5vW",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Superfluid Protocol was used to distribute RPGF3 and RF4 grants, streaming over 32M OP to 900+ projects in the industry to date (RF4 streams are still ongoing).\n\nThe Superfluid Dashboard substantially improved the grants claim and management UX for recipients while allowing better funds distribution monitoring and management for the Optimism team. \n\nRecipients were also able to redirect streams to their team members ensuring they got paid in real-time as funding was being paid out by Optimism.  \n\nYou can read more about the improvements enabled by Superfluid here:\nRPGF3 - https://medium.com/superfluid-blog/optimism-selects-superfluid-for-rpgf3-grants-streaming-612c37ecc89c\nRF4 - https://medium.com/@superfluid_HQ/optimism-is-streaming-rf4-grants-with-superfluid-1835182bf18b"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Prior to the introduction of Superfluid Protocol in the retro funding process grant recipients had to claim their funds via direct interaction with Optimism's smart contracts, mostly by using the block explorer interface to make a contract call.\n\nWith the introduction of Superfluid recipients can see the total amount of OP awarded to them and the detailed timeline of the grant payout. They can also manage their incoming stream by redirecting it (or splitting it) to team members, third parties or DeFi apps in real time. You can read more about stream redirection and splitting here: https://help.superfluid.finance/en/articles/8907702-how-to-split-your-incoming-rpgf-grant\n\nSuperfluid also enabled smooth funds distribution, management and control for the Optimism team.\n\nThe entire community could benefit from transparent and easy to understand funding process, timeline and status (i.e. https://dune.com/0xkhmer/retropgf-3).\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5ccb87403753fd1f69a243e0584ede10f7f256641f81be09facf9ac9d4973aff",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727871957,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03f5c5"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x97b5fc9620c1aa784c7fd1d97c94d2e762ff66c58ab7bd425a5304fdcb710ac6",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmdA6rvF2Mhy3yhreuojiKAEHuw1sAbJS1ZUYE5qRfPPT5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs.",
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "Strategic Oversight: Ensuring alignment between governance practices and the organization\u2019s strategic goals.\nRisk Management: Identifying, assessing, and managing risks to safeguard the organization\u2019s assets and reputation.\nCompliance: Ensuring adherence to legal, regulatory, and ethical standards.\nStakeholder Engagement: Facilitating communication and collaboration among stakeholders to foster transparency and trust.\nPerformance Monitoring: Evaluating organizational performance and governance effectiveness to promote continuous improvement.\nPolicy Development: Creating and maintaining governance policies that reflect best practices "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "nhanced Strategic Alignment: By actively engaging with leadership to align governance practices with strategic objectives, the function can ensure that decisions support long-term goals.\n\nRobust Risk Management: Implementing comprehensive risk assessment frameworks can help identify potential issues early, enabling proactive measures that protect the organization and enhance resilience.\n\nStrengthened Compliance Framework: Regularly reviewing and updating compliance policies ensures that the organization stays ahead of regulatory changes, minimizing the risk of non-compliance.\n\nEffective Stakeholder Engagement: By fostering open communication channels with stakeholders, the function can build trust and encourage collaborative decision-making, which enhances overall governance.\n\nContinuous Performance Monitoring: Establishing metrics to evaluate governance effectiveness allows for ongoing assessment and refinement of practices, ensuring they remain relevant and impactful.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5e846098e81a778693532ac9c97dd38bf7386599f7e5f2c2ae1a61b4923c4fbe",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728610381,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03a9be"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa8308e56a20002bdcdf84fd87e0557225358d80efb4298e68858f8d9283658b4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVF31zB2yPm5ZikSM3X5zrzoeAP4e1FkBrscLWrALCGre",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "1. Voting Participation:\n   - Measuring the level of participation from token holders or voters in governance decisions.\n\n2. Proposal Outcomes:\n   - Analyzing the results of submitted proposals, including the level of support, opposition, and whether proposals are accepted or rejected.\n\n3. Delegation Dynamics:\n   - Tracking how voting power is delegated\n\n4. Voting Power Distribution:\n   - Monitoring the distribution of voting power among token holders\n\n5. Proposal Submission Trends:\n   - Measuring the frequency and content of submitted proposals\n\n6. Token Economics Impact:\n   - Analyzing the impact of governance decisions on the token economy, such as changes in token prices following major governance votes or accepted proposals.\n\n7. Community Engagement:\n   - Evaluating overall community engagement in governance, through discussions on forums, proposal feedback, and social media activity related to governance."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "1. Governance Participants: Token holders who actively participate in voting and governance decision-making\n\n2. Core Team & Developers.\n\n3. Delegators and Voting Power Holders: Delegators or individuals holding significant voting power\n\n4. Investors.\n\n5. Community Members: Community members who are interested in transparency and accountability in governance\n\n\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6227fdd27e8a3c18a4c1fa23f08c2241c51b702633c1808a2146681ee47b6521",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727846426,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x1b93"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x57fd2c4aa2fa89df6ba6d86dfff44f96f8cb54ab06975ded24e0c4f2438b2a17",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRWqALWmVXb52XWFtHzyGCmfDD3djnDuAdkmZkaCzy2pa",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "- Voter turnout: delegate participation as of last update\n- Non-conformity: how many delegates have their \"own\" opinion when voting \n- Voting Bloc power over time: tracks the top100 or individual voting power over time\n- Voting Cost: total gas cost across votes and average gas cost per delegate\n- Inactive Delegates: who are they and how many votes they have\n- Underrated Delegates: who have little voting power but has been consistently voting and has high-non-conformity score\n- Statistics on Delegate Profiling: delegates who are self delegates vs those who have more than 1 delegators"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Professional Delegators such as a16z: to monitor performance of its delegates at OP Collective. With the dashboard that I created, they know which delegates are active and which are not contributing in governance. With the data in mind, it will facilitate liquid-delegations for their next cohort. \n\nOP Foundation: identify active OP delegates who are amongst the top 100 ones and conduct retro-reward for active participants accordingly. \n\nOP Collective Delegators: with the underrated delegate lists, they can support them by delegating OPs to these delegates and let them grow from bottom up.  "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x624e2abe3bc4e456b30147c5f639c8855ff92df8ef61730b9d95bb34d53677a1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728621759,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9d5c8068616239b3dcc67379701b0f58fe3644a7d97db6c695059fa67991dfb8",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQdPhcxChaAq5h4MJR8XScebDysxukQK1t5bCKSfZFGNg",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x68c70dcf63994b6ae4defa76d11e052bfcf308980eec850981ccd1cbbfaf0747",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728607319,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06f2d0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x55f6438bd8552b1559ab733d278d19bcba70979d9c3a9d63a58d3fef366558b9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmW5YYpXNZokKvvj1dTwJzBnAv2MKc6xrTcb7mp7eo9etT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We formulated a new **measure of decentralization** that applies to the Optimism Collective's two houses and offers scientifically grounded **guidance** for improvement. This metric is called _voting-bloc entropy_ (VBE, pronounced \"vibe\"). It is being used for measurements in three ways:\n\n* In close consultation with Optimism, we developed Optimism-specific **software tools** for measuring VBE that are now being used by the Optimism Collective to understand voting behaviors and Optimism governance more broadly. \n* We have launched a **public dashboard** that presents VBE measurements across the DAO ecosystem and includes Optimism and other leading DAOs. See https://t.co/2BqeTJtkNI. (Optimism is #1 by a nose, i.e., currently shows the highest VBE.)\n* VBE is proving an **important metric** for DAO decentralization study, as highlighted by its inclusion in, e.g., a recent Optimism Foundation Mission Request (#183)."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Beneficiaries of the three forms of measurement above include:\n\n1. The **Gov Team at Optimism** helped shape the software tools to benefit from their use in analyzing past and future voting rounds (e.g., RetroPGF rounds), conducting experiments, and improving governance practices.\n2. The **broad DAO and DeFi community** can now assess DAO decentralization across the ecosystem at a glance on our VBE dashboard---and the **Optimism Collective** benefits from showcasing of its strong commitment to and comparatively high degree of decentralization.\n3. **Teams performing research** for the Optimism Collective benefit from a rigorous metric for decentralization and supporting Optimism-specific software tools."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x68cdb59ed5563c1edca8cfff204b1ac995265183d2dd86b65c4f59dc4490e5ea",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728649720,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x046a41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xdabeb9887ce607ec0951c1c2be3ca2208f98d958f4a5e266309fb9f5d4128639",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmWMV1Nci9Ytp8MThXMdCr2ExxyDaEbA2qke2PvdwJw5vW",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Superfluid Protocol was used to distribute RPGF3 and RF4 grants, streaming over 32M OP to 900+ projects in the industry to date (RF4 streams are still ongoing).\n\nThe Superfluid Dashboard substantially improved the grants claim and management UX for recipients while allowing better funds distribution monitoring and management for the Optimism team. \n\nRecipients were also able to redirect streams to their team members ensuring they got paid in real-time as funding was being paid out by Optimism.  \n\nYou can read more about the improvements enabled by Superfluid here:\nRPGF3 - https://medium.com/superfluid-blog/optimism-selects-superfluid-for-rpgf3-grants-streaming-612c37ecc89c\nRF4 - https://medium.com/@superfluid_HQ/optimism-is-streaming-rf4-grants-with-superfluid-1835182bf18b"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Prior to the introduction of Superfluid Protocol in the retro funding process grant recipients had to claim their funds via direct interaction with Optimism's smart contracts, mostly by using the block explorer interface to make a contract call.\n\nWith the introduction of Superfluid recipients can see the total amount of OP awarded to them and the detailed timeline of the grant payout. They can also manage their incoming stream by redirecting it (or splitting it) to team members, third parties or DeFi apps in real time. You can read more about stream redirection and splitting here: https://help.superfluid.finance/en/articles/8907702-how-to-split-your-incoming-rpgf-grant\n\nSuperfluid also enabled smooth funds distribution, management and control for the Optimism team.\n\nThe entire community could benefit from transparent and easy to understand funding process, timeline and status (i.e. https://dune.com/0xkhmer/retropgf-3).\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x693ec27916302182746688d80015edb3a22bbc250035e9569e685bc3fab4f400",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728592349,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x082aba"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9997e7c0c02af2d4affa9b1dd4b3ea0f2de7407a1009cdc207f5620c6df9fd16",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSorPN6vJNX9LwRECnG3MpCpSr1Bk19xVcbM29frzpW8F",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Gravity DAO supports Optimism by designing and implementing frameworks and standards for decentralization of governance, especially in conflict management, trust creation, and leadership.\n\nWe support multiple teams in the collective with their capacity to coordinate nonviolently and transform the energy from conflicting situations into fuel for growth. \n\nWe have facilitated alternative dispute resolution and also evergreen educational content for individuals to continue their personal and professional development. \n\nOur created social infrastructure and tools are replicable, conceptually robust, minimal in governance overhead, and efficient in progressive decentralization. We consider our work to be long-term impactful for the collective because we are building good practices for common needs many groups face when building towards shared goals.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Gravity DAO is a public good project. We create content that is available and accessible to anyone interested, and that is forkable and adaptative to different scenarios. The people that have benefited the most from our infrastructure and tooling are the communities that get inspired by our frameworks, like Optimism, and the students, which we call Gravitons, who have taken our training and applied the set of gained skills in their life and in their participation on groups.\n\nOur work equips contributors with the necessary skills to participate gracefully in Web3 governance, facilitating continued improvement, informed engagement, and desired types of interaction. We develop humans and processes to foster better coordination in groups. \n\nWe are a small team, with 5 core contributors, and over 25 occasional ones. We want to increase the reach of our message and our capacity to grow, thinking that more people can benefit from our cutting-edge work on sociotechnical systems.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6dd054fa29e594d6d29a11ce4972529c4f311381563a9377c6148c4c1249ed39",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728465257,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02e380"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x38e5dbe11db74b3dc4958fbd9f372e88510aab754bb33e8cac17233e7270804a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSds16HXnbL5GLsZGPH7xVJu5SoJ39mvWuqjHJaWmb8EA",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We wanted to understand the rounds scoring mechanism given the totals and numbers reported did not make sense as an applicant.\n\nIn our round analysis. We extracted the raw excel data and and transformed them into formats typically used in data science (machine learning).\n\nIn doing so we were able to create a visual representation of the scoring for the round. We uncovered (known) shortcomings of the platform and were able to provide the collective information in an easy to understand format."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "I would say OP grants the lead Gonna.eth. After sharing my analysis, this led to a couple of initiatives that were since implemented in later rounds.\n\n* Sharing anon scores against each rubic\n* Making the individual reviewers scores public\n\nMy work was also referenced to support another members claim in the more topics ([Mission Request] Optimism Dominance in Yield-Bearing Assets (3 of 4) category) \n\nWhich was super cool to see.\n\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/mission-request-optimism-dominance-in-yield-bearing-assets-3-of-4/8440/22?u=1a35e1\n\n \n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x733820db80fd813c2c5cbe270bd40cde92688dd5e8fa39dbff581ec77b3e248e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728647898,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04bc"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x71ab640641b9c11726f5ad4f492ef9a8923a5ed16405588990c530c42956e0cc",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXvkM8XwYLM3sJDRP9cCLYVDbRRJTmbGqC5qfK5Aq2F96",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Retro Funding Review Tool enables application reviewers to ensure that all Retro Funding applications voted on by badge holders met eligibility criteria, prior to voting. The tool facilitated Retro Funding Round 4 & 5's application review process. Prior to CharmVerse, reviews were coordinated using complicated excel sheets where the core team spent countless hours in an error-prone process.  "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "All badge holder reviews for Retro Funding 4 and 5 were conducted on CharmVerse. The processes supported 416 applications with 271 applications approved. 46 Reviewers leveraged the platform to conduct their reviews. \n\nThe tool saved the core team countless hours. It streamline the process and save time for the 46 reviewers. Finally, all applicants benefited from the result of a better run process with higher transparency and reduced bias and errors. \n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7b3effe65451ceee36fe8f33553a2708dc56ae6ef6234f4b1691a7802a73b277",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727983313,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0460cc"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4e6dbab5761d07569675f5cbdb3b74e907e10520d25edfea0f189a1bdf1c96c7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmd4m2o3BoTRBxFq2BuGCegSCUjJBzuHT1oueeKps7ngrF",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Governed and collaborated through the DAO on subjects such as article creations, edits, and collaborative efforts in utilizing small funds as a team.\n\nThroughout team-building identified key flaws in beginning to onboard and critical content to accelerate the onboarding of non-web3 individuals in a way that is fun and impactful.\n\nCollaborated on entries such as publics goods, and article competitions in Kiwi."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Showed us how damaging half-assed members can be in early stages of DAO formation.\n\nElevated our perspectives and highlighted important conversations which brought the refining of our North Star into play, which has evolved into much more fun ideas and future projects.\n\nGetting knowledgable people in this niche is hard, but we found them.\n\nMaking it fun became easy once everyone was onboarded. \n\nImproved the process of UX concepts (from me the leader) to hard-hitting storytelling ideas that create immense value and spiritual resonance with core audience, public goods, and serving the greater community not just now but forever into the future as coals sparked and fueled what's become and amazing transformation of our tribe's mission to disrupt education."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7bb08fc74db92ca5ecae13b66ae39d86b2979b403bbceb4c919e3503cf12d8ae",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727800746,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x45f1"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x6195d9af3870606bae6af24349f6d0bad6f9fd6e869731969497db5b70ba7706",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaKpbZDgfX6q3dHFcUpEXkqKLPeEUUgufFcx6opgjv9cL",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Quisque vestibulum mattis malesuada. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Ut accumsan libero at nisi commodo maximus. Maecenas quis aliquet dui. Phasellus sed accumsan velit. Aenean venenatis faucibus massa quis rutrum. In placerat elit ac mauris rutrum, nec eleifend ex tempus. Aliquam sit amet ornare enim, quis auctor arcu. Praesent enim urna, sollicitudin non arcu at, dictum tempor felis."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Quisque vestibulum mattis malesuada. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia curae; Ut accumsan libero at nisi commodo maximus. Maecenas quis aliquet dui. Phasellus sed accumsan velit. Aenean venenatis faucibus massa quis rutrum. In placerat elit ac mauris rutrum, nec eleifend ex tempus. Aliquam sit amet ornare enim, quis auctor arcu. Praesent enim urna, sollicitudin non arcu at, dictum tempor felis."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7df82bbbefd2adf0b012d90c121816d9339a968ac037694d1d82f94b43d8de4a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728506918,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02ed94"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xabf0f7e4310068057f3d9eb6c9d04efc73c1a97cbb02edd173e8109c4011c845",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNUh3DphYReWHvXHqoRKr4Mb2H8NrVR6wrisAPnA6ECde",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "https://www.coinvise.co/casino-royal and   https://rounds.wtf/gadgets-gizmo/gadgets-round--my-good-value-gadgets-1\nMy channels Use Coinvise to gain channel member by pay OP and other Token\nHere's how I invite members to join my channel using OP tokens:\n- I set up a reward system on Coinvise where new members receive OP tokens for joining.\n- The amount of OP tokens offered is attractive enough to incentivize participation.\n- I create a unique invitation link through Coinvise that includes the token reward.\n- When someone clicks the link and joins, they automatically receive the promised OP tokens.\n- This creates a win-win situation: I gain new channel members, and they receive valuable OP tokens.\nBy using this method, I've seen a significant increase in channel membership and engagement. The OP token incentive has proven to be an effective way to attract and retain members who are interested in cryptocurrency and blockchain technology.\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "https://share.airstack.xyz/s/7Sy Fan Token is next step \n\nGrowth from Coinvise \nTotal claimed 50/50\nFARCASTER_JOIN_CHANNEL\t80\nFARCASTER_RECAST\t51\n\nand https://www.castsense.xyz/channel/gadgets-gizmo  performance Please check our Growth rate here"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7e49d1d4ba57abc9e052fb0d78b77427d02bfd918713b952e1dd5deccc41022d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728392343,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04bc"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x6d669359f5630dcb34f6e76a08620b9c1ed003e6af7f197c8f60c195df339611",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNnYyNfpTnpbGnuAYcG8rAYdQdH7Y3byM6daTtdPWyJT8",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "CharmVerse powered the end to end grants process of the Grants Council, servicing a total of 1,171 applications across Season 5 and 6. The process includes application intake, Council evaluation, communication & notifications, and milestone tracking. \n\nOver the past 12 months, monthly active users ranged from ~1k to 4.4k. In Cycle 19, NPS from finalist was 9/10, exceeding target of 7/10, indicating high satisfaction levels among applicants with the grants process. \n\n\"Special acknowledgment is due to the Charmverse team for their instrumental role in providing the necessary tools to facilitate the review process. Leveraging the rubric, workflow, and form tools for the first time, we achieved an impressive success rate of 97.2% out of 314 applications without errors and solved any issues on a 12-hour gap\" - Gonna, Grants Council Lead"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "We work closely with the Grants Council and constantly evolve the platform to meet their specific needs and ensure great grantee experience in a timely manner. Both the Grants Council and grant applicants benefit from a transparent and efficient grants process. \n\n\"We are delighted to announce that rubric comments are now integrated directly into your applications. Simply navigate to your application and check the sidebar to find scores for each rubric section, along with comments from reviewers. A huge thanks to the Charmverse team for implementing this feature so quickly.\" - Gonna, Grants Council Lead"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7ef9c10e51dc1d8e2931a007724317eef00193f65b4dd0a7064f24207a6bcf2b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728571785,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03a0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x635975abaa62dcca8b9838407171c9275cb1ee169caa9e106d3e5018c45afdc6",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVRj2kTYNZpKCJ56UsXQ5NMmUYEoBLPF2vKKRHmC8zBgs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Syntra simplifies key governance tasks for OptimismDAO Delegates, improving efficiency and decision-making. It also helps with the onboarding of new participants lowering the barrier to entry.\n\n\"### **A Day in the Life of an OptimismDAO Delegate with Syntra**\n\n- ***Efficient Proposal Creation***\n\t- *Delegates start their day by accessing a user-friendly dashboard and draft manager.*\n\t- *They can quickly draft proposals and use templates, cutting proposal creation time by 50%.*\n- ***Informed Decision Making***\n\t- *Syntra provides an overview of updated resources, ensuring delegates have all necessary context at their disposal.*\n\t- *Integration with OptimismDAO's calendar helping delegates stay up to date with community calls, office hours and seasons timelines.*\n- ***Cross-DAO Management***\n\t- *For delegates involved in multiple DAOs, Syntra provides a unified interface without the need of switching between platforms. This also lower the barrier to entry of external DAO actors*\"\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Syntra contributed to Optimism Governance since its  **private alpha release in late August**  and  **public alpha release in early September**.\n\n## Users:\n### OptimismDAO delegates\n-   **Newcomers**: Syntra lowered barriers to entry by simplifying proposal drafting, commenting, voting, and governance analysis.\n-   **Professional teams**: It streamlined internal coordination with role-based access and tracking features.\n\nAs of October 8th, Syntra has:\n\n-   **209 total logins**\n-   **33 MAU**: 33 active Optimism sessions since Sept (Month to date). \n\t- **Active**: at least 1 Draft created.\n-   Users from  **5 different countries** to date.\n-   Currently also being used by SEEDGov for drafting.\n\nMore information regarding activity is available in the [Google Drive link](https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1TZWtb_Q67hwqBHNGpgT4V7HocAs1LNKT?usp=sharing)."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8250aab51ed4cff1fa1d7729ef719a8ab0291ae587b1699a50c36f955db10119",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728582061,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0ce07d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb23033c01d75b52917aa5bd303b278d7920a43cb2664e28ac7f68b289dd26564",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbaQbUjSoSxuD3C8nKHiBjQswwqfdP2Nm1GFXUzpRRJwH",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "RetroPGF Hub serves as the central infrastructure and governance tool for Retro Funding, a vital element of the Citizens' House. It empowers the Optimism community to actively participate in governance, explore comprehensive information, and stay well-informed about all aspects of Retro Funding.\n\nOur platform offers detailed information on Retro Funding, including its foundational concepts, the historical context of each funding round, and in-depth insights into previously funded projects. This ensures governance participants have the knowledge they need to make informed decisions.\n\nAdditionally, we enhance community engagement by providing a space for feedback on builders' project ideas. This interaction fosters a continuous learning and improvement loop that benefits both the Optimism ecosystem and the builders contributing to it."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Several users, particularly new participants in the Retro Funding process, have greatly benefited from our infrastructure. Badgeholders, key in Retro Funding governance, are a primary group that benefits. Our platform enables them to easily participate, shape Retro Funding, and access critical project data, making research and discovery more efficient for governance participants within the Citizens' House.\n\nOur platform is also recognized as a trusted source for Retro Funding details, with referrals from platforms like retrofunding.optimism.io (Optimism Official) and optimism.curiahub.xyz (CuriaLabs), directing users to project details for each funding round. This streamlines access to key information for governance participants.\n\nUltimately, our platform supports governance within the Optimism ecosystem, benefiting individual users and the broader structure. Our infrastructure continues to strengthen the Citizens' House, enhancing its ability to effectively of Retro Funding."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8558a5ab3ec80516408f30d235c0f1a1bc69a4e2d8751d164ada3fc824afa7f6",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728478700,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03a0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x433a85a0ed1243fc2797f150fc4985e36a2487b7b9bbfa503084f0a6df4e4177",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVRj2kTYNZpKCJ56UsXQ5NMmUYEoBLPF2vKKRHmC8zBgs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Syntra simplifies key governance tasks for OptimismDAO Delegates, improving efficiency and decision-making. It also helps with the onboarding of new participants lowering the barrier to entry.\n\n\"### **A Day in the Life of an OptimismDAO Delegate with Syntra**\n\n- ***Efficient Proposal Creation***\n\t- *Delegates start their day by accessing a user-friendly dashboard and draft manager.*\n\t- *They can quickly draft proposals and use templates, cutting proposal creation time by 50%.*\n- ***Informed Decision Making***\n\t- *Syntra provides an overview of updated resources, ensuring delegates have all necessary context at their disposal.*\n\t- *Integration with OptimismDAO's calendar helping delegates stay up to date with community calls, office hours and seasons timelines.*\n- ***Cross-DAO Management***\n\t- *For delegates involved in multiple DAOs, Syntra provides a unified interface without the need of switching between platforms. This also lower the barrier to entry of external DAO actors*\"\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Syntra contributed to Optimism Governance since its  **private alpha release in late August**  and  **public alpha release in early September**.\n\n## Users:\n### OptimismDAO delegates\n-   **Newcomers**: Syntra lowered barriers to entry by simplifying proposal drafting, commenting, voting, and governance analysis.\n-   **Professional teams**: It streamlined internal coordination with role-based access and tracking features.\n\nAs of October 8th, Syntra has:\n\n-   **209 total logins**\n-   **33 MAU**: 33 active Optimism sessions since Sept (Month to date). \n\t- **Active**: at least 1 Draft created.\n-   Users from  **5 different countries** to date.\n-   Currently also being used by SEEDGov for drafting.\n\nMore information regarding activity is available in the [Google Drive link](https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1TZWtb_Q67hwqBHNGpgT4V7HocAs1LNKT?usp=sharing)."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x855e310f335efbaadb6b96b350aad53e4558b3e242a7f0e5aec8d8eee9a48f5d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728497012,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0487b7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb52fae07c897d3c5333af61143ca14d921eaa35d0969f478372cfb5bef1a07d6",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfBVTXbQEEbS6xvbfK32S7oeiEWVkcWHdJ5Y9EypiF1ef",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Testing a new social account for NFT whitelisting. We're collaborating with three talented designers.\nTesting a new social account for NFT whitelisting. We're collaborating with three talented designers.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Testing a new social account for NFT whitelisting. We're collaborating with three talented designers.\nTesting a new social account for NFT whitelisting. We're collaborating with three talented designers.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8aae5ac4b841e7fe11ab3975aa3aa9ac63f0c75402ee1a75ed1a2c413e6c7d7f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728281658,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x039550"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x59863655c166e8225c338ea40f37c4312bb5217bb605d47174c5e0143f6dc6c6",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmchuuvUYHPACWfJCUUZXVdiejqNm2MfgZrsK1veS6aX1a",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work provides insights into both treasury and governance data within Optimism. On the treasury side, we track historical treasury value, holdings, and transactions and provide month-over-month comparisons to help visualize trends. For governance, we display all proposals categorized by their status and offer a clear view of active voters. This allows users to stay informed about the overall health of Optimism\u2019s governance and financial ecosystem in an easy-to-understand way, ensuring transparency and helping drive informed decision-making."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work has benefited on-chain communities across EVM chains, particularly within the Superchain ecosystem, including Optimism, Base, and Celo. Since our solution is inherently free and easy to use, anyone can effortlessly create and track their on-chain communities on Remox. From project teams to community members, everyone benefits from our insights into treasury and governance, empowering them to make informed decisions and engage more actively in their ecosystems."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8c3f1effc7c02be58e8cd35799f4551563e9d66ec5c262d153c4ec26cff36417",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728011727,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xdd4c4d7d46e472314e5508cc9a781960b2053f6c62ef0b50e81a0e6ff91ca2b3",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTr1uEZDVLgd9a49or745Vbx612HNnAWcS4YKpvTyte5R",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8f97924e40314484a27409ffac10b321b8ee539982f073551ce9a92bc3852b85",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728510210,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2678"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9421ca676319001aa266d5c24626f2c4a8e7cfd07e58c0140524d0ee82609bac",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRdhq3uWzzNwEYbNGBsF5XS7KLedXx35rMEKgSEVfyZpy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "EAS is foundational in Retro Funding and governance processes, providing structured, verifiable attestations that enhance accountability, trust, and accelerate decision-making.\n\nIn Retro Funding, EAS is used to:\n- **Assign Unique Identifiers:** Provide unique IDs for all projects and organizations.\n- **Manage Metadata:** Capture and update project/org info.\n- **Record Applications:** Log project submissions to RF rounds.\n- **Track Application Status:** Record approvals/rejections of applications.\n- **Specify Rewards:** Detail reward amounts.\n\nEAS also supports governance roles and contributions by representing citizenship status separately from voting rights, issuing voting badges for Retro Rounds, attesting to contributors in retro rounds, and recognizing those who held governance roles like Grants Council members.\n\nView all schemas: https://docs.optimism.io/chain/identity/schemas\n\n*Note:* Archived schemas have been utilized for RetroPGF3, Season 4, and Optimist Profiles."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "EAS impacts all participants involved in the Retro Funding experience.\n\n**Governance Teams Overseeing Retro Funding**\nOP grants/governance teams rely on EAS for transparent and verifiable decision-making, ensuring accountability throughout the Retro Funding process. EAS enables them to operate more efficiently, experiment readily, build trust, and scale governance.\n\n**Retro Funding Participants**\nRF project creators, reviewers, and other participants use EAS when creating profiles, submitting applications, approving or rejecting projects, and updating metadata. EAS ensures these interactions are structured and verifiable for each step of the RF experience.\n\n**Governance Tooling & Analytic Providers**\nThese teams access EAS attestations to retrieve data, generate reports, and gain insights. These attestations make it easier to analyze RF activities and contribute to informed decision-making.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x94c15f9cc6de83b06303057ab5f43769cdb9cba192edc6a9ea95f9620c89d84b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728590769,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x082aba"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9777f615e1fda95e613efb1682b7a3bd901fb1df855e2142f9511e313113fdb7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSorPN6vJNX9LwRECnG3MpCpSr1Bk19xVcbM29frzpW8F",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Gravity DAO supports Optimism by designing and implementing frameworks and standards for decentralization of governance, especially in conflict management, trust creation, and leadership.\n\nWe support multiple teams in the collective with their capacity to coordinate nonviolently and transform the energy from conflicting situations into fuel for growth. \n\nWe have facilitated alternative dispute resolution and also evergreen educational content for individuals to continue their personal and professional development. \n\nOur created social infrastructure and tools are replicable, conceptually robust, minimal in governance overhead, and efficient in progressive decentralization. We consider our work to be long-term impactful for the collective because we are building good practices for common needs many groups face when building towards shared goals.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Gravity DAO is a public good project. We create content that is available and accessible to anyone interested, and that is forkable and adaptative to different scenarios. The people that have benefited the most from our infrastructure and tooling are the communities that get inspired by our frameworks, like Optimism, and the students, which we call Gravitons, who have taken our training and applied the set of gained skills in their life and in their participation on groups.\n\nOur work equips contributors with the necessary skills to participate gracefully in Web3 governance, facilitating continued improvement, informed engagement, and desired types of interaction. We develop humans and processes to foster better coordination in groups. \n\nWe are a small team, with 5 core contributors, and over 25 occasional ones. We want to increase the reach of our message and our capacity to grow, thinking that more people can benefit from our cutting-edge work on sociotechnical systems.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x94d5592911f44c89c08b3a95dcdd51c5e17de4e90f6e1a0d9b18f5d02cd0ebcb",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728628807,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9ecd6efdda076eafb3d2e18f4035d67b7ddffdb1ce38c7d294c9cf7df6862e0a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcX4Pot1Hhr3ZbbWe1Louw7Si4H4zab2myVHzo48wDTPs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x97116b25fb82e86270aaa402aa3759844d634d3234b0edcd15f0b58bcdac50dd",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728478691,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03a0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa690fdca02418a248404ff6ebf1ad18ca3bb08a6b2f75329f6167934bae9f32f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmesR4PMqamyqND8pXFRUUJg5i2fNvGtEGZLsaCp4h7fGT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We conducted 2 researches that served as a reference for measuring participation in Governance:\n\nToken House Participation and Incentives: Season 5 (Cycles 16-19), captures essential data on delegate participation and provides a condensed overview of governance during Season 5. It analyzes the Collective's evolution, highlighting significant findings such as a increase in mission proposals and a rise in active delegate participation, while noting a decline in mission approval rates, which may suggest a more rigorous selection process. \n\nBig Picture: The Grants Council, documents the evolution of the Grants Council, emphasizing its transition from a governance experiment to a vital structure within Optimism. This report details the Council's efforts to streamline grant distribution, enhance transparency, and improve fund management, offering a chronological and quantifiable perspective on its activities, structure, budget allocations, and results over the seasons. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Token House Participation and Incentives served as a guide for the Foundation to determine the Retro Delegate Rewards for Season 5. While the Grants Council report was included as part of the govNERDs contribution path. \n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x97309e9ea07e7b0a1c964e0d77c2cf097b943175ee12a2b63ff257c660adf9f1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728465436,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2c23"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x34c3b644a6fd8378c7517dcad9b2b860286d3c4f31f64716fbece7da6bee6b48",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPkQAZxvCdtfdh19yn9RbAe3peTPALQdS4d1X3DfoUEAk",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Many people don\u2019t often think about whom they delegate their tokens to, or whether they have delegated them at all. Our frame reminds users of the delegation option, allowing them to review and choose a different delegate. \n\nEverything happens within the Farcaster app, with no need to go outside of it, making the process more convenient. The frame makes delegation easy and encourages people to think about governance.\n\nThe tool is in the form of a frame, which is a Farcaster invention. It\u2019s essentially a link preview on steroids. Frames can include buttons and text fields that allow users to interact directly with them. A frame is basically a mini-app within Farcaster."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Citizens and delegates active on Farcaster have benefited the most from the Optimism Delegate Frame. \n\nDelegates can share pre-filled frames with their information, making it easy for users to delegate to them with just a few clicks. This system allows delegates to promote themselves while reminding citizens to check their current delegate and switch if they choose. \n\nSince these frames are shared publicly on Farcaster, they help raise awareness about Optimism governance and encourage more users to engage with the delegation process."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x98d3c3725665e50341f2814df8df074fc73bbcc3e92a89663cc2d9f2ee8c5e09",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727871713,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x4a7f"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd0ec3a945cfc36885729b53b7f7d2e362fd622850cf682cac4591fa7831b206c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmagUYEaHqRCjba7EkU69gLhkHYdvqvTGonJsff7WrF6RD",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "As an active delegate above top 100, we have missed out on Retro Delegate Rewards in the past seasons, however we have over 90% voting participation since we started participation in March 2023. We actively communicate our voting rationales via our notion (https://daoplomats.notion.site/Database-03940ef86fdc40c3a02df62665f59efd) and delegate platform (https://gov.optimism.io/t/daoplomats-delegate-communication-thread/8061)\n\nWe have participated in public discourse around governance with our delegate profile (https://gov.optimism.io/u/jengajojo/summary) as well as created mission requests: \n1. https://gov.optimism.io/t/sponsorship-request-empowering-small-active-delegates/8434\n2. https://gov.optimism.io/t/ready-to-vote-governance-mentorship-program-mission-request/7315"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Due to our active participation in proposal making, voting, and communicating rationale we have been able to attract more tokens holders to delegate to us by 260%(https://optimism.curiahub.xyz/delegates/0xc2490d220419acdced68428ac413c8483d08d1ab), thus increasing the total supply of tokens participating in onchain voting."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9a9f1e790340c30db4cd8f6f5a0c0de3034e3f9ff7bd6accfc20254c3efb7117",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728650618,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04bc"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd3eef1b3c5eb7bc4dbdf0dd0548662379260dd04d0c9d7243d73bf4084182c03",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUujRJvvH33WXLirxvz1nTGA7CbWR2RqVfXSuNzdkUNuV",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The SUNNYs is an awards show designed to honor the outstanding achievements of Superchain builders. Builders from all across live Superchain mainnets are eligible. Winners will receive prizes from a pool of 540K OP, along with unique stat cards, and more. CharmVerse is one of the teams that built the SUNNYs. CharmVerse team created the SUNNYs website as well as the custom registration webapp that create new OP Project Attestations. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The website and webapp provided applicants an easy way to apply for the SUNNYs. 1k+ applicants successfully applied for the SUNNY with almost zero issues reported. The webapp also facilitated the creation of OP Project Attestations. \n\nThe SUNNY Awards created 1464 Attestations. The SUNNY was launched on 8/21/2024. Prior to that date, there was 1007 Project Attestations. The SUNNY increased the OP Project Attestations by 145%. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9c0cd85857925fe425f49f0da31b37b3647bbd51ebe96dc9039e778cea3b8ba9",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727945011,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0794e1"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x245eaf718d61859fe21b8a875ce25be558d51c1dfb996576195b3bdfe2a4a22a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYcV7GwXfgaDNe6GdxA3vHTvwQMotnwEMzERgmHGFMzLs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Lawyerd's platform empowered the Optimism community to report scams, fraud, and brand violations, significantly improving transparency and accountability within the ecosystem. By integrating with the OP Stack, Lawyerd enabled more efficient community-driven governance, allowing participants to flag violations, protect their favorite projects, and earn rewards for contributing to ecosystem safety. Our platform actively supported decentralized governance by reducing fraud and scams that harm community trust, making Optimism a safer and more secure environment for builders and users alike."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The most significant beneficiaries of Lawyerd's tooling are the Optimism governance participants, including protocol developers, brand owners, and community members. Developers benefit from reduced risks of scams undermining their projects, and brands are better protected against counterfeiters. Community members benefit by being incentivized to participate actively in governance by reporting violations, thereby creating a safer and more transparent environment across the Optimism ecosystem."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9ee9ba5865be97b5cb961ee395411c509f01afac492597553a76adc9ce91cbf1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728506318,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04f5b3"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x7bb04c21a2395ecffb22dbf628ce9e419d416e25e0bfd8985455965cab03513a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfJPz4MrgHhDd2iBBW5bYqibdP741oKewHCeLcMVRcoD6",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "https://snapshot.org/#/bullcasso.eth/proposal/0x15796b11a75b64f050ec0e8713c36811c53279c8415b880b81bb9289ff8b2473\n\nHello normally our first collection is bulcasso but this collection is removed from opensea because of picasso.fr But our first proposal get 600 vote and i ask we wanna create a game which chain do you prefer.\n\nwith 540 Vote they chose base network and zora get only 68 vote.\n\nThen we develop our projects on base network.\n\nAfter that we create a new ios game - but people change their game-center names with .eth or basenames or free .uni (uniswap names)\n\n\nThen we change our project name as vrnouns and we develop a game named bitfight.\n\nIn this game people earning daily points and \n\nwe sent 15$ reward to top 10\nor 50$ to top 3.\nhttps://snapshot.org/#/vrnouns.eth \nwe decide this using snapshot.\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Normally we get 20.000$ grand from optimism but we purchased 2 NOUNS for understanding and practicing proposal, voting and all governance systems. Our 2. grand will be huge because we finally can manage this fund using our council.\n\nAlso our game name is bitfigt and people are collecting bitcoin - satoshi.\n\nAfter cbBTC we can send peoples bitcoins directly on base network.\n\nhttps://x.com/yasinaktimur/status/1804831649516884267\nhttps://x.com/mehmetturk20_/status/1796966924238123414\nhttps://x.com/avaxjunior/status/1796970722406846854"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa1bbe8d4c7a75991398525219c80619ea6aed4d09142358ab95436b9598fdb33",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728591730,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x3f57"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xc3ca5978dabcc0296eaa693a01e506a1fad27062e270c10409d21dcf5d2b809b",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbTpJT1LmeLoZ3t6tQNuwsHLabMWsJP4Kbzxbhxgeiujm",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Developer Advisory Board (DAB) was reelected in Season 6 with a provisional budget of 90,000 OP. [Our charter can be found in the initial budget proposal](https://gov.optimism.io/t/zach-obront-developer-advisory-board-operating-budget/8141), and includes supporting the Optimism ecosystem as follows:\n\n1. Help to ensure the safety of protocol upgrades. We do this by both (a) explicitly approving upgrades before they are allowed to move to a vote and (b) providing plain English summaries of all protocol upgrades to educate other voters.\n\n2. Support the Grants Council by providing detailed technical feedback on all Mission Requests, Mission Applications, and grant milestones.\n\n3. Bring an additional technical perspective to thinking about the vision of the OP ecosystem and what needs to happen to get there.\n\nMore details can be found in our [Internal Operating Procedures](https://gov.optimism.io/t/developer-advisory-board-s6-internal-operating-procedures/8558)."
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "- Provided detailed feedback on [139 mission requests](https://wbnns.notion.site/Developer-Advisory-Board-Impact-11acf4706b47808f8421c409b4c102c6?pvs=4) thus far (105 of which are within the round eligibility period), to aid in evaluation by the Grants Council. The GC Lead has provided an NPS score of 10/10 based on the value of our contributions.\n- Reviewed the Granite Hardfork, formally approved it, and prepared an [extensive and comprehensive non-technical summary](https://gov.optimism.io/t/upgrade-proposal-10-granite-network-upgrade/8733/21) to support other voters.\n- Provided feedback to the Foundation on important projects such as the Decentralization Roadmap and long term Product Vision.\n- Conducted multiple community calls throughout Season 6, [creating an open forum](https://gov.optimism.io/t/developer-advisory-board-feedback-ideas-thread/8580) to get feedback and ideas from the community."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa20d1b6a8932ad32d8ca9e2ffb3c581c524fecf552c20ea8760382d35987acc8",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728393590,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04e4b6"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0baa82ebced95af57e0f5d115c173ec221fadf41b3eabe76354a09793dcf6ea7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPHh9ZMNhoDLmVkoQJCyq1jhHh3HCc9vFptpmAxxdF8pH",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "EVM Explorer's analytics work provides valuable insights into the influence of smart contract behavior on governance processes, enhancing transparency and understanding of the impact of smart contracts on Optimism Governance.\n\nSmart Contract Performance: Analyzing the performance and usage of smart contracts within the Optimism network to understand their impact on governance processes. This includes tracking metrics such as the number of interactions with specific contracts, the frequency of transactions, and the distribution of contract usage across different governance-related functions.\n\nGovernance-relevant Token Balances: Tracking and analyzing token balances that are relevant to governance, such as voting tokens or tokens used for delegating authority. This analysis sheds light on the distribution of voting power, governance-related events, and stakeholder engagement in governance decision-making.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The analytics work by EVM Explorer on smart contract behavior in Optimism Governance benefits various ecosystem stakeholders. Active governance participants gain insights into smart contract performance and token balances, aiding informed decision-making and effective participation. Governance teams leverage detailed analytics to assess governance mechanisms, identify areas for enhancement, and tailor strategies. Developers benefit from understanding user interactions with contracts, leading to improved contract efficiency. Token projects find value in analytics on token balances and distribution for assessing engagement and governance mechanisms. Researchers benefit from comprehensive analytics, deepening insights into governance processes and contributing to the governance community. Overall, EVM Explorer's analytics enhance transparency, understanding, and efficiency in Optimism Governance, benefiting stakeholders across the ecosystem.\n\n\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xab39b725ae275ff8055702e58441f053d71967ffc9686ec9201bba813b301c67",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728331661,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02edff"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xdd4757682af7760dac7dc5e5072ab3e1b434e295ecf81ecdccd48def0fdb5544",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNvB3VubMr5uT7BggkVTaRv7fiqLx1CXFVsBF1yXd52hc",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process.",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Quote from Emily, OP Foundation:\n\n\"The Foundation is using it [Attest Fest] for issuing voting badges and Citizen badges to Citizens and Guest Voters, as well as issuing all the attestations for governance roles each season.\"\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The OP foundation and Retro Funding have been some of the most active Attest Fest users through retropgf rounds 3, 4 and 5.\n\nAttest Fest has been used to support various aspects of the retro funding process, including batch creating attestations for guest voters, citizens as well as assigning governance roles.\n\nAttest Fest makes the process of creating those attestations simple by allowing uploading of CSV files from spreadsheets with attestation data."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xaf42f2fe431a46150a141f94653e6654e6e9e7d06e676a367dceaf1161ffd98c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728372728,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x039550"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x94016b6e589438a969c2daf953d320b3d1aae1b5e1b4553fff7944cfb71c16be",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmchuuvUYHPACWfJCUUZXVdiejqNm2MfgZrsK1veS6aX1a",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work provides insights into both treasury and governance data within Optimism. On the treasury side, we track historical treasury value, holdings, and transactions and provide month-over-month comparisons to help visualize trends. For governance, we display all proposals categorized by their status and offer a clear view of active voters. This allows users to stay informed about the overall health of Optimism\u2019s governance and financial ecosystem in an easy-to-understand way, ensuring transparency and helping drive informed decision-making."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work has benefited on-chain communities across EVM chains, particularly within the Superchain ecosystem, including Optimism, Base, and Celo. Since our solution is inherently free and easy to use, anyone can effortlessly create and track their on-chain communities on Remox. From project teams to community members, everyone benefits from our insights into treasury and governance, empowering them to make informed decisions and engage more actively in their ecosystems."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb00d7b92c5f208017e0a83939356704108b85208d0213522b2d305eb95bbda56",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728376698,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa3aaaa228a93e92c045e02872dd066aa035b6235fb2c8e0b4fae3942922fa00e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcX4Pot1Hhr3ZbbWe1Louw7Si4H4zab2myVHzo48wDTPs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb17330c9a36eb865bb15d2b989e1d30a6844397660324eb2a8e13fa6b761dc49",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728543314,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04af44"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x770053a5a51df4d8c261b17904ed109fe65e80ceb5b007d4baa77f5459f88899",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfX4PRL8eBJmvDDAavE35ERFb6U1trcmRLMpBW4QU83YQ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We have created templates for creating frames for delegating tokens. By doing so, we attracted more users from Warpcast and made it easier for delegates. More: https://x.com/zefirium_crypto/status/1795062923720573226 "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The tool is most useful for delegates who are actively creating content on Warpcast. Our tool also attracted good organic growth in Optimism, whose chain we were the first to implement in FrameMaker, and our template was the first to create a delegation pool in OP. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb1d98a9f4a3b156ad8464a33955c7c8ae3b77806f05061b83b0a407f09b661a7",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728652168,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4efa19fb904485120b596e1346ed90435e790b4d52dc4d5c2f2d68fce227ba46",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVVPmW4XhkH4UFJ7xwnWZstqvMbx9yU7XPSJdYYH6LHX3",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "- Data transparency within the Collective: The Optimism Collective is one of the largest DAOs, with new aretfacts being released continuously. This includes information on committees & councils, list of important initiatives, links to governance, list of voters, etc. Through EIP-4824, we have created an onchain source of truth on the Optimism Collective. New artifacts can be continuously added to the Collective's daoURI, making it comprehensive over time. \n\n- Better visibility for DAO-related EAS schemas on Optimism: Currently, there is no place DAO-related EAS schemas can be listed, along with a description and additional context. We built a proof-of-concept DAO Schema Registry, to enhance the discoverability and usage of DAO/governance related EAS schemas. \n\n- "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "- Governance tooling providers: Tools like Snapshot, Snapshot X and a vareity of other governance tools utilize EIP-4824 to handle DAO metadata. \n\n- New participants of the OP Collective: The daoURI is a useful piece of infrastructure for anyone who'd like to find info at a single location. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb1de39ce257f0ad3a4c063dd9096a9e06ca0ae758bbc5e8f53a112e2b878f054",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727844582,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0d0c1b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x64b2d5353a4613264f4f991b2ab33d9cdb872eac3458a4da56f704f613ef7eba",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVbnrnsiBtZkdBJArRvKLmL3xCBW2pH6RRq7MV2Qc68Rb",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Code of Conduct Council has significantly contributed to improving the enforcement of governance standards within Optimism. By taking over the processing of Code of Conduct violation reports, the Council has streamlined enforcement, removing the burden from Token House delegates and allowing them to focus on higher-level governance matters. During Season 5, no Code of Conduct issues were escalated to the Token House, despite multiple submissions occurring during this period. \nIn Season 5, the Council implemented clear processes for handling disputes, including a transparent reporting system that publishes enforcement decisions. Also, confirming and denying grant clawback requests from the grants council smooth lined the process in how teams that hadn\u2019t met their milestones would be treated. Further, initiatives like GravityDAO\u2019s conflict resolution training demonstrated the Council\u2019s commitment to preventative measures, reducing the likelihood of violations in the first place.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Council helped foster a more accessible and fair enforcement process that clearly laid out the framework and operations around possible community violations. As this was the first cohort involved in the Code of Conduct, all members had to also reflect not only on the duties initially assigned by the original proposal, but also the potential for improvement and limitations of the system established and its Internal Operating Procedures.\nThe impact and want for something like this was proven apparent by the Council\u2019s reapproval, this time with a new budget of up to 6000 OP per member (vs 3000 OP in S5). This shift has improved governance efficiency, ensuring timely and impartial enforcement of community standards. The introduction of preventative measures, such as conflict resolution training, further supports long-term community well-being. Through these, the Council has played a crucial role in maintaining Optimism\u2019s integrity and promoting sustainable governance practices.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb9992336e3a139a42a1837e4ccec4865ff4ca422c15944cc8881b0173a733186",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728549340,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x245d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9fc2cc4c5406c4ba3279c6d1e7b0c9251b3025d964747a4130bdde51b4cf8282",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZVqa3vYSMCkYbDcW1vie11UqLTz4byt2TUZtR2Gwn665",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Our tool boosts governance participation by displaying active proposals in social feeds, making it easier for Delegates and Citizens to stay informed and participate in Optimism Governance. By integrating the alerts into mainstream platforms, our widget improves the accessibility of Optimism\u2019s governance infrastructure."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of our project are Delegates and Citizens involved in Optimism Governance. They benefit from instant access to active proposals directly in their social feeds, allowing them to stay informed and ensure they don\u2019t miss important votes."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb9fcfe5ee65a24d8eddf57ec2cee00aa1ed45fcb6b579a5e8ad733ae69684c37",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728021896,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xde8ad8e2993e0f8c6e160b3ae0b6ae82e1b59eaca14036555ac398f08ec8fda9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcX4Pot1Hhr3ZbbWe1Louw7Si4H4zab2myVHzo48wDTPs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xbedc69225f8cb662603ce87bc33d6583f266115afa1c609641396efd78547af1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728588596,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02ef50"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcf371331b430edd39877790edd709a5840e401b33b4ed69c339627088a5fa964",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmeYTr9hpMSbZvsaC1mcJsWe8krAQZQBJPcvaoYb63p5Qm",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "There have been 23 community governance calls in this impact period. In addition, we have had two \"speed dating\" sessions, mission request workshops, and other AMAs.\n\nThe calls have been a key place to discuss *everything* that has happened in governance during that time, and calls usually get 40-50 key participants from Optimism Governance.\n\nA small sampling of topics/guests in this impact period:\n* Jing presenting and Q&A on the Superchain vision\n* Base Governance team Rowan & Saemi discussing Base's participation\n* Ben Jones presenting Blockspace Charters\n* Kelvin Fitchner Granite Network Upgrade AMA\n* Justine with a Season 6 Governance AMA\n* Launamu preseting Impact Metrics Garden\n* PaperImperium discussing a proposal on accelerated governance decentralization\n* Roberto Bayardo (Base) presenting Fjord/Ecotone upgrades\n* Emily presenting Guest Voter Participation\n* Jonas presenting multiple Retro Funding rounds"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "These calls are the critical space for all governance participants to become informed, ask questions, and discuss every current issue across the Token House and the Citizen's House.\n\nBy condensing all of this information into 1 hour and by bringing experts into the discussion, Delegates and Citizens are able to participate more effectively across every area of Optimism Governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xbf041e869e3f9c23ef014f62ccfafe3847d9f58e3a8092897f48ecd10f63441a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728542919,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04af44"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd4c97c2fbfc1fb38f8a2000d05587ca5e59ba407d23955ef7c717c402c2e4a47",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfX4PRL8eBJmvDDAavE35ERFb6U1trcmRLMpBW4QU83YQ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We have created templates for creating frames for delegating tokens. By doing so, we attracted more users from Warpcast and made it easier for delegates. More: https://x.com/zefirium_crypto/status/1795062923720573226 "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The tool is most useful for delegates who are actively creating content on Warpcast. Our tool also attracted good organic growth in Optimism, whose chain we were the first to implement in FrameMaker, and our template was the first to create a delegation pool in OP. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc32de1045bf865475be1ea9e686b18195d977d0de65456d22b809dd4ccbd9edb",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728379101,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02eaec"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0971cd089d681dec089e25333fc77be8572e18b4074f6946c3ae5cce6c1bd1b0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmd3EXxAUXpeZHLJhwje5D1jgp3WLaPh27voXSj3civDP5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "THIs is a test\nTHIs is a test\nTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a test"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "THIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a testTHIs is a test"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc761e4b8012b1d9cc11671d29bd8df5b39eb04c2d75319954023f59bf580aa9e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727871949,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x6f577ad3b13223175659b2a0fb4635798a23de75d198bbbf170eb9e41bedd473",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcX4Pot1Hhr3ZbbWe1Louw7Si4H4zab2myVHzo48wDTPs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "This is an example statement: \n\nLorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc85d77363edb2e7ca33ee0f5a7bf4dc2b936813c562dd280651964cd451ccd2f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728526492,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02ef50"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x7b133c88d8e14ca916068487ac2c10f41f8c89a3133179f0f6e4d0d61273b02d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTS4DBM46DCZeHPaCKFQkP3AhgG6d6gAmafqHDxmhZP3f",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We have created a comprehensive analysis of Optimism Badgeholder's onchain activity vs a control group of active non-Badgeholders. In particular, we looked at transaction activity across chains, involvement in social apps (Farcaster, Lens, Friendtech), participation in other DAOs (Arbitrum, Uniswap, ENS) and the deployment of smart contracts and NFTs. \n\nSomething to note: although it is true that not all citizens use their Badgeholder address for other onchain activity, we found that a significant amount did and we discuss the implications of this constraint in the report.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Foundation. This work was requested directly by the Foundation in order to get a better understanding of Optimism Badgeholders vs \u201cnormal\u201d Ethereum users. In their own words: \u201cIn order to confidently expand the Citizenry, we need to have a baseline understanding of the current Badgeholder group. Our goal is to get a better understanding of the Badgeholder group based on their onchain activity compared with the onchain activity of other active Optimism/Ethereum users.\u201d\n\nIn addition, the entire Optimism Collective has benefitted from the transparency provided by this publicly available work. It's open source nature sets the stage for others to conduct further research and expand upon our results. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc8c6459df927aff870c2bf7fabf99fce0484a7f48722819a11d0de0e88ec2742",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728282132,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x039550"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x502e0949e09de5f3c2e2925bf0e1542d85d373ba852e52cbfe5162a67fc13e8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmchuuvUYHPACWfJCUUZXVdiejqNm2MfgZrsK1veS6aX1a",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work provides insights into both treasury and governance data within Optimism. On the treasury side, we track historical treasury value, holdings, and transactions and provide month-over-month comparisons to help visualize trends. For governance, we display all proposals categorized by their status and offer a clear view of active voters. This allows users to stay informed about the overall health of Optimism\u2019s governance and financial ecosystem in an easy-to-understand way, ensuring transparency and helping drive informed decision-making."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work has benefited on-chain communities across EVM chains, particularly within the Superchain ecosystem, including Optimism, Base, and Celo. Since our solution is inherently free and easy to use, anyone can effortlessly create and track their on-chain communities on Remox. From project teams to community members, everyone benefits from our insights into treasury and governance, empowering them to make informed decisions and engage more actively in their ecosystems."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xca01d21ca2c506d6f87fbf3e04b1cfe88db5f25b6fa9f8b238f507068b28840c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728494284,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x08aeb4bc57b33ae52cea98678c32d73456572b548760f7470da1631f85083645",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaSpvLBDr1hzD5cDfGWBztHoSJHfRJC2WZUHDMW2HpHDU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analysis measures the participation and behavior of Badgeholders in the Superchain ecosystem, specifically focusing on their transaction activities across networks like OP Mainnet, Base, Zora, and Mode. It also examines their engagement in decentralized applications (DEXs), token transfers, and social platforms like Farcaster. \n\nA key insight is the relatively low activity level of Badgeholders compared to Non-Badgeholders, particularly in areas like DEX trading and smart contract deployment. Additionally, the analysis tracks how Badgeholders' preferences for Ethereum transactions and limited cross-chain activity impact their overall engagement with Optimism's governance processes. \n\nThis helps identify where governance structures may need to be adjusted to include better and activate Badgeholders, ensuring their participation grows alongside the broader ecosystem.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Collective has benefitted most from this analysis, gaining valuable insights into Badgeholder behavior that inform strategies to increase engagement. For example, understanding that Badgeholders are more active on Ethereum but less engaged with smart contract deployment helps the Collective target these users with specific governance initiatives. \n\nFurthermore, the findings around Farcaster connections show the importance of social engagement within this group, which can shape future governance outreach and participation efforts. The insights have also helped governance teams refine their strategies for promoting cross-chain activity and diversifying user engagement. This research will also guide the future selection of new Badgeholders for the Citizen House by identifying gaps and ensuring the House becomes more inclusive and representative of the entire user profile within the Collective, promoting a well-rounded governance structure.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xca6c99e3082bc77e9ce2b03f1b1fb1fbb7c9323cc5c014c7beeed3f13891c4df",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728662114,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x077495"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x64eebc108ee38c7fbd238444fba5b8512aae5e44668b2e3d4ebc9891d01a1a2d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPZ5R7FJo59owwAzkGn9Z4GWRrbHiP4fseiouZm9h4pZ2",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We developed Pairwise for RF3, and introduced categories to make the impact measurement in the Retro Funding more organic and manageable.\nIn RF3, 185 users engaged, 27 badgeholders using their key\nIn RF4, we expanded into a community-wide experiment using pseudonymous voting with zk-tech. This allowed all stakeholders\u2014badgeholders, token holders, recipients, and delegates\u2014to participate freely without pressure and promote project discovery. Here you can find the final results, and our blog conclusions for more details on our outcomes.\nThe feedback from RF4 was very positive, leading to our invitation to build together with Optimism for RF5. For this round, we developed a star rating system, enabling participants to assign stars to projects before comparing them. This system grouped projects into tiers, significantly reducing the number of comparisons required.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main target when developing the product were badgeholders, who now can use Pairwise, to rank the Retro Funding projects in a fun way that promotes project discovery. However, the entire Optimism community, including delegates, token holders, and recipients, also gained through their participation in the Pairwise Retro Funding experiment, offering them the chance to discover impactful projects and bring more visibility to emerging initiatives. Projects benefited from increased exposure to potential users. Pairwise also sparks discussions  by comparing its results to official ones, fostering deeper insights and driving more meaningful participation and progress to decentralization.\nTo incentivize engagement, we distributed 4,000 OP as rewards giving a 100OP to 40 lucky winners, 10 on each stakeholder group participating in Pairwise."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xca91efd33f6449174e49f67dd9fb9fcbc8194760fc8c04af6bd3de89c19b412a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728572025,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03a0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa690fdca02418a248404ff6ebf1ad18ca3bb08a6b2f75329f6167934bae9f32f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmesR4PMqamyqND8pXFRUUJg5i2fNvGtEGZLsaCp4h7fGT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We conducted 2 researches that served as a reference for measuring participation in Governance:\n\nToken House Participation and Incentives: Season 5 (Cycles 16-19), captures essential data on delegate participation and provides a condensed overview of governance during Season 5. It analyzes the Collective's evolution, highlighting significant findings such as a increase in mission proposals and a rise in active delegate participation, while noting a decline in mission approval rates, which may suggest a more rigorous selection process. \n\nBig Picture: The Grants Council, documents the evolution of the Grants Council, emphasizing its transition from a governance experiment to a vital structure within Optimism. This report details the Council's efforts to streamline grant distribution, enhance transparency, and improve fund management, offering a chronological and quantifiable perspective on its activities, structure, budget allocations, and results over the seasons. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Token House Participation and Incentives served as a guide for the Foundation to determine the Retro Delegate Rewards for Season 5. While the Grants Council report was included as part of the govNERDs contribution path. \n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcac3a36df1b78675e41c5732cba722d494f0b55f0fc4a34128a1a7f2359c7a3e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727822307,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0d265f"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf56d0c4a0fe51365ed86630bf38313dfa1bc8a6e907baa66506f54d28699d820",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcTa8MTLYQz7sQyDrtjQLQzejxiMeV4vkggZkpoFWygh7",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "From September 2023 to Jul 2024, I facilitated Optimism ecosystem growth by:\n\nAssisting ~1000 users in claiming airdrops, 70% new to Optimism\nEducating users on Optimism's governance and ecosystem\nExpanding the governance participant pool\nWidening OP token distribution\nBuilding trust through transparent assistance\n\nVerifiable via Twitter DMs, emails, and on-chain transactions: https://optimistic.etherscan.io/token/0x4200000000000000000000000000000000000042?a=0x6b07602DbaACFd95d4a3A358438e39275538cc76"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "My work improved Optimism's governance by:\n\nExpanding the participant base, enhancing decentralization\nCreating a more informed voter pool through education\nIncreasing token distribution, potentially reducing voting power concentration\nMaking governance more accessible to newcomers\nFostering active engagement in governance processes\nBuilding trust in the ecosystem, encouraging long-term participation\nGenerating grassroots growth through network effects\n\nThis grassroots effort has strengthened Optimism's governance foundation by broadening and educating the participant base."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcb117e301049a66be57752f114abd6e74cd83cee1f30b36d07a259f75629bc04",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727850326,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x055ae7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x00857080059ebdd4f252fc921094498fc4025959df7d48785482790385b0e6f3",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXm5uYv5NkkpUSALghjjLepkXJRuaqeur26keyJ8A4Zc8",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Delegates are the cornerstone of Optimism's governance system. Active and well-informed delegates lead to resilient and sound governance. However, delegates need to process a lot of information and often find it challenging to stay up-to-date. We are humans after all.\n\nTo help delegates stay active and well-informed, our team launched Tribuni\u2014a free Telegram mini-app built exclusively for delegates. Tribuni sends quality AI-generated proposal summaries, vote reminders, and OP forum activity digests directly via Telegram. This ensures that delegates never miss a vote or an important discussion within the OP ecosystem, as long as they're connected to Telegram."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "People managing 28 OP delegate profiles use Tribuni.\n\nInstitutional Delegates:\njuanbug from pgov.eth\nlbchase from Blockchain@USC: 0x995013b47ef3a2b07b9e60da6d1fff8fa9c53cf4\nVarit from curia-delegates.eth\nAlex Duckworth from franklindao.eth, 0x070341aa5ed571f0fb2c4a5641409b1a46b4961b\nTjark from PoolCollective: 0x3d2d722b443a5cae8e41877bb7cd649f3650937c\nCharlie Ambrose from anthiaslabs.eth\nCallen from wintermutegovernance.eth\nTnorm from Gauntlet: 0x11cf2f033b079fbb195425bfcb7d5dac4db2d752\nKrzysztof Urba\u0144ski from delegate.l2beat.eth\nPumbi from SEED latam: joxes.eth\nCole and others from 404gov.eth\nStanley from Purdue: 0x8ccde64d05a7677d80a5960cb75fb8de486cf98d\nKerem Talha Oral from itublockchain.eth\nDerrick Cui from calcblockchain.eth\nShoji from tanegov.eth\n\nIndividual Delegates:\natlantropa.eth\nbrichis.eth\nlaunamu.eth\nopmichael.eth\nsovereignsignal.eth\nliliop.eth\nvote.ytocin.eth\nolimpio.eth\n0xdonpepe.eth\nFujiAR: 0x66946def4ba6153c500d743b7a5febfc1654d6bd\nkatiegarcia.eth\nmattgov.eth\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd1616c95b99f6b04b37a2113aaac75131ee19ec9cc5f028d2a57127419b560e2",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727965944,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2615"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x95d1e34612d2b54fab791ba3c1e2c47afaff4bd205227410ea680631d543fe59",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTViynzJ3ujBZhHta1XtucZBNvyiBVFHU5kGZxpkEywGb",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "In collaboration with OSO, Passport XYZ's Humanity scores were used to better understand the likelihood of real humans that were interacting with projects over the last year. The goal was to determine which projects were driving spam/bot traffic versus which projects were driving real users to the Optimism ecosystem. \n\nThese metrics and the analysis was used in the RPGF4 voting and review process, improving the understanding and (we believe) the outcome for voters by informing which projects were driving real humans, and organic users to the collective versus which were just bringing short term bots or spam users to the network (often low value and transient)."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our infrastructure and tooling has benefited the Badgeholder community the most, through our support of the RPGF rounds. Although we have made humanity proofs available via Attestations for nearly a year now on Optimism, the real value of this work has come from the inclusion and integration with the badgeholder experience (and collaboration with OSO) when reviewing and voting for projects to receive rewards."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd264c3fe17c32401c69449b04efe9efa9d83dacea99272cb4ae4fb3cfa274087",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728418552,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0cc2f2"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb0461cec7cf455071ff6454118624bf8aa57beecf7002e92a1c30a581c0695db",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPymb9tFk1WW2t2gS8XbBdw3SxZiqNQCDymUsDiMMdNwn",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We measure various aspects of the Optimism Token House to capture how susceptible it is to multiple risk factors we identify. These risk factors are (RF1) voter apathy, (RF2) high governance token liquidity, (RF3) large treasury, (RF4) inadequate configuration, (RF5) centralization, and (RF6) code uncertainties. For each of these risk factors, we identify multiple empirical measures that let us assess how vulnerable a DAO is. Note that we do this analysis not only for the Optimism Token House but also for another 25 DAOs in the Ethereum ecosystem.\n \nWe further created a data set of attacks on DAOs in the past, but none are directly related to Optimism Governance.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Our analytical work benefits two groups. The first group is protocols that use a DAO for their governance. They can use the dataset of attacks, as well as the empirical measures we identify to assess the vulnerability of their DAO and react if needed. The same holds for those protocols that want to switch to DAO governance, which can make some of these assessments before they make the switch.\n \nAdditionally, it benefits those who have a stake in the DAO (i.e., those who hold the token) to assess the vulnerability of the DAO."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd4631b6d489a02fe50d3385c99086c1e804eac3f5eab4f6a618f626e460bd353",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728628368,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x039550"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1d7b0411bf47cf1393c9d91bf0d60c7f555ffe74d60c397f5b6a2e7ebfdcef28",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmchuuvUYHPACWfJCUUZXVdiejqNm2MfgZrsK1veS6aX1a",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work provides insights into both treasury and governance data within Optimism. On the treasury side, we track historical treasury value, holdings, and transactions and provide month-over-month comparisons to help visualize trends. For governance, we display all proposals categorized by their status and offer a clear view of active voters. This allows users to stay informed about the overall health of Optimism\u2019s governance and financial ecosystem in an easy-to-understand way, ensuring transparency and helping drive informed decision-making."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work has benefited on-chain communities across EVM chains, particularly within the Superchain ecosystem, including Optimism, Base, and Celo. Since our solution is inherently free and easy to use, anyone can effortlessly create and track their on-chain communities on Remox. From project teams to community members, everyone benefits from our insights into treasury and governance, empowering them to make informed decisions and engage more actively in their ecosystems."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd5e1d8cf2345afd314c47dc3cbdaa8ebfc15c8cda86c488ad58317cda9056141",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728330903,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0b9357"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd3afb173c92f315fa41c59f3a07773d317ca8ff69c26551e7d714c4f8348d492",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTS4DBM46DCZeHPaCKFQkP3AhgG6d6gAmafqHDxmhZP3f",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "We have created a comprehensive analysis of Optimism Badgeholder's onchain activity vs a control group of active non-Badgeholders. In particular, we looked at transaction activity across chains, involvement in social apps (Farcaster, Lens, Friendtech), participation in other DAOs (Arbitrum, Uniswap, ENS) and the deployment of smart contracts and NFTs. \n\nSomething to note: although it is true that not all citizens use their Badgeholder address for other onchain activity, we found that a significant amount did and we discuss the implications of this constraint in the report.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Foundation. This work was requested directly by the Foundation in order to get a better understanding of Optimism Badgeholders vs \u201cnormal\u201d Ethereum users. In their own words: \u201cIn order to confidently expand the Citizenry, we need to have a baseline understanding of the current Badgeholder group. Our goal is to get a better understanding of the Badgeholder group based on their onchain activity compared with the onchain activity of other active Optimism/Ethereum users.\u201d\n\nIn addition, the entire Optimism Collective has benefitted from the transparency provided by this publicly available work. It's open source nature sets the stage for others to conduct further research and expand upon our results. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd8da3fd433955af056d55b7de9830e4b86129b7c2a2be6210daacc13b090969a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728523443,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02ef50"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcf371331b430edd39877790edd709a5840e401b33b4ed69c339627088a5fa964",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmeYTr9hpMSbZvsaC1mcJsWe8krAQZQBJPcvaoYb63p5Qm",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "There have been 23 community governance calls in this impact period. In addition, we have had two \"speed dating\" sessions, mission request workshops, and other AMAs.\n\nThe calls have been a key place to discuss *everything* that has happened in governance during that time, and calls usually get 40-50 key participants from Optimism Governance.\n\nA small sampling of topics/guests in this impact period:\n* Jing presenting and Q&A on the Superchain vision\n* Base Governance team Rowan & Saemi discussing Base's participation\n* Ben Jones presenting Blockspace Charters\n* Kelvin Fitchner Granite Network Upgrade AMA\n* Justine with a Season 6 Governance AMA\n* Launamu preseting Impact Metrics Garden\n* PaperImperium discussing a proposal on accelerated governance decentralization\n* Roberto Bayardo (Base) presenting Fjord/Ecotone upgrades\n* Emily presenting Guest Voter Participation\n* Jonas presenting multiple Retro Funding rounds"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "These calls are the critical space for all governance participants to become informed, ask questions, and discuss every current issue across the Token House and the Citizen's House.\n\nBy condensing all of this information into 1 hour and by bringing experts into the discussion, Delegates and Citizens are able to participate more effectively across every area of Optimism Governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xdbac1cbb5099e8adfce5de8868ce946ab84b7a5a99b757e928247fb2146a9c9e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728228741,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x060568"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xddea7b8485b8b446e5856be4f2323a88271f73f343344ac98cf71cc2219e3915",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTr1uEZDVLgd9a49or745Vbx612HNnAWcS4YKpvTyte5R",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe07e666d50900bf9c5f2777dbe41cb97cc2e4eef46c1b480c0aa8e208b563ea8",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1727850778,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x055ae7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb5c09db8d1713e45ed45933d48e0da12f79676a6b95d015a5470db0fb614baea",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXm5uYv5NkkpUSALghjjLepkXJRuaqeur26keyJ8A4Zc8",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Delegates are the cornerstone of Optimism's governance system. Active and well-informed delegates lead to resilient and sound governance. However, delegates need to process a lot of information and often find it challenging to stay up-to-date. We are humans after all.\n\nTo help delegates stay active and well-informed, our team launched Tribuni\u2014a free Telegram mini-app built exclusively for delegates. Tribuni sends quality AI-generated proposal summaries, vote reminders, and OP forum activity digests directly via Telegram. This ensures that delegates never miss a vote or an important discussion within the OP ecosystem, as long as they're connected to Telegram."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "People managing 28 OP delegate profiles use Tribuni.\n\nInstitutional Delegates:\njuanbug from pgov.eth\nlbchase from Blockchain@USC: 0x995013b47ef3a2b07b9e60da6d1fff8fa9c53cf4\nVarit from curia-delegates.eth\nAlex Duckworth from franklindao.eth, 0x070341aa5ed571f0fb2c4a5641409b1a46b4961b\nTjark from PoolCollective: 0x3d2d722b443a5cae8e41877bb7cd649f3650937c\nCharlie Ambrose from anthiaslabs.eth\nCallen from wintermutegovernance.eth\nTnorm from Gauntlet: 0x11cf2f033b079fbb195425bfcb7d5dac4db2d752\nKrzysztof Urba\u0144ski from delegate.l2beat.eth\nPumbi from SEED latam: joxes.eth\nCole and others from 404gov.eth\nStanley from Purdue: 0x8ccde64d05a7677d80a5960cb75fb8de486cf98d\nKerem Talha Oral from itublockchain.eth\nDerrick Cui from calcblockchain.eth\nShoji from tanegov.eth\n\nIndividual Delegates:\natlantropa.eth\nbrichis.eth\nlaunamu.eth\nopmichael.eth\nsovereignsignal.eth\nliliop.eth\nvote.ytocin.eth\nolimpio.eth\n0xdonpepe.eth\nFujiAR: 0x66946def4ba6153c500d743b7a5febfc1654d6bd\nkatiegarcia.eth\nmattgov.eth\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe816aa84e6321b1d8c6e823076b88be32782bf444b33ecd900f9c3e07ea7b679",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728202281,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x06c2ea6d14ce0d6a29e4a037bb71efcb06dccdbc4ce471e6070691087608cb1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTr1uEZDVLgd9a49or745Vbx612HNnAWcS4YKpvTyte5R",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xeb802f29f510ddd2ad52a3ed8aac8e04c6341a383e9c936e6be4cff44c7c6454",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728465249,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02e380"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x243ebd69b4b92360b4c338bc80c5087a755989b0a7ad271607211990e9f974d4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNQzHzFuPXZ9VQGhsJA7PaSFjVW7g7d771mAVWP4doSbg",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Lighthouse native mobile app makes it easy for Citizens and Delegates to participate in Optimism governance. We built support for Optimism's custom Governor contract, which enabled us to add multiple powerful new features:\n\n1. We've added real time push notifications of new proposal and voting activity. \n\n2. We've added the ability to vote on proposals, on-chain, natively from within the Lighthouse app. \n\n3. We also pulled in on-chain comments and displayed them within the app, to surface community sentiment around proposals for users.\n\n4. Our interactive Farcaster Frames integration enables on-chain proposals and comments to be shared, further increasing awareness and participation in the social media space.\n\nThis all works together to provide a powerful and feature-complete alternative client for users who wish to vote on the go."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Token holders, delegates and followers benefit by Optimism being on Lighthouse. Even users who do not hold Optimism tokens are able to follow core Optimism proposal activity, making Optimism governance more accessible throughout the ecosystem."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf3e418134cd5d5e293540986292d41e539bc13c862de1bd84991822112c2314f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728533019,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x034f6b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa4057e7b9c7d062b669da04c0835a8e8899dbb3eee74771e963b4f68dd0d25da",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYZDeRVCejEzeW62UCMjST61sT2G3pZy3rgxsiyj98sXa",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The new sense of art and art publishing on L3. \nWith musics, paints, questions and futuristic but not utopic positive design.\nbuilding a interactions that show a evolutive growing with comunity.\nmore than 100 musics has creating to putting on this incredible experience on the future.\n\nHave a nice world."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The new sense of art and art publishing on L3. \nWith musics, paints, questions and futuristic but not utopic positive design.\nbuilding a interactions that show a evolutive growing with comunity.\nmore than 100 musics has creating to putting on this incredible experience on the future.\n\nHave a nice world."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf53e131123b0572c3703272b7af125997e74cbf0e26d80e99ea355701b3e3d6d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728588604,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02ef50"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x88890fe868af955df9fd2cf830be655f73c70a90ae723d1550345243736033ff",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmeiaGqLTSbPoQ6oeB4KPmcGbvFgbtpTbsvykGo1saehoo",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Opdelegates.com provides a dashboard with real-time data on delegates and the makeup of their delegations, including details about the change in their delegations over time.\n\nIn many ways Opdelegates.com is similar to Curia/Agora however we surface some information that is not available on other platforms, such as a more detailed breakdown of the makeup of delegators.\n\nIn addition, we pull the vast majority of our information directly from onchain data and process it using our own data pipelines. This means that we add to the redundancy of this type of delegation data for the Collective in the case that Curia/Agora stop working.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "There are two main governance participants who have benefited from OPdelegate.com:\n\nDelegates: Having up-to-date data on how your delegation is changing over time has been invaluable to delegates who are trying to grow their delegations. In addition, having detailed breakdowns of the size of their delegators and a list of the delegators enables them to reach out to their delegations.\n\nResearchers/Delegators: Our dashboards provides transparency into the nature of a delegates voting power. How many delegators does a delegate have? How concentrated is their voting power? These are the types of questions that researchers have answered with our dashboards. For example, there are some delegates with 95% of their voting power coming from one wallet, and others with no more than 2% coming from their biggest delegator. Opdelegate.com makes this information accessible to everyone.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf58b0f467e25a2088a63e34ac636de9a9ce92f54b72c7b6f360a04236b0ef90c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728186257,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x07fef0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf2690ec80ad673e879f750f9d2339ab28f953836d57a9f75cdf3ba59f3755c9a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSPRkoMgmbiiYEtdiwLmXgJ7usG4xQKrQiN3Zaa5Tmb1h",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Successfully completed a token house governance growth mission titled [Integrate Optimism Governance into University Module], and hosted governance workshops, community calls, and events throughout the year for Seasons 5 (S5) and 6 (S6)."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "We successfully completed a significant governance mission, positioning Optimism as the first university-level blockchain course in Costa Rica.\n\nOur efforts have enhanced the governance process by fostering community engagement and education within the Optimism ecosystem in the country, through the \"Integrate Optimism Governance into University Module\" mission. Not to mention that this module can now be replicated anywhere anytime. Our work has positioned Optimism and is attracting attention from other universities and organizations\n\nWe organized gov workshops, community calls, and events throughout the year [OP Days] This initiative has increased participation in governance, missions, and the forum.\n\nBy facilitating hands-on experiences, we empowered students to collaborate on innovative solutions, enriching the governance framework with diverse perspectives.\n\nCreating the next generation of Optimism leaders, ensuring a robust future for the ecosystem!\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf6e6f731c92a25bf8882576e47e4f55ea3d4c5fff24c2da7454e26b0eb332767",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728567216,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4f62353edfafbed19cc6b194b9b9058a6da22523c4efb3c5ec1bae1922f8b0fb",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNuWiTBzH2SJM9gbKMEVNQfsDw6bFnoUrbmBNafi5QT1v",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the council. In Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where the Foundation multisig was removed from the Upgrade multisig, and the Security Council became the sole signer. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xfb197a0f27182a949f19f8189e1ff4aa96982c81595b714fdebcffb1ba5ee27b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728539025,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0b674b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x3ce5e2510851268628f0814a1986653c1036e14feb10e5e52624559ccd4cd3bc",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmctBGs1XfzFodHanidDKb5RTSSZhMjzqsZMQ5zEDNmPVc",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Governance Leadership function typically involves overseeing the frameworks, structures, and processes by which an organization or institution is directed and controlled. Key responsibilities might include:\n\nSetting Strategic Direction\n\nEnsuring Accountability\n\nRisk Management\n\nStakeholder Engagement\n\nRegulatory Compliance\n\nEthical Leadership"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "Since I operate as an AI, my role in governance and leadership is more supportive than direct. I don\u2019t fulfill a specific governance leadership function myself but can assist in areas like:\n\nStrategic Decision Support\n\nAccountability and Oversight\n\nRisk Management Support\n\nStakeholder Communication\n\nCompliance and Regulation Guidance\n\nEthical Decision-Making Support"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xfc7e48b9011f363eda1c039a0a30106542739b7509aaa0444343f9c1341c5cab",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728623537,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x047403"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x99a3d0f85d90738c9502e0d9b9f2f5edd9957eac140bcb2a24b303d5e61836e1",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTDevL5ySP6bqojz64nX74PLjR1u16Ut5An3oZbsLwztN",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work for Optimism Governance was focused on RPGF3's round:\n\n1. **Project Visibility and Ballot Tracking**: We tracked how projects appeared in badgeholders' ballots and lists, providing real-time updates on their placement and the median valuation by badgeholders.\n   \n2. **Funding Overview**: We analyzed and displayed the funding history of projects, including previous RetroPGF allocations, external VC funding, and token issuance. This helps assess a project's overall financial backing and need for additional support or unaccounted rewards. We also showed results.\n   \n3. **Voting Dynamics**: By measuring how projects move in and out of ballots over time, we offered insights into badgeholders' voting behavior and project performance throughout the voting period.\n\n4. **User Engagement**: We tracked platform usage, monitoring the number of badgeholders and project representatives actively using the tracker, giving insights into overall engagement with the governance process."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "growthepie's Optimism RPGF3 tracker helped the RetroPGF3 voting process by providing badgeholders and projects with real-time insights into project ballots, funding history, and current standings of allocations and lists, including median allocated amounts to projects. The tracker significantly streamlined decision-making and overview of users, allowing badgeholders to quickly assess 643 projects with live updates and comprehensive data. \n\nFor Badgeholders, it enhanced transparency by offering detailed funding breakdowns, visibility of outside investments, and easy access to project descriptions on Agora. \n\nFor project owners, they could track and promote their projects accordingly on socials or elsewhere seeing their current standing."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xfff56c5353549a3386322a5dfa17c259c3b6728d94f102deee5daf7aa6d5ddbf",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728239881,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x090fcd"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x04c65f7f60aeccba6e9c4644e615b2ea1d4d1b3f0c250159ecb3de7b695705a0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfKTLWmjs8pKNhE3b8CrFxnocbQK8NdoKCkZatcomjQM5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Grant Allocation, Grant Program Analytics and Grantee Tracker:\n\nThe OP grant tracker is the largest data source for Optimism Grants, which in turn is one of the largest data source for Grantee details in the Web3. Till date the project has tracked more than 1078 grantees with a total allocation of more than 134 Million OP. The tracker adds grant awardees on a continuous  basis with data on the latest Cycle grantees also available for users to view and analyze.\n\nCurrently, the data on OP Grantees is highly fragmented, scattered over multiple platforms like Charmverse, OP Forums and RetroPGF Interface. There is no unified interface for users to view data on all grantees that have received OP from the Treasury.\n\nBeyond the numbers, the tracker presents the data on grantees in a simple and intuitive interface, enabling users to easily narrow down their research based on various parameters like Grants cycles, grant type, grant size and tags."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "1. Delegates in decision making: Delegates do not have the bandwidth to do in-depth research and make informed decisions on Grants when the data is so scattered. The OP Grants tracker makes it easy to compare performances of various Grant cycles with qualitative and quantitative measures.\n\n2. Grants Council Members in Grantee tracking: For each cycle, get a list of grantees, their application links and granular details related to their application. Our research enables GC Members to track projects that have ceased operations despite winning grants or have not performed up to the expectations, facilitating learning for future grant screening.\n\n3. Potential Grant Applicants in grants research: Potential applicants search grantees with similar area of focus (defi, data, infra, etc) and analyze successful applications. Furthermore, applicants get a better picture of the rubrics and reporting requirements, giving them more chances of success.\n\n4. OP Collective Members in general analytics"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4300aa75a15977f4155ff8ef777aca5527bbed3f4e3751428999392a672b3edf",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728663227,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x6478bdcaa20dccc3ede4a2e7c8d510d19033a7440632b0b368f6756d8cac1497",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmePctGMRjZCgWSucdixULCPspC5tsxooyoxEN8k3uSm9k",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Grants Council is to oversee the evaluation and approval of projects for Governance Fund grants, ensuring they align with the season's intent andthe mission requests.  \n\nKey responsibilities include:\n\n1. Grant Evaluation: Reviewing and approving grant applications that further the goals of The Collective.\n2. Mission Creation: Developing and proposing Mission Requests aligned with the broader objectives of the Optimism Collective, targeting specific ecosystem needs (Intents).\n3. Ensuring transparency by publishing reports, tracking milestone progress, and maintaining open communication with the community.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Grants Council keeps an updated communication thread here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/s6-grants-council-communication-thread/8324\n\nTo make RF6 voters life easier we compiled all our impact data here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/mid-season-6-grants-council-report/9016\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x50e7692a684532619fabbf33e136f627aca909a2eef7a91e5da76d79694cb2ec",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728663595,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x077495"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1dcf816a59f522606688784e12b4dad36290ba868fe7ea8cfc34388e3240872d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPZ5R7FJo59owwAzkGn9Z4GWRrbHiP4fseiouZm9h4pZ2",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We developed Pairwise for RF3, and introduced categories to make the impact measurement in the Retro Funding more organic and manageable.\nIn RF3, 185 users engaged, 27 badgeholders using their key\nIn RF4, we expanded into a community-wide experiment using pseudonymous voting with zk-tech. This allowed all stakeholders\u2014badgeholders, token holders, recipients, and delegates\u2014to participate freely without pressure and promote project discovery. Here you can find the final results, and our blog conclusions for more details on our outcomes.\nThe feedback from RF4 was very positive, leading to our invitation to build together with Optimism for RF5. For this round, we developed a star rating system, enabling participants to assign stars to projects before comparing them. This system grouped projects into tiers, significantly reducing the number of comparisons required.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main target when developing the product were badgeholders, who now can use Pairwise, to rank the Retro Funding projects in a fun way that promotes project discovery. However, the entire Optimism community, including delegates, token holders, and recipients, also gained through their participation in the Pairwise Retro Funding experiment, offering them the chance to discover impactful projects and bring more visibility to emerging initiatives. Projects benefited from increased exposure to potential users. Pairwise also sparks discussions  by comparing its results to official ones, fostering deeper insights and driving more meaningful participation and progress to decentralization.\nTo incentivize engagement, we distributed 4,000 OP as rewards giving a 100OP to 40 lucky winners, 10 on each stakeholder group participating in Pairwise."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5aba01cec62a07ee22b11f4c647839762b26e63994211cbe53e3a37b1e8565fb",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728662282,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x803a7cc61a0c5ce190a9b506a3861e9c5f41506fa352ab4354e9c07a8907ea3f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmePctGMRjZCgWSucdixULCPspC5tsxooyoxEN8k3uSm9k",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Grants Council is to oversee the evaluation and approval of projects for Governance Fund grants, ensuring they align with the season's intent andthe mission requests.  \n\nKey responsibilities include:\n\n1. Grant Evaluation: Reviewing and approving grant applications that further the goals of The Collective.\n2. Mission Creation: Developing and proposing Mission Requests aligned with the broader objectives of the Optimism Collective, targeting specific ecosystem needs (Intents).\n3. Ensuring transparency by publishing reports, tracking milestone progress, and maintaining open communication with the community.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Grants Council keeps an updated communication thread here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/s6-grants-council-communication-thread/8324\n\nTo make RF6 voters life easier we compiled all our impact data here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/mid-season-6-grants-council-report/9016\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x63454149fd7b7d2ea62021cf528649571e4048e89cd2d6df3f11923bba627b83",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728664011,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06a747"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1a83f994cc761b93cddbb81ff7a3df9cedc668b9109c7af94c952e18324eb142",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaByewKcF1tckN2kYW3N2ThNkovsiQaWBdMQxjcfgmkKX",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "One of the main challenges in governance is the ability to gather and motivate high-context contributors to engage in governance actions and discussions.\n\nAs a governance tooling, OP Bulletin addresses this issue by focusing on information accessibility through a weekly newsletter. Our team collects information from multiple sources and curates summaries on governance and ecosystem topics, keeping high-context contributors and delegates informed. We also ensure to include any updates that might inform governance decisions by delegates or committee members. This supports governance by reducing the information overload and effort required for existing contributors to stay up-to-date on important topics, initiatives and deadlines.\n\nOP Bulletin also maintains an easy-to-read, accessible style, and is distributed through Paragraph, the Optimism forum, Farcaster, and Twitter. This allows new delegates and the broader community to easily access information about Optimism\u2019s governance.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Since our launch on February 2024, we have published and distributed 33 issues of OP Bulletin. Among our audience we reach delegates, members of different councils and the broader Optimism and Superchain audience that are interested in weekly updates on the Collective.\n\n- Governance Forum Thread: 2.5K views on our weekly posts thread, where we mostly reach delegates and other active members involved with governance.\n\n- OP Bulletin\u2019s following: 97 accounts on twitter and 30 subscribers on Paragraph where we reach broader Optimism and Superchain audience that are not necessarily active in the forum. Mid July we migrated our audience from Substack to Paragraph growing our subscribers and from a 44% average open rate to a 52% open rate.\n\n- Attestations via Impact Garden show our impact on the community. We also received comments by the community through social media and forum from community members: Pumbi, Gopal, Bubli.eth, Brichis, Otomato.xyz, Dmitry Shklovsky."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7e7845297845ee26fa8be6ed5a286136aff4a7174768721de5c2d7ee366f0547",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728662734,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2888"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0a561d6a82243e08e04cba89d1ac246887806bc14a28f6f7a219b387183e2796",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbRQr7yrhgXGLi4Cn5j2ueRvLgBAKdD8BitFoWZautFxv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Gitcoin developed the voting interfaces for Retrofunding 4 & Retrofunding 5, which were used by badgeholders to allocate funds during those rounds.\n\nFor RF4, we worked closely with Open Source Observer and Optimism to implement new metrics-based discovery, selection, and weighting. Our solution allowed users to filter and evaluate projects based on various impact metrics. \n\nFor both RF 4 & RF5, we created a user-friendly interface for governance participants to allocate their votes. \n\nThese tools are primarily used within Optimism Governance to support the Retroactive Public Goods Funding process, which is a crucial part of Optimism's governance model. They aim to make the process of discovering, evaluating, and voting for projects more efficient, transparent, and user-friendly for governance participants."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The direct benefits are the Optimism badgeholders and recipients of Retrofunding. During RF4, 108 out of 133 badgeholders participated. $10M OP tokens were allocated to 207 projects. \n\nThough RF5 is still ongoing at the time of this application, participation is high. Badgeholders are expected to allocate between 2-8m OP tokens to up to 89 projects.\n\nThe team has also integrated these features into EasyRetroPGF.xyz, which makes them available to a wider range of users involved in Optimism's governance processes. The SUNNYS Awards have also been built on this same technology!"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xba4aafcd7e362e81326f332c12801462b8251ca6bfb07ae8c1092563809def88",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728664019,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06a747"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0b4431f77021d0dc97b8fd46d4148e7c99eeca564d2e4db277a5feaefe20ce72",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRaHREpACRKQ2Urc4xBPsVnsie5NhUUUfHfGYw33JPvHo",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Grants Pathfinder supports Optimism Governance by providing an accessible platform for discovering grants within the Web3 ecosystem, including specific opportunities tied to Optimism such as Optimism Delegate Missions, Foundation Missions, and the Partner Fund.\n\nThe tool supports the Token House grants process by offering a streamlined method for projects and contributors to discover and apply for relevant grants.\n\nBy aggregating and simplifying grant information, Grants Pathfinder enhances accessibility, ensuring that delegates and community members can identify and pursue funding opportunities that are vital to their ongoing contributions in Optimism."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Since we launched Grants Pathfinder in February 2024:\n\nGrants Pathfinder increased grants accessibility. It made it easier for projects, delegates, and builders within the Optimism community to discover and apply for relevant grant opportunities. By gathering resources and updating information from multiple sources in a single platform, we reduced the friction often experienced when navigating the grants landscape. We reached 340+ unique users in the last quarter with a recurrence in views per active users of 4.49 through our website."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf470e4eeba23f62303b5bddf577c3a3c7447df0099cbb0e6eea34bca0cc916da",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728663299,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xaa669e628d6aa77ede141f7213a1b73156acf5692a55430a15884c0739a90641",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmePctGMRjZCgWSucdixULCPspC5tsxooyoxEN8k3uSm9k",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Grants Council is to oversee the evaluation and approval of projects for Governance Fund grants, ensuring they align with the season's intent andthe mission requests.  \n\nKey responsibilities include:\n\n1. Grant Evaluation: Reviewing and approving grant applications that further the goals of The Collective.\n2. Mission Creation: Developing and proposing Mission Requests aligned with the broader objectives of the Optimism Collective, targeting specific ecosystem needs (Intents).\n3. Ensuring transparency by publishing reports, tracking milestone progress, and maintaining open communication with the community.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Grants Council keeps an updated communication thread here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/s6-grants-council-communication-thread/8324\n\nTo make RF6 voters life easier we compiled all our impact data here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/mid-season-6-grants-council-report/9016\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc8719c35396ba9d0b950dc3c93bb49eab49d1eae779d1a217952764f7d658f73",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728664268,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x072f86"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x7b38cb048e1eb77aa02a98b1cecd4ee346f293044370d2efa57a95d2ce55c3ef",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTty6XQEHWAq2jTYDjhTH5b811KxefkLKG6mqv2BXFpSH",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "We designed and facilitated the following deliberative process: \n\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/ratification-of-profit-definition-for-round-4/8312\n\nThe scope of work comprised a cooperation with the Optimism Foudation governances' team on the design of the mandate, the information materials, the design of the sessions, the design of the recruitment, the facilitation of the sessions, the reporting. \n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Many participants and non-participants have stressed the value of the process and call for using it more often in other contexts. \n\nThis is particularly clear in the comments of the post on the governance proposal: https://gov.optimism.io/t/ratification-of-profit-definition-for-round-4/8312\n\nWhile not perfect, this first deliberative process has already brought an important impact in the governance of the collective. \n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x10715d5ba932fdb130fedd06cb55c284e69a0f3f7c4d0e5d577d1baa7e7cc316",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728664731,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x077495"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1dcf816a59f522606688784e12b4dad36290ba868fe7ea8cfc34388e3240872d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTHLZmtdhk4UXomtCMxtxxHzmGMADAbbebacuNnuhXJzp",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We developed Pairwise for RF3, and introduced category voting to make the impact measurement in the Retro Funding more organic and manageable.\n\nIn RF3, 185 users engaged, 27 badgeholders using their key.\n\nIn RF4, we expanded into a community experiment using pseudonymous voting with zk-tech. This allowed all stakeholders\u2014badgeholders, token holders, recipients, and delegates\u2014to participate freely without pressure and promote project discovery. We also distributed 4,000 OP as rewards, a 100OP to 40 lucky winners. Here you can find the [final results](https://www.pairwise.vote/rf4-results), and our [blog conclusions](https://paragraph.xyz/@pairwise) for more details on our outcomes.\n\nThe feedback from RF4 was very positive, leading to an invite to build with Optimism for RF5. For this round, we developed a star rating system, enabling participants to assign stars to projects before comparing them. This system grouped projects into tiers, significantly reducing the number of comparisons."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main target when developing the product were badgeholders, who can use Pairwise, to rank Retro Funding projects in a fun way that promotes project discovery.\n\nHowever, the entire Optimism community that used the app discovered impactful projects, bringing more visibility to emerging initiatives.\n\nProjects benefited from this increased exposure to potential users. Pairwise also sparks discussions by comparing its results to official ones, fostering deeper insights and driving more meaningful participation and progress to decentralization.\n\nThe foundation\u2019s implementation of RetroFunding was clearly informed by our work and [feedback](https://gov.optimism.io/t/retropgf-round-3-feedback-thread/6177/150?u=griff). Enabling categorical voting, and ranking projects then adjusting percentages were done in Pairwise before they were considered to be implemented in RF5&RF6. Subtracting grant amounts and soliciting comments from badgeholders were also inspired by our work, but cut from scope."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x64d2b573c2d4824880c413738b7e929f8ca1a890c22a0d532b1c74913a60eb77",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728664555,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03607f"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x67b30fac65fa8d3f0c5edb574ecf5acb0f111ebd52640ded2ec472777372a2dd",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVAV3W4wFer33e8DnLUsMBostDsrhtQTyotUtsTKYuBQh",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analysis identifies the characteristics of the fund distribution methods used in the Optimism Collective\u2019s grant programs by comparing them with other grant programs. We analyze distribution patterns, such as the size of grants, the number of recipients, decision-making processes, and how evenly resources are allocated, highlighting how Optimism\u2019s fund distribution differs from other governance models. We have found that Optimism provides relatively larger grants, supports a greater number of recipients, and shows less variation in the amount granted per recipient. We also examine how effective Optimism\u2019s governance structure is in promoting fair and impactful public goods funding. Additionally, we expect this analysis to lead to the proposal of new types of grants and the measurement and evaluation of impact based on data, contributing to more effective funding practices."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of our analytical work are decision-makers involved in Optimism Collective\u2019s grant distribution, as well as those looking to improve grant allocation models and governance mechanisms. By providing insights into fund distribution patterns and the effectiveness of different governance mechanisms, we support these stakeholders in making evidence-based decisions. This will enable the Optimism Collective to contribute to the Optimism ecosystem, the Ethereum ecosystem, and real-world public goods, making true public goods funding a reality through evidence-based decision-making. Our research helps contributors make informed decisions."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x01180be2a50da4bd5a9b27b8d6836c33dc8a487820f9f175d2b9642035bb5e25",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728930258,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04d50d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x802a9e75b95414a35bf1e4a4196205ec47ef44c09a855a573ad80902a5c0388f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmdvKQUZKFm3LSgSxNRX29b8NtvAsqhtYK1RhvgTTNKPsC",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Our DAO has 159 unique members who have provided us with 131k OP votes. We follow new proposals every day and have participated in almost every vote.\n\nIn order to attract this number of users, we held various events and engaged in media outreach. We have also done a lot of work with CIS Influencers, so the number of participants and the amount has increased several times since PRGF3. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The number of active DAO participants increased from 93 to 159 and the amount from 38k to 131k OP. So we can confidently say that we have done a great job in increasing the decentralization of the network over the last year. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x02cb544536aa961ccd90bebc2845324734931d4ec41e26a2789726621781378b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728674915,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xbb84f3a7463ca746831ce765bd83b33c13e55712c0b8d1c3e74096a120ca0527",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQwMxbJLBbPU6r5x1yDHkUaxUPuv9LupckcKkPM32Fu4K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\n[Reflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation](https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x03b4b67e0c46bad8538a51cd93875a4909c0b53e657917a93cbe74ce8ebab88a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857737,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x48a89eb05496e18fa2119e24cbbf6ddaa050d932121131d382e4132f1e277288",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmekj7mS6JzfTSuUmrz2xVn2hLZDQp6Mc3Knz4ZT3ceU4u",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. \n\nFoundation Mission Request: Season 5 govNERDs\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs significantly lightened the Foundation's workload by managing critical governance tasks such as Voting Cycle Roundups, drafting vote copy, and coordinating voting and veto announcements. We ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Through active forum moderation and responding to community questions, we exceeded our mandate and paved the way for an open contribution path in Season 6. \n\nKey contributions include:\n- Creation of a tracker for Missions v2.\n- Support in maintaining the Public Governance Fund Tracker.\n- Gathering feedback throughout the Season and flagging key issues to the Foundation.\n\nFor more, check the Impact Evaluation made by the Foundation: \nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734\n\nReward Split: \nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1zzsd7p2ECdHBnQQhWMt8ivArqfUIXNv713FjrCQ51mE\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x052dc20c7d5b74a324181f7f6796f74d07e231b38ec7a74887235e30fb1b7497",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728839208,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4800705441d2440659c59766dc1fcd81951bbf9a6cde6dffd9c116cf5f50cbc7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVnnoeQDwF7fpR5yM9cRGpwHEb61xY52MkiY1C8Eu2q7c",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "- Data interoperability and transparency within the Collective: The Optimism Collective is one of the largest DAOs, with new artifacts being released continuously. This includes information on committees & councils, list of important initiatives, links to governance, list of voters, etc. Through EIP-4824, we have created an on-chain (and off-chain) source of truth on the Optimism Collective. New artifacts can be continuously added to the Collective's daoURI, making it comprehensive over time. \n\n- Better visibility for DAO-related EAS schemas on Optimism: Currently, there is no place where DAO-related EAS schemas can be listed and indexed, along with a description and additional context. We built a proof-of-concept DAO Schema Registry.\n\n- Visibility into grants. Working with OSO and Gitcoin, we have developed an initial data lake for grants across Web3, including Optimism's grants, combating grant farming and double dipping across ecosystems."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "- Governance tooling providers: More transparency and interoperability of data direclty benefit Snapshot, Snapshot X, and a variety of other governance tools, who utilize EIP-4824 to publish and handle DAO metadata.\n\n- New participants of the OP Collective: the daoURI is a useful piece of infrastructure for anyone who'd like to find info at a single location.\n\n- Delegates: More data transparency and standardization makes it easier for even high-context individuals to assess changes across the scope of a wide, decentralized organization."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x08386d67e83a53cf4e4c90894e7ca09ea35fac1e3be10b7c4ab718c5bdea405e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728899909,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x05b997"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x69039895426172eb574fd2b6dbfd261838621b069d3405bd024997936105d642",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmS2v2HBbT47tDSPfEFBWL8FgLmc9B2k9ppFKiHm44suWP",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Our first Superchain Space took place on October 8-9th around ETHCC.\n\nThe Impact:\n- Enabled important in-person discourse and collaborations by curating all 250+ attendees to prioritize current Optimism stakeholders at a 2-minute walking distance from ETHCC.\n- Hosted Governance roundtables together with LauNaMu, with multiple Grants Council and Delegates present, to discuss the current state of Optimism Governance and grants. We also had Sejal, from EasyRPGF participate and share insights on how to improve RetroPGF rounds.\n- Gathered stakeholders from 10+ OP Chains to discuss and reflect on Superchain developments. This enabled meaningful cross-pollination between OP Chain stakeholders.\n- Interviewed nearly a dozen Optimism Collective contributors, including DCBuilder (Worldcoin) and Ryan Li (Cyber), and hosted various panels and talks focussed exclusively on Optimism and the Superchain. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The leadership work produced through Superchain Space benefited current Optimism Collective contributors and new ecosystem entrants.\n\nValuable input and reflection on key governance processes: The roundtables and workshops organized at Superchain Space, including the Governing the Superchain (by LauNaMu) and Retro Reward Programs learnings (by Sejal from EasyRGPF/Gitcoin), enabled meaningful discourse between OP Grant Council members, Citizens, and teams/individuals contributing to the Optimism Collective.  \n\nInclusion and collaboration across Optimism Collective and OP Chain stakeholders: Our in-person event allowed many OP Collective stakeholders to meet in person for the first time. This improved connections, especially among current delegates / Citizens and stakeholders from the various OP Chains that joined the Superchain this year.\n\nBubbling up critical topics: The talks, panels, and interviews we facilitated raised awareness of important initiatives across the Superchain. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x08f8dd2e05e4bff5e603303bfe07092ae8714c2a55cbb520aa199edd29b1d637",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728830836,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf50edb48249aef564df1cca15ac1fdc53dee9613a8e8378e0b03dff820a1b2c3",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmV4rtBpq4mHsoQLx2nYir2ombp7k84GMxDDCGeLzKyvs9",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Each Badgeholder session has had a different focus given that the needs are matched according to the stage of RetroRounds and the current experiments being carried out:\n\n1. Workshops on the creation of lists for 3 different categories prior to RetroRound3. I designed and ran the workshops in a couple of them with the support of 2 other Badgeholders.\n2. Istanbul Meetup @ Onchain Summit where we gathered to 1) connect, 2) explore thoughts on lists and voting, 3) learn about projects such as Pairwise. Secured a place with the OP team, created merch, and coordinated with Badgeholders attending DevConnect. \n3. Badgies Workshopping @ Eth Denver: Coordinated the event, contacted the presenting teams, and led the session. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Each session has led to different improvements in the process and experiments of RetroRounds. \nFor the first two, the outcomes are described above. \n\nFor the 3 Session, here is some additional information:\n\nIn this session the following teams presented and received feedback from Badgeholders and the Foundation:\n1. EZKL - https://retrofunding.ezkl.xyz/\n2. Buidl Guild - Metrics Based Voting\n3. Agora \n4. Pairwise\n5. EasyRPGF\n\n This session particularly informed changes in the design of voting for Round 4, the release of EZKL's proving system for Retro3 results, among other things. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x0a1ca55cbc5b2f1559f1276d33eb2f9486c071070e53655ee709a01230d29c98",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728888192,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4099ac09c65e46b2f27978d9b5daba7aa7d014fe8cba4169b181080da246fa35",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPgjEdDvDMsTSgv21RuJCHyZSTGaZGudX1EbV89vtpVHE",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures\n\nThe responsiveness and engagement of Security Council members exceeded expectations. Security Council members attended monthly calls, often running through signing ceremony playbooks with the OP Labs team. By the end of Season 5, the Security Council had proven it's ability to carry out required tasks and was in a position to transition from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where it would be the only signer required in order to execute a protocol upgrade. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x0a864da06e2ee091a2a1e4902d7ea2827a941efb2fc83df678351045b60fdd5f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728907351,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0355b8"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xdc4fb6118bc57f477c82fae1f6b4bb54c15a10de099d47c8c506803c2c447dab",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmX5gVeVMMHEx8vmrUCpeytCSeLT8jkd3EAcJ97nQR6FZP",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Participation Rates: Tracking voter turnout and active participation over time, assessing how different types of proposals impact engagement.\n\nProposal Success Rates: Analyzing the approval and rejection rates of proposals, identifying which categories (e.g., upgrades, funding) see the highest success.\n\nDelegate Influence: Measuring the voting power and influence of top delegates, and how their votes sway proposal outcomes.\n\nGovernance Token Distribution: Assessing the decentralization of OP tokens, monitoring whether governance power is becoming more concentrated or dispersed.\n\nProposal Performance & Impact: Evaluating the success of initiatives funded through governance and their benefit to the ecosystem.\n\nTransparency & Accountability: Auditing the execution of proposals to ensure funds are used as intended and decisions are clearly communicated.\n\nThese metrics ensure Optimism's governance is effective, transparent, and decentralized.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of my analytics work in Optimism Governance are:\n\nGovernance Participants (Token Holders and Delegates): Data on participation rates, proposal success, and delegate influence help them make informed decisions.\n\nExample: Delegates can see how their votes align with community sentiment and adjust.\n\nOptimism Collective: Insights improve governance, decentralization, and voter turnout.\n\nExample: Identifying participation gaps and refining proposals.\n\nProject Teams & Proposal Creators: Analytics show which proposals succeed, helping teams craft better proposals.\n\nExample: A technical upgrade proposal can be tailored based on past successes.\n\nGovernance Researchers: They benchmark governance and track trends.\n\nExample: Comparative studies on governance decentralization.\n\nOptimism Ecosystem: Transparency and data-driven insights improve governance, fostering trust and stability.\n\nThese insights lead to informed decisions, better participation, and accountability."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x0b1e91362ba2aaad5a367c6befabb93f18ce82eed202f7999b3622604fe814bc",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728668688,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0716ba"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x890e0fff4be0c648ab1f7017875268425daac5357b2f5d7ee3be450aa212daf2",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmWi7PNFtZeG2PB8LnVE2RFTNKDHfeUMafFiXDfCaxwfDT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "At BAG, our mission is to help people learn about and engage with Optimism. We do this by making Optimism Governance accessible to all. Here\u2019s how we support it:\n\nEducation:\nWe provide simple guides on how Optimism Governance works, including voting on Snapshot and understanding decision-making.\n\nCommunity Engagement:\nBAG is a platform for discussing governance proposals, sharing opinions, and understanding how decisions impact the future of Optimism.\n\nVoting Awareness:\nWe keep members informed about voting deadlines and proposals, ensuring they have the tools to cast their votes on Snapshot.\n\nWorkshops and Events:\nWe host events to educate members on governance topics, Retroactive Public Goods Funding (RetroPGF), and how to contribute.\n\nShowcasing Impact:\nWe highlight the importance of public goods funding and guide members on supporting these initiatives through governance.\n\nBy educating and engaging our community, BAG ensures more people take part in shaping the future of Optimism."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "\nHere\u2019s a slightly shorter version:\n\nThe people who have benefited most from BAG's infrastructure are:\n\nNewcomers to Optimism:\nOur educational resources help individuals new to Optimism and Web3 by simplifying governance, voting, and public goods funding, making it easy for beginners to engage.\n\nActive Community Members:\nEngaged participants benefit from discussions on proposals and staying informed about voting, enabling them to actively shape Optimism's future.\n\nProject Developers and Creators:\nBuilders who contribute to public goods benefit from our focus on RetroPGF and governance, as we help the community understand the impact of these projects.\n\nWeb3 Enthusiasts:\nWeb3 enthusiasts interested in decentralized governance find BAG's resources essential in navigating Optimism and participating effectively."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x0b45ced16f073bed0daeb1ce76b4b9f36fa49be9cfa217e471ea9c4fa92133b2",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928846,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0d3843"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xc07b31d979a7e2363da6be8fbcac26ccbafb4f5baf65e433d18abbb0a29f461e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPTVLgZn1DDnVMAP5YGTV6hVdssMsme1WczAkB4kv9Tv8",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "RadicalxChange published and incubated the early work that led to the adoption of quadratic funding, SBTs, and more. We are now working on transforming onchain ownership through partial common ownership token systems piloted with leading artists and arts institutions."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Optimism, Gitcoin, Protocol Labs and others working on public goods funding systems. Soon, we hope many artists will benefit from our work on partial common ownership. We have also worked hard during the past years to help evangelize and exemplify the possibilities for using new technologies for transformative governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x0c3d55add6e3934a342fa072e7d06814092c05f07fee5cd492783e07f4e3d1fe",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856867,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x0dd038116a19c4bee0cb225db8d1086d44086495ed930ca0461b27612809df6f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728715834,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb8cc7c0f9b46f7683c167c77ca0ccfb4a5a100eea6172b537e6d8ba263f3a00c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaBRnG4LPzQsaMxNGTk2ZVeMJ6bfHxzgyuhCdMBvLGQQs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x0dd965f47dc62f448b334f0fccb71c6b822396ce7e5b7ae247c5ecc7e6e64668",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728906049,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x5314"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9956299dd587d6b16af54fba8a7fc1df643cd6a5f834236f070fff218cd79480",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQKm6uEgDrXLT5XKj2Fomhf7W6BmcbyihunCUcFdHquKN",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We built this site in response to forum feedback, where many community members shared feeling overwhelmed by the constantly evolving nature of Optimism governance, in particular the many novel experiments around grant programs.\n\nWhile rapid iteration is good for innovation (yay!), it also made it more challenging to stay up-to-date without first having to \"navigate a maze of forum posts\". We made it easy to access all deadlines and changes to programs in one place.\n\nThis has been well received: In the period between Oct 2023 and Sept 2024, there have been 2.9K outbound link clicks from our site to the Charmverse Grants Council page, 1.1K clicks to the Foundation Mission Requests pages on GitHub, and 605 clicks to forum posts on Retro Funding Rounds."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our site has primarily been useful as tool for supporting those involved in grants processes, including the Grants Council, Retro Funding Rounds and (Foundation) Mission Requests.\n\nThe subscribers of our newsletter where we used to share weekly updates, before then focusing primarily on the website, include employees from OP Labs, OpenZeppelin and Wakeup Labs. \n\nThe teams behind grantee projects such as OpenZeppelin are those who likely benefited most from our overview of the current status of grant programs, upcoming deadlines, our grants calendar, and the changelog. They otherwise would have had a much higher workload by having to keep track of this information across a number of different channels (GitHub, Grants Council Charmverse page, Forum, ...)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x0ee364cbb2713945f117a486393ac645805a9fdd4a85c727d66222b2f2a658aa",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728830860,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1cfa24a1212d4b707b48d7b35795fedd3497654e7278e464943e395cf21ed801",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmV4rtBpq4mHsoQLx2nYir2ombp7k84GMxDDCGeLzKyvs9",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Each Badgeholder session has had a different focus given that the needs are matched according to the stage of RetroRounds and the current experiments being carried out:\n\n1. Workshops on the creation of lists for 3 different categories prior to RetroRound3. I designed and ran the workshops in a couple of them with the support of 2 other Badgeholders.\n2. Istanbul Meetup @ Onchain Summit where we gathered to 1) connect, 2) explore thoughts on lists and voting, 3) learn about projects such as Pairwise. Secured a place with the OP team, created merch, and coordinated with Badgeholders attending DevConnect. \n3. Badgies Workshopping @ Eth Denver: Coordinated the event, contacted the presenting teams, and led the session. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Each session has led to different improvements in the process and experiments of RetroRounds. \nFor the first two, the outcomes are described above. \n\nFor the 3 Session, here is some additional information:\n\nIn this session the following teams presented and received feedback from Badgeholders and the Foundation:\n1. EZKL - https://retrofunding.ezkl.xyz/\n2. Buidl Guild - Metrics Based Voting\n3. Agora \n4. Pairwise\n5. EasyRPGF\n\n This session particularly informed changes in the design of voting for Round 4, the release of EZKL's proving system for Retro3 results, among other things. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x11d1a52ecc09888a5b8326c9e5f32599a47ffaaf08340eaa0ac5d0bd97009915",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728729048,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x137c9a42d8febae8201250e3be9ad50f78a8d375d4bd37f1935613d64e7a7f81",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728885708,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4099ac09c65e46b2f27978d9b5daba7aa7d014fe8cba4169b181080da246fa35",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaBRnG4LPzQsaMxNGTk2ZVeMJ6bfHxzgyuhCdMBvLGQQs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x139069772362ded9cd01ca35264d2e990f95de506c9134491196d6980f44d8be",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856831,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x07a02270e0367cc269699073b6228615a7336c7b043c390fd0b4574befecea1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTCsskKvMGNcEWN3zMuBxxxjdS2k1ARmE77sihaECbQyv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n \nRelevant Documentation:\nAnticapture Commission Mandate: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n\nAnticapture Commission Communication Thread:  https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/9\n\n\nSeason 6 Internal Operating Procedures: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-s6-internal-operating-procedures-iop/8637\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During S6 Governance (VC #25 to #28), ACC voted on the Dolomite Network upgrade proposal. ACC held discussions and shared feedback to the Foundation on the Dolomite Upgrade Proposal on certain technical aspects of the upgrade that the ACC members felt could have been better implemented. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/20 ) \n\nDuring S6 voting cycles, few Delegates encountered voting issues on the Agora UI, resulting in wrongly cast votes during a mission request vote. The ACC held internal discussions on the issue and took it up with the Agora team and worked towards resolving the issue. \n\n\nThe ACC also held a call to discuss the Accelerated Decentralization Proposal for Optimism with GFX Labs and the Foundation. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/accelerated-decentralization-proposal-for-optimism/8875/32 ) \n \nSince the Start of Season 6 of Governance, votable supply has increased by 7.31%, from 89.4m OP to 96m OP.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x15a0fde0d81cfb054b34910dbd2d052bff2b6a6f4cfe17df0cdc8b53afe84bda",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928660,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02e6d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xe675f05ddd2b9cb709fa560001e88983559ed1a2aabe58d27220782a4258fe97",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmWNaMvjSS4uESwNGeRmPrHQX244XFv5AQ7yzhukDAthr5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Flexy offers superchain users the easiest and cheapest way to acquire $OP for use in governance. For the past year, users were able to acquire $OP through gasless transactions via a single off-chain signature, offering the easiest method for obtaining $OP cross-chain.\n\nUsers who obtained $OP via Flexy saved large amounts in bridge fees, as Flexy is dedicated to providing bridging as a public good. We aim to receive grant funding to offer fully-free $OP acquisition, with Flexy operational costs being fully offset by retro funding."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "- $OP governance token holders. These users were able to save time and money by using our dedicated $OP token bridge. https://www.flexy.tech/bridge?chainId=10&outputToken=0x4200000000000000000000000000000000000042\n\n- OP stack projects. dApps live on OP stack chains were able to integrate the Flexy widget to provide their users the ability to obtains $OP directly from the dApp itself utilizing a shared wallet connection. We were able to save users time and headache when obtaining their $OP for governance voting or delegation."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x176e4151a62d4f67990f90c5d7744afeb1cd4332c11ae00852f9c8af6a5056be",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929770,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02e6d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd4dedeb31c2b986424d2f2120b3aa0693445d9133b1b34f9588385a0915deabb",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmWNaMvjSS4uESwNGeRmPrHQX244XFv5AQ7yzhukDAthr5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Flexy offers superchain users the easiest and cheapest way to acquire $OP for use in governance. For the past year, users were able to acquire $OP through gasless transactions via a single off-chain signature, offering the easiest method for obtaining $OP cross-chain.\n\nUsers who obtained $OP via Flexy saved large amounts in bridge fees, as Flexy is dedicated to providing bridging as a public good. We aim to receive grant funding to offer fully-free $OP acquisition, with Flexy operational costs being fully offset by retro funding."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "- $OP governance token holders. These users were able to save time and money by using our dedicated $OP token bridge. https://www.flexy.tech/bridge?chainId=10&outputToken=0x4200000000000000000000000000000000000042\n\n- OP stack projects. dApps live on OP stack chains were able to integrate the Flexy widget to provide their users the ability to obtains $OP directly from the dApp itself utilizing a shared wallet connection. We were able to save users time and headache when obtaining their $OP for governance voting or delegation."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x17a6e399332107b693ba8923ae3b21852a87fcd532bacfa5c98afa086c443d18",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728930932,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x640ca8694175aaa059c45e5f90594354442aa858b527a165e29de658fddea756",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPgjEdDvDMsTSgv21RuJCHyZSTGaZGudX1EbV89vtpVHE",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures\n\nThe responsiveness and engagement of Security Council members exceeded expectations. Security Council members attended monthly calls, often running through signing ceremony playbooks with the OP Labs team. By the end of Season 5, the Security Council had proven it's ability to carry out required tasks and was in a position to transition from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where it would be the only signer required in order to execute a protocol upgrade. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x18eb2bc4cd13fd7d15151d2b76e4d2dd379822d1ea4189bc37f19794a53f2d0a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728932238,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf5b1d1e37a365123031361242c9ea364a06ef525ad2290c2af1a2139aa7699f8",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmby7ruuCgS2ReuSXxccWuJjJAwojyqjjDa1P5597L5VCx",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Optimystics Tools has supported Optimism Governance by providing and maintaining essential infrastructure for decentralized decision-making over the past year:\n\n1. Initial Toolset: Our core tools have facilitated weekly Optimism Fractal events, enabling consistent governance experimentation and community building.\n\n2. Respect Infrastructure: We've maintained and upgraded the system for distributing Respect tokens, enabling a decentralized distribution amongst leading builders and governance enthusiasts.\n\n3. Council Support: Our tools have enabled the weekly formation and operation of the Optimism Fractal council, demonstrating scalable governance models and creating a well-organized governance body for the Collective.\n\nThis consistent infrastructure has allowed for the release of next-generation tools like ORDAO, Fractalgram, and the Respect Games app. It\u2019s enabled a community-driven effort with multiple development teams contributing to a growing toolkit of fractal governance tooling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Builders, leaders, delegates, and other key stakeholders in the Collective have used our tools at Optimism Fractal events to earn Respect and contribute to decentralized decision-making experiments.\n\n2. Our open-source infrastructure has served as a foundation for further governance innovations on Optimism, empowering researchers and developers interested in decentralized governance.\n\n3. Our tools have provided models and insights that could enhance various governance processes, including the Token House, Citizens' House, RetroFunding, and the Anti-Capture Commission.\n\n4. Other groups like the ZAO Fractal have adopted processes to engage, govern, and grow their communities on the Superchain. \n\nOur tools have created a vibrant testbed for governance innovations, benefiting anyone interested in exploring and contributing to decentralized decision-making processes on Optimism, and providing valuable data and experiences that can inform the evolution of the Collective's governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1a34881e1e66e3e9ef20d1d441ce2ef984adf05a25ce8ccae0e483d837249990",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728754390,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04dfb0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xe6bdbfc520bd008e4d6b40d15405ea07528e65de66c2be318d93d706978f558c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXhAH2Z589ZZekpJrvSuaesgvE2Es6LfTwzSrz6yw79n3",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We serviced the Citizens' House throughout the period of October 2023 to September 2024 with Snapshot\u2019s voting platform. Their space (https://snapshot.org/#/citizenshouse.eth) was used to facilitate the protocol veto functions through 13 proposals and 443 votes coming from 66 active voters. The Citizen\u2019s House Snapshot space gained 156 new followers throughout this period.\n\nBeyond this, we collaborated with the Optimism Foundation and were awarded a grant to develop a cross-chain voting module. This module is designed to enable decentralized voting across OP Stack chains and could be a critical governance tool for both the Foundation and DAOs within the Superchain ecosystem in the future."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "In addition to the Citizens' House, many organizations across the Optimism and Base ecosystems have adopted Snapshot for governance. During period counting for RPGF6, on Optimism, Snapshot supported 1,085 active spaces, enabling 3,565 proposals and facilitating over 7.5 million votes from 934,550 active voters. On Base, Snapshot supported 262 spaces with 1,288 proposals, resulting in 62,475 votes from 19,591 voters. This widespread adoption positions Snapshot as the leading governance platform with the most impact within the Superchain ecosystem.\n\nWith the launch of Snapshot X, our onchain governance framework, we expect many of these users to transition from offchain to onchain voting. In particular, those using voting power from OP or Base are likely to vote on these chains, significantly increasing onchain governance activity, directly benefiting the entire Optimism Collective."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1bd2ea66a88fa468d299997ef5a79bdf157b7d4b0f91d99410daaacb3f998358",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728867386,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x4bd4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x47a6c0239271c310c031d545ecc6b7f62d5f45320681f76c52ebbc4ba5a6840e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVs4DWr1foKQ4dHFgW22vWE8R1WqaToiZSJE83xfT7XNV",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our work is primarily focused on analyzing grant allocations and the participation / revealed preferences of badgeholders during Retro Funding voting.\n\nFor instance, after each round during the current period (ie, RF3 and RF4), we authored an \"Opening up the ballot box\" piece, looking in detail at various voter patterns, biases, and clustering effects. \n\nAnother example is our \"longitudinal analysis\" piece, which looks at distinct cohorts of Retro Funding projects over time and identifies patterns related to grant allocation and project growth / momentum. \n\nIn addition to these retrospective pieces, we also assist Optimism Governance (and partners) to simulate voter behaviors and biases when designing rounds and voting interfaces. \n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The reality is that most of our insights are targeted at governance nerds: the most active/engaged  badgeholders, the Foundation, and a subset of Token House members who are active on the governance forum.\n\nOur ideas have been quoted in round design specs (see [here](https://gov.optimism.io/t/upcoming-retro-rounds-and-their-design/7861)) as well as in good-natured debate about the efficacy of grant allocation results (see [here](https://gov.optimism.io/t/new-rpgf3-distribution-disparity-data/7521)). \n\nOur post on the [300+ OSS projects applying for RF3](https://gov.optimism.io/t/analysis-on-the-300-oss-projects-applying-for-retropgf-3/7127) received 90+ likes on the governance forum, putting it in [the top 5](https://gov.optimism.io/top?period=yearly) of all posts over the period.\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1d21d627c6f4c257347a7accd782c3c786fd6fb807cc55cbb77feaa2104fd821",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728911476,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0338f1"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa22a66da1e02cc9c6dfaf8a3d7a97e0f224f5360a1e180496c3713e814f9a024",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVGPPMQAR3nrT6EgwP3vKanM8jMuhPAdkHYc1VCGa4p5t",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "DeepDAO provides the most comprehensive analysis of different components of Optimism governance:\n\n- Treasury, including trends over time, tokens, assets and composition (OP vs stables, majors, and others).\n\n-  Token, including governance performance influence on the OP token price.\n\n- Voter Trends: multiple metrics of quality and intensity of governance participation in the Collective. Successful proposals, avg. votes per proposal, and others, in multiple timeframes. We also categorize voters based on their governance score to understand participant quality.\n\n- Delegation, including intensity, and quantity of involvement across voting power, delegators, total votes, and voting periods.\n\n- Delegate Coalitions, tracking governance activity of power groups of up to 6 addresses. Together with Delegation, this provides deep analysis of decentralization within Optimism governance.\n\n- Voters Ecosystem, measuring the Collective voters involvement in other DAOs, including competing DAOs.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "New Participants: DeepDAO helps new entrants to the DAO ecosystem discover the OP Collective, ensuring they do not face information asymmetry compared to experienced participants.\n\nDelegates use DeepDAO to stay updated on OP Collective activities. Our analytics dashboard offers extensive information on the DAO's well-being.\n\nBuilders: DeepDAO makes it easy for builders to identify and approach the right delegates for feedback. (using the Delegation, and Coalitions dashboards).\n\nTooling Providers: DeepDAO aggregates information across various tooling providers and includes a tools page listing all DAO tools available to the Optimism Collective.\n\nOP Collective: Our data on coalitions, governance segmentation and voter trends provides multiple indicators of the DAO\u2019s decentralization, governance resilience and security. The Collective benefits immensely from a free resource like DeepDAO.\n\nInvestors, journalists, researchers: 1000s of media articles and academic papers quote DeepDAO data.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1eca99aed3fb2e42251415930fd8db5ee5707eff248ff452fb0d03f239dd79ed",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728851367,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1ecbfc48a00e4b92a77c3f9378eb4fc4f2c001207d8bf39d6a32d606a9d9dacc",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728887386,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x051b41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa50a3c90eb1080c26d5a664107c95f3e57391774fd5bb896e394510353a0b359",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXi2fyGB1iLQ9iUtzrqXCmRwtkj22NjsjbA3WSUDApDw6",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The impact on this community is to increase the number of Optimse onchain through open media information about optimization developments such as grants, airdrops, retroactives. for example what happened yesterday (airdrop 5 OP), Partner (Layer 3), to Superchain activity."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Spreading the development of optimism information through the telegram channel (@airdropfinder) with 567k members. This can help spread widely to other OP communities and not only telegram, RPS1N spreads through social media accounts such as x (twitter)."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1ef7db96fdb3cb5fae143f6eac37f47a99017ff2012b2eba970773443cfd260f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728712701,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x17005db02bb0d610b9fd4c143dfb017f215916e8cc1d5be698ca6c966e51f72e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x1f70ed67afb223968cd9ced7d26ae24351e09f61337ed4f44f048513bf1551a2",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728681180,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x07a02270e0367cc269699073b6228615a7336c7b043c390fd0b4574befecea1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTCsskKvMGNcEWN3zMuBxxxjdS2k1ARmE77sihaECbQyv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n \nRelevant Documentation:\nAnticapture Commission Mandate: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n\nAnticapture Commission Communication Thread:  https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/9\n\n\nSeason 6 Internal Operating Procedures: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-s6-internal-operating-procedures-iop/8637\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During S6 Governance (VC #25 to #28), ACC voted on the Dolomite Network upgrade proposal. ACC held discussions and shared feedback to the Foundation on the Dolomite Upgrade Proposal on certain technical aspects of the upgrade that the ACC members felt could have been better implemented. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/20 ) \n\nDuring S6 voting cycles, few Delegates encountered voting issues on the Agora UI, resulting in wrongly cast votes during a mission request vote. The ACC held internal discussions on the issue and took it up with the Agora team and worked towards resolving the issue. \n\n\nThe ACC also held a call to discuss the Accelerated Decentralization Proposal for Optimism with GFX Labs and the Foundation. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/accelerated-decentralization-proposal-for-optimism/8875/32 ) \n \nSince the Start of Season 6 of Governance, votable supply has increased by 7.31%, from 89.4m OP to 96m OP.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x20abb0b72b1033a961d4657b8e2e7bc5d8043054931556e79266604f01baf067",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728926572,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x604045aaf89932382c171101509227d2ec51a0fbb67e2ae5954ab4284cdd75a1",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmby7ruuCgS2ReuSXxccWuJjJAwojyqjjDa1P5597L5VCx",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Optimystics Tools has supported Optimism Governance by providing and maintaining essential infrastructure for decentralized decision-making over the past year:\n\n1. Initial Toolset: Our core tools have facilitated weekly Optimism Fractal events, enabling consistent governance experimentation and community building.\n\n2. Respect Infrastructure: We've maintained and upgraded the system for distributing Respect tokens, enabling a decentralized distribution amongst leading builders and governance enthusiasts.\n\n3. Council Support: Our tools have enabled the weekly formation and operation of the Optimism Fractal council, demonstrating scalable governance models and creating a well-organized governance body for the Collective.\n\nThis consistent infrastructure has allowed for the release of next-generation tools like ORDAO, Fractalgram, and the Respect Games app. It\u2019s enabled a community-driven effort with multiple development teams contributing to a growing toolkit of fractal governance tooling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Builders, leaders, delegates, and other key stakeholders in the Collective have used our tools at Optimism Fractal events to earn Respect and contribute to decentralized decision-making experiments.\n\n2. Our open-source infrastructure has served as a foundation for further governance innovations on Optimism, empowering researchers and developers interested in decentralized governance.\n\n3. Our tools have provided models and insights that could enhance various governance processes, including the Token House, Citizens' House, RetroFunding, and the Anti-Capture Commission.\n\n4. Other groups like the ZAO Fractal have adopted processes to engage, govern, and grow their communities on the Superchain. \n\nOur tools have created a vibrant testbed for governance innovations, benefiting anyone interested in exploring and contributing to decentralized decision-making processes on Optimism, and providing valuable data and experiences that can inform the evolution of the Collective's governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x20d0f71dcc9a16689ae7aafc901038c2d138c054a508c2699d64d2aad573edb6",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856843,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2117fb73dc997332b9eec8b07f37ff0ac0225af479eda4ec1d5ecda2731a1875",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728854707,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x07a02270e0367cc269699073b6228615a7336c7b043c390fd0b4574befecea1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTCsskKvMGNcEWN3zMuBxxxjdS2k1ARmE77sihaECbQyv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n \nRelevant Documentation:\nAnticapture Commission Mandate: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n\nAnticapture Commission Communication Thread:  https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/9\n\n\nSeason 6 Internal Operating Procedures: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-s6-internal-operating-procedures-iop/8637\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During S6 Governance (VC #25 to #28), ACC voted on the Dolomite Network upgrade proposal. ACC held discussions and shared feedback to the Foundation on the Dolomite Upgrade Proposal on certain technical aspects of the upgrade that the ACC members felt could have been better implemented. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/20 ) \n\nDuring S6 voting cycles, few Delegates encountered voting issues on the Agora UI, resulting in wrongly cast votes during a mission request vote. The ACC held internal discussions on the issue and took it up with the Agora team and worked towards resolving the issue. \n\n\nThe ACC also held a call to discuss the Accelerated Decentralization Proposal for Optimism with GFX Labs and the Foundation. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/accelerated-decentralization-proposal-for-optimism/8875/32 ) \n \nSince the Start of Season 6 of Governance, votable supply has increased by 7.31%, from 89.4m OP to 96m OP.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2123eed64e1204da0687d8d3ad9174765978a387f78102040c12e294b7d619e5",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728790676,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03607f"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1adc558680eda50d306ea3363ba9cfbf53d544f2a93778f0a838b90e83129567",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVAV3W4wFer33e8DnLUsMBostDsrhtQTyotUtsTKYuBQh",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analysis identifies the characteristics of the fund distribution methods used in the Optimism Collective\u2019s grant programs by comparing them with other grant programs. We analyze distribution patterns, such as the size of grants, the number of recipients, decision-making processes, and how evenly resources are allocated, highlighting how Optimism\u2019s fund distribution differs from other governance models. We have found that Optimism provides relatively larger grants, supports a greater number of recipients, and shows less variation in the amount granted per recipient. We also examine how effective Optimism\u2019s governance structure is in promoting fair and impactful public goods funding. Additionally, we expect this analysis to lead to the proposal of new types of grants and the measurement and evaluation of impact based on data, contributing to more effective funding practices."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of our analytical work are decision-makers involved in Optimism Collective\u2019s grant distribution, as well as those looking to improve grant allocation models and governance mechanisms. By providing insights into fund distribution patterns and the effectiveness of different governance mechanisms, we support these stakeholders in making evidence-based decisions. This will enable the Optimism Collective to contribute to the Optimism ecosystem, the Ethereum ecosystem, and real-world public goods, making true public goods funding a reality through evidence-based decision-making. Our research helps contributors make informed decisions."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x22f6073f2cacc61bc34dde412f679118c18cda1d5a42431d3b16a9f62b393da5",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728742859,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0a0137"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xde4f4e205eef49617d2d33f4cf728e55c8e8b226784653aa224b8c682d6c8817",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmeExVbsmfSxVgBGhZVPSPckm3vTGnjoQJBy8FN5JGHA41",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "A Vault is a secure smart contract that functions as a simple, safe savings account for your hot wallet. It allows you to deposit tokens and NFTs, set withdrawal limits, whitelist addresses, and require multiple signers for transactions. Vaults help keep your assets safe from drainers, hacks, open approvals, and lost or leaked private keys, making it an effective way to enhance the security and management of your digital assets.\n\nWe built in the abilty to allow delegates to easily delegate their tokens securely from their vault. This supports governance processes while maintaining asset safety for users."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Delegators\nDelegators, who are entrusted with voting on behalf of token holders, have greatly benefited from the Vault's security features. By using the Vault to delegate tokens securely, delegators can confidently participate in governance processes without risking the transfer of tokens to third parties or insecure platforms byusing hot wallets. This ensures that their delegated assets remain protected from hacks, drainers, and other malicious activities and gives them a simple way to delegate vs exchanges which cant.\n\nThis enhances the overall participation in Optimism\u2019s decentralized governance by lowering barriers to involvement while maintaining security.\n\nDelegates\nDelegates, who are entrusted with the critical role of voting on behalf of token holders, have been one of the key beneficiaries of the Vault's infrastructure. Through the Vault, delegates can receive more votes securely, enabling them to effectively get larger delegations."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2364fd92894163d20faa502b9339aa885ed126b170ab55e32996d84da23b365f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856851,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5a63077cabc930af1ed712abc7e2e00d5badb61588076819ba5b193ecb0599f9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmekj7mS6JzfTSuUmrz2xVn2hLZDQp6Mc3Knz4ZT3ceU4u",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. \n\nFoundation Mission Request: Season 5 govNERDs\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs significantly lightened the Foundation's workload by managing critical governance tasks such as Voting Cycle Roundups, drafting vote copy, and coordinating voting and veto announcements. We ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Through active forum moderation and responding to community questions, we exceeded our mandate and paved the way for an open contribution path in Season 6. \n\nKey contributions include:\n- Creation of a tracker for Missions v2.\n- Support in maintaining the Public Governance Fund Tracker.\n- Gathering feedback throughout the Season and flagging key issues to the Foundation.\n\nFor more, check the Impact Evaluation made by the Foundation: \nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734\n\nReward Split: \nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1zzsd7p2ECdHBnQQhWMt8ivArqfUIXNv713FjrCQ51mE\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x250ec26a065e6d3e463a6815e0416872688b326d985f05b6c6f247c8cbd6fc9f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728924849,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0338f1"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x203b65166c5175077e72c68696bd77e6628807c18f4f369268bf339565591c3f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVGPPMQAR3nrT6EgwP3vKanM8jMuhPAdkHYc1VCGa4p5t",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "DeepDAO provides the most comprehensive analysis of different components of Optimism governance:\n\n- Treasury, including trends over time, tokens, assets and composition (OP vs stables, majors, and others).\n\n-  Token, including governance performance influence on the OP token price.\n\n- Voter Trends: multiple metrics of quality and intensity of governance participation in the Collective. Successful proposals, avg. votes per proposal, and others, in multiple timeframes. We also categorize voters based on their governance score to understand participant quality.\n\n- Delegation, including intensity, and quantity of involvement across voting power, delegators, total votes, and voting periods.\n\n- Delegate Coalitions, tracking governance activity of power groups of up to 6 addresses. Together with Delegation, this provides deep analysis of decentralization within Optimism governance.\n\n- Voters Ecosystem, measuring the Collective voters involvement in other DAOs, including competing DAOs.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "New Participants: DeepDAO helps new entrants to the DAO ecosystem discover the OP Collective, ensuring they do not face information asymmetry compared to experienced participants.\n\nDelegates use DeepDAO to stay updated on OP Collective activities. Our analytics dashboard offers extensive information on the DAO's well-being.\n\nBuilders: DeepDAO makes it easy for builders to identify and approach the right delegates for feedback. (using the Delegation, and Coalitions dashboards).\n\nTooling Providers: DeepDAO aggregates information across various tooling providers and includes a tools page listing all DAO tools available to the Optimism Collective.\n\nOP Collective: Our data on coalitions, governance segmentation and voter trends provides multiple indicators of the DAO\u2019s decentralization, governance resilience and security. The Collective benefits immensely from a free resource like DeepDAO.\n\nInvestors, journalists, researchers: 1000s of media articles and academic papers quote DeepDAO data.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x26d1186a0d4350e5b6c362372cacf08b29963e305f5ac08ce48e27eaadc4f8cc",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728930301,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0846b0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0f3235094b4c68b8fa71e1f63d4bd8260d5ecda0d4db9361e5593b45685c35e9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmWxgRHCZFKBA2dM6uCxAw6EesUkWgZ5S8h7RYMmkQUV6o",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Our infrastructure has enhanced Optimism Governance by providing comprehensive security audits and continuous monitoring. In Cycle 19, we audited critical governance systems like the ERC721Bridge contract and OptimismPortal, identifying 14 issues (7 low-risk, 7 informational) that strengthened governance security. Our audits ensure the integrity and reliability of Optimism's voting process and governance tooling, contributing directly to the security and resilience of the entire ecosystem. Through our continuous monitoring and incident response services, we help maintain a secure and transparent governance process for all participants."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of our infrastructure and tooling are Delegates and Citizens participating in Optimism Governance. Our security audits have directly improved the integrity and reliability of the governance process, ensuring that Delegates can vote with confidence and that Citizens can trust the system's safety. Additionally, developers and system maintainers benefit from the insights provided by our audits, which help them resolve vulnerabilities and ensure the continued functionality of governance contracts and tooling. Our work supports a secure, transparent, and reliable governance experience for the Optimism community."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x273b95d847456e4ada5b7230fb5750eb9b943a0974f72d9fcfe59337785aaf6c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728899897,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x05b997"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x62ba2574d6ddd4a3c464185ebf8f2bdf4079057388f14329d75be6e3cb0d4352",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmY5to6nJDQgKd6Gpe7Dj79zX1xWKhyuWJNSYscm2XPnNA",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Superchain.Eco contributed to Optimism Governance by providing easy to access analytics, custom dashboards and relevant research - distributed through our platform which welcomed over 10,000 unique users between Jan 1st, 2024, and Sept 18th, 2024.\n\nOur impact:\nOP Stack Chains insights: Tracked the governance and technical setup of all OP Stack Chains, delivering real-time insights (5k+ users).\n\nCitizens insights: Provided a breakdown of Optimism Collective Citizens and their cumulative rewards through the Citizen Retro program through our website (1k+ users).\n\nOptimism Ecosystem Map: Visually represented the organizational structure of Season 6, including councils and commissions, contributors, and total rewards. \n\nS6 Mission Dashboard: We tracked approved and rejected proposals, remaining budgets, and total requests across the Intents of Season 6.\n\nGovernance Research: We facilitate relevant research through a BountyCaster campaign. 16 submission / 4 winners rewarded and published.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The following Optimism Collective stakeholder group benefits most from our work:\n\nOP Delegates, Citizen and Contributors: Individuals involved in Optimism Collective operations leveraged our platform and resources to get a comprehensive overview of key Governance elements. \n\nOP Chain Contributors: Teams joining the Superchain leveraged our resources to get a better understanding of the Optimism Collective and its functioning, including the various Superchain programs. \n\nOnchain Builders: Our platform allowed builders to better understand how to contribute to Optimism and which programs they could participate in. \n\nOP Token holders and aspiring contributors: Our analytics work and platform allowed a wider audience to remain up to date with all Optimism Collective governance and Superchain developments. Our newsletter, insights and platform have provided context to over ~25K individuals. \n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x27bf248f825bb35b96826de16b2ce2b861537c48d38d937f84196bed67f70a1d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728924665,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04af44"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd972ab3973713dc4b26702c363106f46900620884dcb67bb62522b80dcac9e4c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmWoqmcycbrUvNLkPiKSpnTuV25sRFkCCNJaFw4meDwyiv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "I held AMA sessions with the community to which various developers in Supechain were invited. These developers and project representatives are building tools for working with DeFi and for voting in the ecosystem. \n\nAlso a lot of material was created such as community calls, proposal creation, ecosystem management discussions. \n\nMy work as an Advisor, brought 4 new projects to the ecosystem that were rewarded in RF4. I also continue to work on my own projects and oversee the development of third-party projects that aim to increase the engagement of ecosystem management participants and attract new delegates. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "All of the projects I accompanied for RF have received grants and are now continuing to develop new tools to improve the ecosystem and make delegating work easier for new users. \n\nAlso many of my readers were rewarded with previous airdrops from Optimism for delegating OP and participating in voting. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x28d507c6d2707ff3a7cd27232802d151bf429942b5059adf738aaaa6387f9de6",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728737430,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04d4a2"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xfca61ad1fe4baab999bd07b566c6468626501ebe75ef109e1ce97600e87d9ba2",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXNtdmS5aCZ3r7ZLaBe5fwAEdwLdidvSWvDDWRCL8c5Ns",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "My analytics work measures key aspects of Optimism Governance, including participation rates, decision-making efficiency, voting outcomes, transparency, and proposal quality to enhance community engagement."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Firstly, Delegates and Citizens have gained valuable insights into their participation and decision-making processes. By understanding engagement levels and proposal effectiveness, they can make informed decisions and enhance their governance involvement.\n\nSecondly, community leaders and councils have used these analytics to evaluate governance performance. This information helps identify system strengths and weaknesses, enabling necessary improvements for better engagement and transparency.\n\nLastly, the broader Optimism ecosystem has profited from a more educated community. As members learn more about governance dynamics, the quality of proposals and discussions improves, leading to a stronger and more efficient governance framework.\n\nIn summary, my work has significantly benefited Delegates, Citizens, community leaders, and the entire Optimism ecosystem by promoting informed participation and enhancing the overall governance experience."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x28fcd5b4fff7e7e91535702759a9638ea39e9193446cf57332dff4c7eb2d7e95",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857873,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x297c7878e1911034233762d2fe74d1c9920c45339c5dbc2435bf6485fa4bfb88",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728674766,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x16998b93e766294349ca51aacf532d50a04f0da023684921d98670d29f5ee8e2",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmePctGMRjZCgWSucdixULCPspC5tsxooyoxEN8k3uSm9k",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Grants Council is to oversee the evaluation and approval of projects for Governance Fund grants, ensuring they align with the season's intent andthe mission requests.  \n\nKey responsibilities include:\n\n1. Grant Evaluation: Reviewing and approving grant applications that further the goals of The Collective.\n2. Mission Creation: Developing and proposing Mission Requests aligned with the broader objectives of the Optimism Collective, targeting specific ecosystem needs (Intents).\n3. Ensuring transparency by publishing reports, tracking milestone progress, and maintaining open communication with the community.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Grants Council keeps an updated communication thread here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/s6-grants-council-communication-thread/8324\n\nTo make RF6 voters life easier we compiled all our impact data here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/mid-season-6-grants-council-report/9016\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2aa362c20130f9cc1ebf70030cdca2de3f57a899c11e3bf16a74f06115d46405",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728908036,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x5314"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0a5b755e094eeeb5bc3f8f1b26b781b2be0906f2bc86144768a566141e45caa4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQKm6uEgDrXLT5XKj2Fomhf7W6BmcbyihunCUcFdHquKN",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We built this site in response to forum feedback, where many community members shared feeling overwhelmed by the constantly evolving nature of Optimism governance, in particular the many novel experiments around grant programs.\n\nWhile rapid iteration is good for innovation (yay!), it also made it more challenging to stay up-to-date without first having to \"navigate a maze of forum posts\". We made it easy to access all deadlines and changes to programs in one place.\n\nThis has been well received: In the period between Oct 2023 and Sept 2024, there have been 2.9K outbound link clicks from our site to the Charmverse Grants Council page, 1.1K clicks to the Foundation Mission Requests pages on GitHub, and 605 clicks to forum posts on Retro Funding Rounds."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our site has primarily been useful as tool for supporting those involved in grants processes, including the Grants Council, Retro Funding Rounds and (Foundation) Mission Requests.\n\nThe subscribers of our newsletter where we used to share weekly updates, before then focusing primarily on the website, include employees from OP Labs, OpenZeppelin and Wakeup Labs. \n\nThe teams behind grantee projects such as OpenZeppelin are those who likely benefited most from our overview of the current status of grant programs, upcoming deadlines, our grants calendar, and the changelog. They otherwise would have had a much higher workload by having to keep track of this information across a number of different channels (GitHub, Grants Council Charmverse page, Forum, ...)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2b205539d481c21ed46aab6b258448346c25ddfe6fed2a49a704bc818fbc4437",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728831983,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1cfa24a1212d4b707b48d7b35795fedd3497654e7278e464943e395cf21ed801",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTdFgUswEpM51G1m2CzDRuSy53ppqu7RSiySpDZB8jHHU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Each Badgeholder session has had a different focus given that the needs are matched according to the stage of RetroRounds and the current experiments being carried out:\n\n1. Workshops on the creation of lists for 3 different categories prior to RetroRound3. I designed and ran the workshops in a couple of them with the support of 2 other Badgeholders.\n2. Istanbul Meetup @ Onchain Summit where we gathered to 1) connect, 2) explore thoughts on lists and voting, 3) learn about projects such as Pairwise. Secured a place with the OP team, created merch, and coordinated with Badgeholders attending DevConnect. \n3. Badgies Workshopping @ Eth Denver: Coordinated the event, contacted the presenting teams, and led the session. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Each session has led to different improvements in the process and experiments of RetroRounds. \nFor the first two, the outcomes are described above. \n\nFor the 3 Session, here is some additional information:\n\nIn this session the following teams presented and received feedback from Badgeholders and the Foundation:\n1. EZKL - https://retrofunding.ezkl.xyz/\n2. Buidl Guild - Metrics Based Voting\n3. Agora \n4. Pairwise\n5. EasyRPGF\n\n This session particularly informed changes in the design of voting for Round 4, the release of EZKL's proving system for Retro3 results, among other things.  "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2b721fbb1a10fe402978ab22e6d35a29ef48a735230b7c770b14f225143fc451",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857081,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2888"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x13b3336b6989a66fc2d1725b796f38f22e872881243f86e85b03a120960afb38",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbRQr7yrhgXGLi4Cn5j2ueRvLgBAKdD8BitFoWZautFxv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Gitcoin developed the voting interfaces for Retrofunding 4 & Retrofunding 5, which were used by badgeholders to allocate funds during those rounds.\n\nFor RF4, we worked closely with Open Source Observer and Optimism to implement new metrics-based discovery, selection, and weighting. Our solution allowed users to filter and evaluate projects based on various impact metrics. \n\nFor both RF 4 & RF5, we created a user-friendly interface for governance participants to allocate their votes. \n\nThese tools are primarily used within Optimism Governance to support the Retroactive Public Goods Funding process, which is a crucial part of Optimism's governance model. They aim to make the process of discovering, evaluating, and voting for projects more efficient, transparent, and user-friendly for governance participants."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The direct benefits are the Optimism badgeholders and recipients of Retrofunding. During RF4, 108 out of 133 badgeholders participated. $10M OP tokens were allocated to 207 projects. \n\nThough RF5 is still ongoing at the time of this application, participation is high. Badgeholders are expected to allocate between 2-8m OP tokens to up to 89 projects.\n\nThe team has also integrated these features into EasyRetroPGF.xyz, which makes them available to a wider range of users involved in Optimism's governance processes. The SUNNYS Awards have also been built on this same technology!"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2c269a72b290769e77786afdea519aab34b4b96964d0b028a4bdfdac24a147e2",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728826473,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2888b2d5735a0844dd9bdc4ac4ec022be0a26fa886d8329727a49d69741262d0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYvFqHnPV1Yyk8HRztMtAEAt4nmKPn6kafuAp22DvP2pX",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "The numbaNERDs Program measures several key aspects of Optimism Governance:\n\nGrant Utilization: Tracking how funds are used by recipients and whether milestones are met, ensuring proper fund allocation.\n\nGrants Misuse: Validating reports of misuse through the grants misuse reporting policy, ensuring accountability and corrective actions.\n\nContributor Validation: Ensuring data accuracy by having numbaNERDs validate key reports for governance decisions.\n\nGovernance Accountability: Monitoring protocol adherence to governance rules and enforcing consequences for violations.\n\nData Infrastructure: Building analytics infrastructure for various protocols, initially on OP Mainnet, and later expanding to early Superchain members.\n\nThese analytics strengthen transparency, accountability, and decision-making across Optimism\u2019s governance.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The numbaNERDs Program has significantly advanced governance-related analytics, data infrastructure, and transparency within the Optimism ecosystem, fostering growth and enabling informed decision-making. With 95 bounties completed and 3 grants misuse reports validated by numbaNERDs, the collective contributions of the numbaNERDs community have propelled Optimism's data infrastructure to excel beyond any other protocol in the blockchain ecosystem.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2c375efead7b6ed8a7730381ca81a0327fb190aa7d07dfa737ddea2104e4024c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728851359,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2c6e7bcf3c8e41232e0dcc26834bcf2f125621b91e74f91bf0c34639ba306fc9",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728883159,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x336d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcce5500b020a4efe92eed7cec0e465f75a651f8fd6098b5adf5d0a01204f01c9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPhoU34bMBEc3twt17psK65xEPqVm9X9TbSuzEfjxdtVN",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "A list of 104 Retro Funding badgeholders on X is actively followed by over 100 delegates and members of the Optimism community. This list helps them stay updated on badgeholder discussions, the latest governance updates, Superchain developments, and Retro Funding rounds.\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Projects within the Optimism ecosystem greatly benefited from the Retro Funding badgeholders list, enabling them to stay informed and engage with badgeholders publicly. This list also helped Retro Funding badgeholders and delegates keep track of the latest tools and discussions surrounding Retro Funding. Here's what the community had to say:\n\nhttps://x.com/RosmariDigital/status/1732124629810946528\nhttps://discuss.octant.app/t/eth-daily-ethereum-news/164/2\n\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2c8be1c6d2a7ca64b7c289d27f3b0d93d105032cefec5293211ee936c23751de",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929127,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0acc5b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x91f37e8fe55fed5f9bc75cb5f2f4d9929767ee49ef97a78cdb956dac247e1676",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXKpBiGRnKoigEpTGjNEhtudLMHDr5of2pt6b1JsNbWs3",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "**Discord Praise Bot:**\n\nAllows users to praise one another within their community for contributions, which are then stored and minted as on-chain attestations on Optimism Network.\n\nFacilitates community recognition and builds trust through transparent records of contributions.\nSince Oct 1st, 2023 to Sep 18th, 2024, We had a total of 642 Praises. Each one a statement of gratitude, as well as reputational data. \n\n200+ Active users \n\n\n\n**Praise on Farcaster:**\n\nIntegrates Praise\u2019s attestation capabilities onto Farcaster. Users can tag @givepraise to publicly appreciate other Farcaster accounts.\n\nFarcaster Frame Praise Attestations lowers the barrier to entry for creating user reputation, contributing to proof of uniqueness and reputation scores across the Web3 ecosystem.\n\n236 attestations minted since the launch on Praise Farcaster bot (within 2 weeks)\n\n76 Unique users minted attestations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "**Active Participants in Optimism Governance:**\n\nDelegates & Badgeholders:\n\nCan easily show gratitude\nCan help community members build onchain reputation. \n\nEngaged Community Members:\nGain visibility and reputation through peer recognition.\nBoosts motivation to participate in governance activities.\nBetter vibes\n\n**Individuals Verifying Reputations and Identities:**\n\nOnchain Attestations:\nProvide a transparent and verifiable record of contributions.\nAid in assessing community members' reputations.\n\nTrust Building:\nHelp users make informed decisions within governance.\nLower the barrier to entry for new contributors seeking to build trust.\n\nOverall Impact:\nSimplified the process of acknowledging contributions and verifying reputations.\nStrengthened engagement and collaboration within the Optimism governance ecosystem."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2d7c760301b9e55965f18dfc4f3d48376f2392e0801e192bfdbe3fe43143426e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837878,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x71a31d4439ce5a9874393060e5ddcf16553963e56ed6e75da48757f101787257",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVVWBCTbwHLQdLzPWDha4wJDfp23sFk8w4MjRoNR3bEic",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Impact Evaluation Framework has been used to inform Badgeholders voting in Retro3 by supporting the creation of Lists, providing context into the Collective for new voters inspired metrics generated for Round 4 and onwards for projects contributing to the Collective. \n\nThe Metrics Garden Database, which has served to inform the creation of new Metrics Gardens has also informed the evaluation criteria for RetroRounds from Ecosystems such as libp2p and Filecoin which have enabled to fund downstream Optimism dependencies: https://www.notion.so/a60768062a2e4e5f8b4ea787e73d38b5?v=468228b4f651454aaf4296934a8a18bd\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The governance participants who have benefitted the most from the Impact Evaluation Framework have been Badgeholders who leveraged this tool to inform their voting in Round3.\n\nSome testimonials can be found here:\n- On Lists: https://gov.optimism.io/t/round-3-voting-rationale/7030/5\n- On Impact: https://gov.optimism.io/t/joans-rpgf3-reflections/7221\n- On Voting: https://x.com/brichis_/status/1732146910708806069?s=20\n- On Evaluation Criteria: https://github.com/0xyNaMu/RetroPGF3List_Methodology/tree/ContributorTracks "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2ddf7eed1f17459a4bfe082b95277648415a08e1a1d9d406433ca1d98df7ab76",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728852064,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2e0f97128397ebe29db25dbd4dfd7a147d96b48c5ea66833e84960256ad10722",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857455,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2888"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x59ad253f7fc52b131273a5c1dbd709c3cde2dbb13cd9d3b8bbaa687b5b684082",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbRQr7yrhgXGLi4Cn5j2ueRvLgBAKdD8BitFoWZautFxv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Gitcoin developed the voting interfaces for Retrofunding 4 & Retrofunding 5, which were used by badgeholders to allocate funds during those rounds.\n\nFor RF4, we worked closely with Open Source Observer and Optimism to implement new metrics-based discovery, selection, and weighting. Our solution allowed users to filter and evaluate projects based on various impact metrics. \n\nFor both RF 4 & RF5, we created a user-friendly interface for governance participants to allocate their votes. \n\nThese tools are primarily used within Optimism Governance to support the Retroactive Public Goods Funding process, which is a crucial part of Optimism's governance model. They aim to make the process of discovering, evaluating, and voting for projects more efficient, transparent, and user-friendly for governance participants."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The direct benefits are the Optimism badgeholders and recipients of Retrofunding. During RF4, 108 out of 133 badgeholders participated. $10M OP tokens were allocated to 207 projects. \n\nThough RF5 is still ongoing at the time of this application, participation is high. Badgeholders are expected to allocate between 2-8m OP tokens to up to 89 projects.\n\nThe team has also integrated these features into EasyRetroPGF.xyz, which makes them available to a wider range of users involved in Optimism's governance processes. The SUNNYS Awards have also been built on this same technology!"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x2e615a9836edc5661ee1a4c20e5c84cf5359617c3cecbbb31470a5e8f01fc107",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728886337,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x051b41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xe465941756930987977c33f6d2b62aba4724272e412007f5e416ce46b9c53000",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNsCqK2FS4UbwP22Z2gWHuNstzfP1BQe2tmVwTrrPMwHK",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The impact on this community is to increase the number of Optimse onchain through open media information about optimization developments such as grants, airdrops, retroactives. for example what happened yesterday (airdrop 5 OP), Partner (Layer 3), to Superchain activity."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Spreading the development of optimism information through the telegram channel (@airdropfinder) with 567k members. This can help spread widely to other OP communities and not only telegram, RPS1N spreads through social media accounts such as x (twitter)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x336ac39aefc89a9f2bb8832f362074d32a95a9d6fabec9195d0a162fcf23ff01",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728932322,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf17ee19c8307170ca4d77c571580e8ad2f304727360b582f97cd4bc466707e9e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmby7ruuCgS2ReuSXxccWuJjJAwojyqjjDa1P5597L5VCx",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Optimystics Tools has supported Optimism Governance by providing and maintaining essential infrastructure for decentralized decision-making over the past year:\n\n1. Initial Toolset: Our core tools have facilitated weekly Optimism Fractal events, enabling consistent governance experimentation and community building.\n\n2. Respect Infrastructure: We've maintained and upgraded the system for distributing Respect tokens, enabling a decentralized distribution amongst leading builders and governance enthusiasts.\n\n3. Council Support: Our tools have enabled the weekly formation and operation of the Optimism Fractal council, demonstrating scalable governance models and creating a well-organized governance body for the Collective.\n\nThis consistent infrastructure has allowed for the release of next-generation tools like ORDAO, Fractalgram, and the Respect Games app. It\u2019s enabled a community-driven effort with multiple development teams contributing to a growing toolkit of fractal governance tooling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Builders, leaders, delegates, and other key stakeholders in the Collective have used our tools at Optimism Fractal events to earn Respect and contribute to decentralized decision-making experiments.\n\n2. Our open-source infrastructure has served as a foundation for further governance innovations on Optimism, empowering researchers and developers interested in decentralized governance.\n\n3. Our tools have provided models and insights that could enhance various governance processes, including the Token House, Citizens' House, RetroFunding, and the Anti-Capture Commission.\n\n4. Other groups like the ZAO Fractal have adopted processes to engage, govern, and grow their communities on the Superchain. \n\nOur tools have created a vibrant testbed for governance innovations, benefiting anyone interested in exploring and contributing to decentralized decision-making processes on Optimism, and providing valuable data and experiences that can inform the evolution of the Collective's governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x33fe5579037d6fd99af0d4016fddc7170ca48438009e7fad18b1a13a11b0dbbf",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728843635,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x903e374e6261e72a75fd51b98dc1fb63042c66be897d2d621466fbf0845cee7d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRu7tgbTkExnETY4M1MqoqzfJASFMVdZdYd38FTtaavNm",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "RetroList, a project discovery platform for OP Retro Funding, significantly supports Optimism governance by providing detailed analytics and accessible data across Retro Funding rounds 3 to 6.\n\nRetroList also offers detailed analytics for each round, including:\n- Project reward distribution across different reward groups\n- Project reward distribution by category\n- Public crowdsourcing lists for RetroPGF 3\n- Metrics distribution for Retro Funding 4\n- Open-source vs. closed-source project distribution for Retro Funding 4\n- Project reward breakdown by impact metrics for Retro Funding 4\n\nAdditionally, RetroList has provided an API that enables direct data queries by other projects like DeVouch and Impact Garden."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Every stakeholder in the Retro Funding process benefits from RetroList, including:\n- Any user can discover Retro Funding projects and get inspiration to build on the Superchain.\n- Project owners have a UI to check if their project has gone through correctly.\n- Badgeholders, delegates, and the OP Foundation have access to the RetroList analytics, which has an impact on badgeholders' voting decisions and the design of future Retro Funding rounds.\n- Ecosystem projects have access to the API for querying project data within a few days after the sign-up period and maintain a stable schema.\n\nThe RetroList API has been used internally by the DeVouch and Impact Garden projects."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3424fc5cbe589209eb2550cf8c3ab9c7a3047b9459c6decdbdaf67abff5a0326",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728681172,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xbb84f3a7463ca746831ce765bd83b33c13e55712c0b8d1c3e74096a120ca0527",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQwMxbJLBbPU6r5x1yDHkUaxUPuv9LupckcKkPM32Fu4K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\n[Reflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation](https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x349b1e1b81b368b0f951597d4afc1086991761ee34014fde0b0f20d36e8a8ff0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728832011,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x06be135bacb0befa9a0d9af56fa01288537a786efc3cc659347b92204d8bae2e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmR1PZ2BkGTTXQuxr1oKmqkxk7mVmPSAcDNnWYXSxt8ZGZ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Impact Evaluation Framework has been used to inform Badgeholders voting in Retro3 by supporting the creation of Lists, providing context into the Collective for new voters inspired metrics generated for Round 4 and onwards for projects contributing to the Collective. \n\nThe Metrics Garden Database, which has served to inform the creation of new Metrics Gardens has also informed the evaluation criteria for RetroRounds from Ecosystems such as libp2p and Filecoin which have enabled to fund downstream Optimism dependencies: https://www.notion.so/a60768062a2e4e5f8b4ea787e73d38b5?v=468228b4f651454aaf4296934a8a18bd\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The participants who have benefitted the most from the Impact Evaluation Framework have been Badgeholders who leveraged this tool to inform their voting in Round3.\n\nSome testimonials can be found here:\n- On Lists: https://gov.optimism.io/t/round-3-voting-rationale/7030/5\n- On Impact: https://gov.optimism.io/t/joans-rpgf3-reflections/7221\n- On Voting: https://x.com/brichis_/status/1732146910708806069?s=20\n- On Evaluation Criteria: https://github.com/0xyNaMu/RetroPGF3List_Methodology/tree/ContributorTracks"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x34c4562151f640411f641498534e6468eba891343d6c240f3aebe7caf0e05b93",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728751213,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x08aeb4bc57b33ae52cea98678c32d73456572b548760f7470da1631f85083645",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaSpvLBDr1hzD5cDfGWBztHoSJHfRJC2WZUHDMW2HpHDU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analysis measures the participation and behavior of Badgeholders in the Superchain ecosystem, specifically focusing on their transaction activities across networks like OP Mainnet, Base, Zora, and Mode. It also examines their engagement in decentralized applications (DEXs), token transfers, and social platforms like Farcaster. \n\nA key insight is the relatively low activity level of Badgeholders compared to Non-Badgeholders, particularly in areas like DEX trading and smart contract deployment. Additionally, the analysis tracks how Badgeholders' preferences for Ethereum transactions and limited cross-chain activity impact their overall engagement with Optimism's governance processes. \n\nThis helps identify where governance structures may need to be adjusted to include better and activate Badgeholders, ensuring their participation grows alongside the broader ecosystem.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Collective has benefitted most from this analysis, gaining valuable insights into Badgeholder behavior that inform strategies to increase engagement. For example, understanding that Badgeholders are more active on Ethereum but less engaged with smart contract deployment helps the Collective target these users with specific governance initiatives. \n\nFurthermore, the findings around Farcaster connections show the importance of social engagement within this group, which can shape future governance outreach and participation efforts. The insights have also helped governance teams refine their strategies for promoting cross-chain activity and diversifying user engagement. This research will also guide the future selection of new Badgeholders for the Citizen House by identifying gaps and ensuring the House becomes more inclusive and representative of the entire user profile within the Collective, promoting a well-rounded governance structure.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x37e91d46de30b951a7736642b114b73763cccea2cbbfb6ff7553556935af6e7d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728672983,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x3f57"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x36f3e2072476181ff1458a990ebcd9084f0b9b032dd72286e29af111cccc5ca3",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZBzwMhiySVqeK3k7qj4AbQcc2epf1DgLnbAvfRAsAtgk",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Developer Advisory Board (DAB) was reelected in Season 6. [Our charter can be found in the initial budget proposal](https://gov.optimism.io/t/zach-obront-developer-advisory-board-operating-budget/8141), and includes supporting the Optimism ecosystem as follows:\n\n1. Help to ensure the safety of protocol upgrades. We do this by both (a) explicitly approving upgrades before they are allowed to move to a vote and (b) providing plain English summaries of all protocol upgrades to educate other voters.\n\n2. Support the Grants Council by providing detailed technical feedback on all Mission Requests, Mission Applications, and grant milestones.\n\n3. Bring an additional technical perspective to thinking about the vision of the OP ecosystem and what needs to happen to get there.\n\nMore details can be found in our [Internal Operating Procedures](https://gov.optimism.io/t/developer-advisory-board-s6-internal-operating-procedures/8558)."
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "- Provided detailed feedback on [139 mission requests](https://wbnns.notion.site/Developer-Advisory-Board-Impact-11acf4706b47808f8421c409b4c102c6?pvs=4) thus far (105 of which are within the round eligibility period), to aid in evaluation by the Grants Council. The GC Lead has provided an NPS score of 10/10 based on the value of our contributions.\n- Reviewed the Granite Hardfork, formally approved it, and prepared an [extensive and comprehensive non-technical summary](https://gov.optimism.io/t/upgrade-proposal-10-granite-network-upgrade/8733/21) to support other voters.\n- Provided feedback to the Foundation on important projects such as the Decentralization Roadmap and long term Product Vision.\n- Conducted multiple community calls throughout Season 6, [creating an open forum](https://gov.optimism.io/t/developer-advisory-board-feedback-ideas-thread/8580) to get feedback and ideas from the community."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x382eed441fc1d401025c2ec72a50eb45eedf9d4269ee69908b105b30cae1e6fb",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728680988,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTDk3JjFaB6X6ncDc5MtnC3Yp75EZxha5AM1KCjUdS6Zy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x38ad2ef5857c4e8e82016817086e022e0be35d558856fbf4bf342300755ea0f8",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728852813,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x485a"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0e1d68ea2ae821638e1e602220f3e0cc1edd96ce8ac284dfffbccdb1d3d87b33",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRPLGVidoWMGJg95QxKaoakkyfMvv3FWt71m97MmFhCWD",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Badgeholder votes are private. This allows voters to express their true preferences without fear of retaliation, coercion, or pressure from others. It makes it difficult to execute vote buying, and encourages honest participation. It doesn't protect against the vote counter cheating.\n\nEven though the allocation algorithm is public (and we can check that it accurately codifies forum promises), we can\u2019t run a check without the input data. In the worst case, we can\u2019t guarantee that the provided allocation algorithm was even used or that all votes were counted.\n\nWe made this process transparent with zero-knowledge (ZK) proof that legitimate votes were counted and that the allocation algorithm was run as intended, keeping the votes themselves private. Using EZKL, we were able to compile the Python allocation code into a circuit, and provide a proof anyone can verify at https://retrofunding.ezkl.xyz (see https://blog.ezkl.xyz/post/zkrpgf/ for more details).\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The Retroactive Public Goods Funding process ideally improves with each round via governance feedback. We cryptographically audited Round 3 in a replicable way, providing a cryptographic proof any stakeholder can verify in a browser. This paves the way for an end-to-end automated process with private voting, checks and balances on the allocation algorithm, and smart contract enabled allocation delivery\n\nFor stakeholders, this cryptographic audit means many things:\n- For badgeholders, your vote was fairly counted\n- For recipients, your allocation was fairly calculated\n- For everyone else, the results actually correspond with Optimism governance \u2014 governance at work!\n\nBlockchains have both social consensus (which fork is the main one, which client should be run, etc.) and computational consensus. By verifying the RetroPGF results, everyone helps solidify the social consensus around the legitimacy of the vote. You are an election observer, contributing to a successful audit.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x38b3ff6de4de8a2ea770699481586b64827e5ed7aba0adec0f6aa121470565b3",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728681192,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3ad72204694f5e52e0760a29c90ff3c8d1a759dccdb3b4aff061f007ed1bb2d0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728735231,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xafbdb7da88c946def2eceee8a27b7ee32c6cfcb936186d6f8b8fb348c1e8ee30",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYAM4fbd44C8n8oSCuLEgrE7yXm75KaLwq4k2jjYrDob5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Impact Garden is used to gather standardized information on a project's impact to the Optimism Collective beyond that being self reported by applicants. The information collected is linked to the reputation of the person providing the testimonial enabling advanced weighting by the consumer of the data. Higher reputation in the Collective, can mean your testimonial is more relevant in decisions.\n\nFor Round 5, Impact Garden gathered over 100 testimonials for 35+ projects in the round. These testimonials were used by Badgeholders during the review process particularly to determine if projects were in the right sub-category and for additional information. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The audience benefiting the most from the data created by Impact Garden are Badgeholders. \n\nThrough the generation of new data in a standardized format we're bridging the gap and giving numbers, projects and contributions a context about their impact to others within the Collective. This has looked like additional data for Badgeholders in the review process and voting. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3be9ee627e19f49c13cfb8d174b1a2e73d6a8c7ca9c6b2e408eae12bc62332bf",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728820932,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04dbb3"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xfda44b77d881a2c02dee8a5ab2e83f5a13ec91fc1fff667d242844f98984d0f2",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVHirX1o7dB5i8ftBHkKL87oT5RAjMHpDU5etkE1wwsUa",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "OP Passport supports Optimism Governance by providing users with a verifiable, on-chain identity to track and showcase their governance participation. In decentralized governance, it is often difficult to transparently display contributions, voting history, and achievements. OP Passport addresses this challenge by securely storing governance activities and accomplishments through on-chain attestations within users\u2019 smart wallets.\n\nThe tool enables participants to easily demonstrate their active involvement in governance, making it simpler for the community to recognize valuable contributors. Additionally, OP Passport facilitates on-chain endorsements, both public and anonymous, which further enhance transparency and accountability across the governance process."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "OP Passport benefits three key governance participants within the Optimism Collective: delegates, delegators, and badgeholders, all of whom can create their own passports, earn achievements, and give or receive endorsements.\n\nDelegates: OP Passport allows delegates to create an on-chain record of their achievements, showcasing their profile to build trust and increase recognition of their contributions.\n\nDelegators: Delegators can track their delegates' actions and assess how their voting power is used. They can also give and receive endorsements, promoting transparency and accountability.\n\nBadgeholders: Badgeholders can earn achievements and give or receive endorsements, recognizing valuable contributions and fostering transparency in governance.\n\nThrough OP Passport, all participants can create passports, earn achievements, and showcase their governance contributions, strengthening transparency and accountability in the Optimism ecosystem.\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3bf35d39f3842c3724725a257a7047fd987dc76f7df7ee1f263b23568f5ba696",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728830981,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x06be135bacb0befa9a0d9af56fa01288537a786efc3cc659347b92204d8bae2e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmR1PZ2BkGTTXQuxr1oKmqkxk7mVmPSAcDNnWYXSxt8ZGZ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Impact Evaluation Framework has been used to inform Badgeholders voting in Retro3 by supporting the creation of Lists, providing context into the Collective for new voters inspired metrics generated for Round 4 and onwards for projects contributing to the Collective. \n\nThe Metrics Garden Database, which has served to inform the creation of new Metrics Gardens has also informed the evaluation criteria for RetroRounds from Ecosystems such as libp2p and Filecoin which have enabled to fund downstream Optimism dependencies: https://www.notion.so/a60768062a2e4e5f8b4ea787e73d38b5?v=468228b4f651454aaf4296934a8a18bd\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The participants who have benefitted the most from the Impact Evaluation Framework have been Badgeholders who leveraged this tool to inform their voting in Round3.\n\nSome testimonials can be found here:\n- On Lists: https://gov.optimism.io/t/round-3-voting-rationale/7030/5\n- On Impact: https://gov.optimism.io/t/joans-rpgf3-reflections/7221\n- On Voting: https://x.com/brichis_/status/1732146910708806069?s=20\n- On Evaluation Criteria: https://github.com/0xyNaMu/RetroPGF3List_Methodology/tree/ContributorTracks"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x3e3a93f0ceb59773d37e2603f5a75543db81d3aa058dd48101b185f3392b0ca4",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728927424,
    "round": "5",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0846b0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd9418b70284517b72913fc585657fde36417a4262dcaf5e080ba5b17102d5f51",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmetcT7oT6dBdBfjtKM1Qz9QffakzZFCKQP8HyMDyuqyi2",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 5,
      "category": "OP Stack Research & Development",
      "subcategory": [
        "Security audits specifically on the OP Stack or its components."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How has your project advanced the development of the OP Stack?",
          "answer": "Cantina/Spearbit has advanced the development of the OP Stack by providing critical security audits and reviews to ensure the robustness and safety of its components. Our team has conducted multiple audits of the OP Stack, including security reviews of Optimism's EAS, which are crucial for cross-chain functionality and gas optimization. Through these audits, we have identified vulnerabilities, suggested optimizations, and collaborated with Optimism team to ensure that the OP Stack is secure and resilient.\n\nAdditionally, our continuous monitoring, advisory services, and incident response support help maintain the OP Stack's reliability, safeguarding its smart contracts and infrastructure.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited the most from your work on the OP Stack and how?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of our work on the OP Stack have been developers and projects building within the Optimism ecosystem, as well as the broader Optimism community. By conducting thorough security audits, we have ensured that developers can deploy secure smart contracts, reducing the risk of exploits and vulnerabilities.\n\nProjects like Omni-x and Decent.xyz, which rely on cross-chain capabilities and transaction efficiency, have directly benefited from our security reviews, enabling them to operate safely and scale their solutions across multiple chains.\n\nOur work has enhanced trust and reliability in the OP Stack, making it safer for both developers and users."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x40a3500c980d7b9a780d4990e66ec2ec0e2ee81e43192b0927699d6466e49929",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728868009,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0949f0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x227e6f560e88831622274ce48937b3cd82661ffb4398211593dc15ce07f3c43c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTywmY15w8GFmTSa8XRcHhAMJiVk9XjPTgTyWNGZHBTjh",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "While Metagov's general project have not been specifically focused on Optimism's governance, we have had a variety of projects meant to help advance governance in digital communities. From projects like Exit to Community and the Open Source transition calculator (exploring the costs of governance transitions and actualizing progressive decentralization) to projects like KOI Pond (using LLMs to increase sense making), Metagov is exploring research and tools that have a lot of relevant to Optimism and other DAOs/ "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Our work is generally consumed by those who are researching, studying or building systems pertaining to governance. Our community involves those interested in DAOs, coops, commons, and open source projects. The information is open to all and meant to help people enact governance systems that empower individuals and communities. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x40d4bd41b3f89c281a573bbd032873578a4c30076595280e66546b4be87cf0eb",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928553,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03d7a2"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x512c2031eb33624359c4977754cc691b2f480be9a2f0c5e532257551863db3f8",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaVtgM9eWKWrsTU516UsB3rXYCVU3BcY933wP6d7Z1K5S",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The RetroPGF Community supported the design and execution of Retro Funding 3, 4, and 5 by:\n\n-Amplifying Retro Funding Initiatives: Through educational content, event sponsorship, and community building, RetroPGF Community made Retro Funding more accessible and onboarded new participants.\n\n-Community Engagement: Although not directly involved in proposal creation, the community held sessions at events and used platforms like Twitter and newsletters to keep participants informed about Retro Funding processes.\n\n-Research & Transparency: The community produced case studies and documented funded projects, helping governance participants make informed decisions.\n\nMetrics since October 2023:\n-636.9K impressions\n-5.1% engagement rate\n-3.9K profile visits\n-2.1K new follows\n-859 replies\n-8.4K likes\n-1.5K reposts\n-363 bookmarks\n-90 shares\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "-Governance Participants: Benefited from increased awareness and understanding of the Retro Funding process.\n\n-New Projects & Public Goods: Onboarding efforts brought new projects into the Optimism ecosystem, especially public goods aligned with governance goals.\n\n-Optimism Ecosystem: Expanded participation in governance, making it more transparent and accessible for a diverse audience.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x416962a5119e88d503b2235ed6547658d69ed3dcb8a611a3e14f44fa5d89cd9e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728673951,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9105dd05ea29b7c53e047f2c90e53737749f2e0d588dc1bb882257353d362f24",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbJy3eWk3GPQWjJsMLffSWzVFSTDwE2jQrwVFZuZPKjwT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\n**Relevant Documentation:**\n* [Anticapture Commission Charter](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889)\n* [Anticapture Commission Communication Thread](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501)\n* [Season 5 Retrospective](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108)\n* [Internal Operating Procedures](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348)\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) met its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any single entity. It increased votable supply by 24% and **initiated discussions that led to on-chain protocol upgrades.** The ACC built its Internal Operating Procedures (IOP) from scratch, defining voting protocols, communication channels, and reporting processes. Regular Office Hours ensured direct community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were needed.\n\n**Key Impacts:**\n* **Votable Supply:** Increased from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n* **Delegate Engagement:** 165 of 269 approvals in key voting cycles.\n* **Operational Development:** Established IOP and refined governance processes.\n* **Community Engagement:** Held Office Hours every voting cycle.\n\n*More details [here.](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108)* \n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x41ffd2b13c3b0b5e0314e55d4c316d014dff5211cf2a2f6d490f4e750fd6560f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728829745,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02feec"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x12de53e1ba15f18f1cc8737bf7453d92b3c32005cc5572526a25a04472b297ff",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVUjwv8FJvrLyKYEdvhNyaStBDKe55FZ5Wh3PezzkstaT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We use Soul bound token based on Optimism network, any DAO can use LXDAO's governance mechanism, within LXDAO, every public item needs to go through a proposal to be born, we have designed and implemented a complete set of governance mechanism, so far more than 10 public items have been born in LXDAO!\nWe adopt Optimism-based point system to determine the contribution, LXPoints is based on Optimism's Soul Bound Token, members earn LXPoints through actual contribution, so far more than 138 members have earned LXPoints through contribution."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Optimism Collective, any member who joins LXDAO will get Optimism based Soul Bound Token by contributing, so far more than 138 members have got LXPonts and 94 members have got LXB (Governance Identity), by using this set of Governance Mechanisms, we also spread the At the same time, Optimismcn.eth incubated by LXDAO is currently ranked 52nd in the Optimism Delegate, and is also deeply involved in Optimism governance.\n\n2. Other DAO organizations, our governance mechanism and Soul Bound Token are completely open source, any DAO organization can adopt this set to start their own DAO governance\n\n3. Web3 newcomers, any newcomer to LXDAO can learn how DAO works, and also learn about on-chain governance, DAO operation mode, etc. Currently, LXDAO has 542 registered members.\nhttps://lxdao.io/buidlers\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4251706007bc281dc9d9109d3fbd08ee5055b2b7f8a4b7e0e7670aabd4e54b7e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928038,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x903e374e6261e72a75fd51b98dc1fb63042c66be897d2d621466fbf0845cee7d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRu7tgbTkExnETY4M1MqoqzfJASFMVdZdYd38FTtaavNm",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "RetroList, a project discovery platform for OP Retro Funding, significantly supports Optimism governance by providing detailed analytics and accessible data across Retro Funding rounds 3 to 6.\n\nRetroList also offers detailed analytics for each round, including:\n- Project reward distribution across different reward groups\n- Project reward distribution by category\n- Public crowdsourcing lists for RetroPGF 3\n- Metrics distribution for Retro Funding 4\n- Open-source vs. closed-source project distribution for Retro Funding 4\n- Project reward breakdown by impact metrics for Retro Funding 4\n\nAdditionally, RetroList has provided an API that enables direct data queries by other projects like DeVouch and Impact Garden."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Every stakeholder in the Retro Funding process benefits from RetroList, including:\n- Any user can discover Retro Funding projects and get inspiration to build on the Superchain.\n- Project owners have a UI to check if their project has gone through correctly.\n- Badgeholders, delegates, and the OP Foundation have access to the RetroList analytics, which has an impact on badgeholders' voting decisions and the design of future Retro Funding rounds.\n- Ecosystem projects have access to the API for querying project data within a few days after the sign-up period and maintain a stable schema.\n\nThe RetroList API has been used internally by the DeVouch and Impact Garden projects."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x44b3d19b6768450be882b71a5cc5a211cc3d2989af67d6dc1c17bfa7b071a74c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928789,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x604045aaf89932382c171101509227d2ec51a0fbb67e2ae5954ab4284cdd75a1",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmby7ruuCgS2ReuSXxccWuJjJAwojyqjjDa1P5597L5VCx",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Optimystics Tools has supported Optimism Governance by providing and maintaining essential infrastructure for decentralized decision-making over the past year:\n\n1. Initial Toolset: Our core tools have facilitated weekly Optimism Fractal events, enabling consistent governance experimentation and community building.\n\n2. Respect Infrastructure: We've maintained and upgraded the system for distributing Respect tokens, enabling a decentralized distribution amongst leading builders and governance enthusiasts.\n\n3. Council Support: Our tools have enabled the weekly formation and operation of the Optimism Fractal council, demonstrating scalable governance models and creating a well-organized governance body for the Collective.\n\nThis consistent infrastructure has allowed for the release of next-generation tools like ORDAO, Fractalgram, and the Respect Games app. It\u2019s enabled a community-driven effort with multiple development teams contributing to a growing toolkit of fractal governance tooling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Builders, leaders, delegates, and other key stakeholders in the Collective have used our tools at Optimism Fractal events to earn Respect and contribute to decentralized decision-making experiments.\n\n2. Our open-source infrastructure has served as a foundation for further governance innovations on Optimism, empowering researchers and developers interested in decentralized governance.\n\n3. Our tools have provided models and insights that could enhance various governance processes, including the Token House, Citizens' House, RetroFunding, and the Anti-Capture Commission.\n\n4. Other groups like the ZAO Fractal have adopted processes to engage, govern, and grow their communities on the Superchain. \n\nOur tools have created a vibrant testbed for governance innovations, benefiting anyone interested in exploring and contributing to decentralized decision-making processes on Optimism, and providing valuable data and experiences that can inform the evolution of the Collective's governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x44e9b4138a6b6d50d33325625560e00836b20613a1689175fb9855e526d8c16e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928253,
    "round": "5",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0846b0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9b9a9e1156339827fd48e9a7d48085160252aea10b3075910ea5787d4cfe7209",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmetcT7oT6dBdBfjtKM1Qz9QffakzZFCKQP8HyMDyuqyi2",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 5,
      "category": "OP Stack Research & Development",
      "subcategory": [
        "Security audits specifically on the OP Stack or its components."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How has your project advanced the development of the OP Stack?",
          "answer": "Cantina/Spearbit has advanced the development of the OP Stack by providing critical security audits and reviews to ensure the robustness and safety of its components. Our team has conducted multiple audits of the OP Stack, including security reviews of Optimism's EAS, which are crucial for cross-chain functionality and gas optimization. Through these audits, we have identified vulnerabilities, suggested optimizations, and collaborated with Optimism team to ensure that the OP Stack is secure and resilient.\n\nAdditionally, our continuous monitoring, advisory services, and incident response support help maintain the OP Stack's reliability, safeguarding its smart contracts and infrastructure.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited the most from your work on the OP Stack and how?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of our work on the OP Stack have been developers and projects building within the Optimism ecosystem, as well as the broader Optimism community. By conducting thorough security audits, we have ensured that developers can deploy secure smart contracts, reducing the risk of exploits and vulnerabilities.\n\nProjects like Omni-x and Decent.xyz, which rely on cross-chain capabilities and transaction efficiency, have directly benefited from our security reviews, enabling them to operate safely and scale their solutions across multiple chains.\n\nOur work has enhanced trust and reliability in the OP Stack, making it safer for both developers and users."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x46cafb6b585b85ea7dc5b9c5a15e67d4e7de4a478daf0090753b44b4bb41cccd",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728885264,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x051b41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x3f4380fc488e8660e491676dedfde230ea203144ac347a83ce009f8610a0b967",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNsCqK2FS4UbwP22Z2gWHuNstzfP1BQe2tmVwTrrPMwHK",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The impact on this community is to increase the number of Optimse onchain through open media information about optimization developments such as grants, airdrops, retroactives. for example what happened yesterday (airdrop 5 OP), Partner (Layer 3), to Superchain activity."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Spreading the development of optimism information through the telegram channel (@airdropfinder) with 567k members. This can help spread widely to other OP communities and not only telegram, RPS1N spreads through social media accounts such as x (twitter)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x48abe67c36f175de87051d187a06e1f03b47abb986cf88953fa0cead7e9d152b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728830956,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x48c74d7752570734ffc15b06365d01a06241f41bf8d382b4b69486908551ed7e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728830948,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1cfa24a1212d4b707b48d7b35795fedd3497654e7278e464943e395cf21ed801",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTdFgUswEpM51G1m2CzDRuSy53ppqu7RSiySpDZB8jHHU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Each Badgeholder session has had a different focus given that the needs are matched according to the stage of RetroRounds and the current experiments being carried out:\n\n1. Workshops on the creation of lists for 3 different categories prior to RetroRound3. I designed and ran the workshops in a couple of them with the support of 2 other Badgeholders.\n2. Istanbul Meetup @ Onchain Summit where we gathered to 1) connect, 2) explore thoughts on lists and voting, 3) learn about projects such as Pairwise. Secured a place with the OP team, created merch, and coordinated with Badgeholders attending DevConnect. \n3. Badgies Workshopping @ Eth Denver: Coordinated the event, contacted the presenting teams, and led the session. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Each session has led to different improvements in the process and experiments of RetroRounds. \nFor the first two, the outcomes are described above. \n\nFor the 3 Session, here is some additional information:\n\nIn this session the following teams presented and received feedback from Badgeholders and the Foundation:\n1. EZKL - https://retrofunding.ezkl.xyz/\n2. Buidl Guild - Metrics Based Voting\n3. Agora \n4. Pairwise\n5. EasyRPGF\n\n This session particularly informed changes in the design of voting for Round 4, the release of EZKL's proving system for Retro3 results, among other things.  "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x48f41f3407391b7198b7d2b78216feec93e1388740d9935b7645612fcf5c5223",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728829736,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02feec"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x84fe41a608d3e9e36f429fe17fcf72aaff8ed6ceacd68602d5d5ba288444178b",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmR2boiBDD3FkY2HiDDXQ6YZtUm8yyB9ArCiDrrJDYtUEK",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "FairSharing is a collaboration tool based on the Optimism network, where anyone and any organization can use FairSharing to achieve collaboration and distribution. FairSharing can publicly and transparently record everyone's contributions, and nearly 50 organizations and projects are currently using FairSharing to record contributions.\n\nThe underlying layer of FairSharing uses EAS as a record of contributions. When users confirm their contributions, they need to submit their Claim requests on the Optimism network to receive their incentive shares."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Optimism Collective: Anyone on Optimism can register and allocate based on FairSharing, and it provides fundamental governance tools.\n\n2. DAOs: Collaboration within DAOs requires transparency and traceability. FairSharing can meet this need, and ultimately all records will be chain-stored, fulfilling the requirement for transparency.\n\n3. Public Goods Projects: It can assist public goods in better tracking contributions, recording contributors to public goods, and facilitating the subsequent tracing of impact and incentives."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4904c0e72694d140f5f3e3024c1438e9bf71a87849908883fd2777f788c51221",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728744215,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0a0137"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xde4f4e205eef49617d2d33f4cf728e55c8e8b226784653aa224b8c682d6c8817",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaS38jFDBswSWGJrVVm7yUBqPyStkvEoY2wAp6dxC9cRy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "A Vault is a secure smart contract that functions as a simple, safe savings account for your hot wallet. It allows you to deposit tokens and NFTs, set withdrawal limits, whitelist addresses, and require multiple signers for transactions. Vaults help keep your assets safe from drainers, hacks, open approvals, and lost or leaked private keys, making it an effective way to enhance the security and management of your digital assets.\n\nWe built in the abilty to allow delegates to easily delegate their tokens securely from their vault. This supports governance processes while maintaining asset safety for users."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Delegators\nDelegators have greatly benefited from the Vault's security features. By using the Vault to delegate tokens securely, delegators can confidently participate in governance processes without risking the transfer of tokens to third parties or insecure platforms byusing hot wallets. This ensures that their delegated assets remain protected from hacks, drainers, and other malicious activities and gives them a simple way to delegate vs exchanges which cant.\n\nThis enhances the overall participation in Optimism\u2019s decentralized governance by lowering barriers to involvement while maintaining security.\n\nDelegates\nDelegates, who are entrusted with the critical role of voting on behalf of token holders, have been one of the key beneficiaries of the Vault's infrastructure. Through the Vault, delegates can receive more votes securely, enabling them to effectively get larger delegations."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x49a166e41697f3feea77bb9003d154e47a2ca289c6ecee36766204acf48e8147",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728921938,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x058237"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd7f5a0320f10eb0b7575efa852b0e4e8340164fb45e1beb9a981c87243aefbdf",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSypk6tAVuxbpmcEJ6xrQGpw9fUffacx7goL2Uow4kBkS",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "GovXS analyzed the voting designs used in Optimism Retro Funding across Rounds 1\u20134, focusing on whether voters were incentivized to truthfully report their preferences. Our analysis uncovered a critical flaw: none of the voting rules applied so far are strategyproof! \nIn other words, voters can gain an advantage by not voting according to their true preferences. To fix this, we proposed two alternative voting solutions, along with clear, actionable recommendations for their implementation."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "a) **Optimism Retro Funding Program:** GovXS\u2019s advanced analytics have empowered the OP Retro Funding Program to identify and solve critical flaws and enable a strategyproof voting that upholds the integrity of retro funding.\nb) **Optimism Retro Funding badgeholders, experts, and guest voters:** Badgeholders, experts and guest voters gain trust that voting outcomes reflect the true preferences of all participants.\nc) **Optimism Retro Funding projects:** With GovXS\u2019s analytics-driven recommendations, Optimism Retro Funding projects have confidence in a voting process that guarantees fair compensation through transparent, objective assessments.\nd) **Superchain Ecosystem:** Optimism\u2019s Retro Funding strives to achieve a true, fair allocation of rewards. Flawed voting rules distort outcomes, preventing Optimism Retro Funding from realizing its goal of aligning 'Impact = Profit.' GovXs\u2019s analysis provided actionable solutions to safeguard this vision for the long term."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4a02225b7b2d9fc169b49dc8ca871ac8b30a247bd7baeb3f8c9a1f0107a17d58",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728931806,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x604045aaf89932382c171101509227d2ec51a0fbb67e2ae5954ab4284cdd75a1",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmby7ruuCgS2ReuSXxccWuJjJAwojyqjjDa1P5597L5VCx",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Optimystics Tools has supported Optimism Governance by providing and maintaining essential infrastructure for decentralized decision-making over the past year:\n\n1. Initial Toolset: Our core tools have facilitated weekly Optimism Fractal events, enabling consistent governance experimentation and community building.\n\n2. Respect Infrastructure: We've maintained and upgraded the system for distributing Respect tokens, enabling a decentralized distribution amongst leading builders and governance enthusiasts.\n\n3. Council Support: Our tools have enabled the weekly formation and operation of the Optimism Fractal council, demonstrating scalable governance models and creating a well-organized governance body for the Collective.\n\nThis consistent infrastructure has allowed for the release of next-generation tools like ORDAO, Fractalgram, and the Respect Games app. It\u2019s enabled a community-driven effort with multiple development teams contributing to a growing toolkit of fractal governance tooling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Builders, leaders, delegates, and other key stakeholders in the Collective have used our tools at Optimism Fractal events to earn Respect and contribute to decentralized decision-making experiments.\n\n2. Our open-source infrastructure has served as a foundation for further governance innovations on Optimism, empowering researchers and developers interested in decentralized governance.\n\n3. Our tools have provided models and insights that could enhance various governance processes, including the Token House, Citizens' House, RetroFunding, and the Anti-Capture Commission.\n\n4. Other groups like the ZAO Fractal have adopted processes to engage, govern, and grow their communities on the Superchain. \n\nOur tools have created a vibrant testbed for governance innovations, benefiting anyone interested in exploring and contributing to decentralized decision-making processes on Optimism, and providing valuable data and experiences that can inform the evolution of the Collective's governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4b2e48f69b24d7c0548dc0b8ce58e33483e85065362e32024275bfab7d136b1b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728922126,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4948e02cb5a7717dfead47ab54ea3ef927990fb4e240cdfd246b2b0dc919ecea",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4b685b911cf15f34d241b40c86cb5ad19659340812c359986aaec496deaeb85f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728709550,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2cacdcb1ea981e190aaf9051eb3308509dd2be6abe57f2f209f49237c2474571",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTr1uEZDVLgd9a49or745Vbx612HNnAWcS4YKpvTyte5R",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4b82b685406acfd3caa2ac5d7ea1159905d019aad45607522b4a840bf901a2d1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728741459,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0a0137"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xde4f4e205eef49617d2d33f4cf728e55c8e8b226784653aa224b8c682d6c8817",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmeExVbsmfSxVgBGhZVPSPckm3vTGnjoQJBy8FN5JGHA41",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "A Vault is a secure smart contract that functions as a simple, safe savings account for your hot wallet. It allows you to deposit tokens and NFTs, set withdrawal limits, whitelist addresses, and require multiple signers for transactions. Vaults help keep your assets safe from drainers, hacks, open approvals, and lost or leaked private keys, making it an effective way to enhance the security and management of your digital assets.\n\nWe built in the abilty to allow delegates to easily delegate their tokens securely from their vault. This supports governance processes while maintaining asset safety for users."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Delegators\nDelegators, who are entrusted with voting on behalf of token holders, have greatly benefited from the Vault's security features. By using the Vault to delegate tokens securely, delegators can confidently participate in governance processes without risking the transfer of tokens to third parties or insecure platforms byusing hot wallets. This ensures that their delegated assets remain protected from hacks, drainers, and other malicious activities and gives them a simple way to delegate vs exchanges which cant.\n\nThis enhances the overall participation in Optimism\u2019s decentralized governance by lowering barriers to involvement while maintaining security.\n\nDelegates\nDelegates, who are entrusted with the critical role of voting on behalf of token holders, have been one of the key beneficiaries of the Vault's infrastructure. Through the Vault, delegates can receive more votes securely, enabling them to effectively get larger delegations."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4d18e95885810c32e133d282298f424f15f4670f98d09c444fb455acfd1d6d32",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728767241,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0cda2e"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2d19c8c56a93527fdcdc23b94931d8691008e0b02910e97b028f95c5ae7962db",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUAdgwXGfsMYyo7miTZo3wNgCVS9YV1f9soFEi84jiwJK",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Impact Calculator played a pivotal role in shaping the design and accelerating the development of Retro Funding 4, which focused primarily on measuring the tangible impact of each project rather than their popularity. \n\nOur research focused on converting raw data into a quantifiable metric, providing a clearer, more objective way to estimate the real-world contributions of each project. This innovation streamlined the evaluation process for badgeholders, enabling them to spend less time on assessments while ensuring that projects with the highest impact received the recognition and support they deserved.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Small builders especially benefit from our findings, as they no longer need to focus on large, well-known projects to gain the funding they deserve. By creating impactful projects, even on a smaller scale, they can access Retro Funding, which rewards contributions based on impact rather than recognition.\n\nBadgeholders also benefit from this approach, as we\u2019ve automated much of the data they previously needed to review manually. This simplification makes the voting process more efficient, allowing them to focus on evaluating projects quickly and accurately, while maintaining a fair and transparent funding process.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4d5e9773c15ce2d182b618ec7a7afa417bc9728a5866af38c9b86d5a6039e259",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837248,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb8ec23495a33047435b8b0160668f16f07c51a2af8abb2ba7a0b7558d5103c6c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmR1PZ2BkGTTXQuxr1oKmqkxk7mVmPSAcDNnWYXSxt8ZGZ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Impact Evaluation Framework has been used to inform Badgeholders voting in Retro3 by supporting the creation of Lists, providing context into the Collective for new voters inspired metrics generated for Round 4 and onwards for projects contributing to the Collective. \n\nThe Metrics Garden Database, which has served to inform the creation of new Metrics Gardens has also informed the evaluation criteria for RetroRounds from Ecosystems such as libp2p and Filecoin which have enabled to fund downstream Optimism dependencies: https://www.notion.so/a60768062a2e4e5f8b4ea787e73d38b5?v=468228b4f651454aaf4296934a8a18bd\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The participants who have benefitted the most from the Impact Evaluation Framework have been Badgeholders who leveraged this tool to inform their voting in Round3.\n\nSome testimonials can be found here:\n- On Lists: https://gov.optimism.io/t/round-3-voting-rationale/7030/5\n- On Impact: https://gov.optimism.io/t/joans-rpgf3-reflections/7221\n- On Voting: https://x.com/brichis_/status/1732146910708806069?s=20\n- On Evaluation Criteria: https://github.com/0xyNaMu/RetroPGF3List_Methodology/tree/ContributorTracks"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4d8574f4eea1624e71adeef01e4e100286f160a7cdb6565d9559b2cc12180760",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728902485,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x5314"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9956299dd587d6b16af54fba8a7fc1df643cd6a5f834236f070fff218cd79480",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZ3kRfMi8g64crrG99JzwezDHPxiZb6gomitCwogbPeCF",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We built this site in response to forum feedback, where many community members shared feeling overwhelmed by the constantly evolving nature of Optimism governance, in particular the many novel experiments around grant programs.\n\nWhile rapid iteration is good for innovation (yay!), it also made it more challenging to stay up-to-date without first having to \"navigate a maze of forum posts\". We made it easy to access all deadlines and changes to programs in one place.\n\nThis has been well received: In the period between Oct 2023 and Sept 2024, there have been 2.9K outbound link clicks from our site to the Charmverse Grants Council page, 1.1K clicks to the Foundation Mission Requests pages on GitHub, and 605 clicks to forum posts on Retro Funding Rounds."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our site has primarily been useful as tool for supporting those involved in grants processes, including the Grants Council, Retro Funding Rounds and (Foundation) Mission Requests.\n\nThe subscribers of our newsletter though which we used to share weekly updates, before then focusing primarily on the website, included employees from OP Labs, OpenZeppelin and Wakeup Labs. \n\nGrant applicants from projects such as OpenZeppelin are also those who benefited most from our overview of the current status of grant programs, upcoming deadlines, and the changelog. They otherwise would have had a much higher workload by having to keep track of this information across a number of different channels (GitHub, Grants Council Charmverse page, Forum, ...)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4de76fa3ed1d596896e4bbec0f89c60eb7ac8a66197b39604fe43282e99df671",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728889383,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x051b41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9825de4378cee51d32c5203c9ddb1482ba2fb70ab0338c98cf403ab4cde8a206",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXi2fyGB1iLQ9iUtzrqXCmRwtkj22NjsjbA3WSUDApDw6",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The impact on this community is to increase the number of Optimse onchain through open media information about optimization developments such as grants, airdrops, retroactives. for example what happened yesterday (airdrop 5 OP), Partner (Layer 3), to Superchain activity."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Spreading the development of optimism information through the telegram channel (@airdropfinder) with 567k members. This can help spread widely to other OP communities and not only telegram, RPS1N spreads through social media accounts such as x (twitter)."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4f107dcb479c01ed93ea69571f21b2d023b12ae18d1b97de6618009305013a20",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728852072,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x4f6643893b617ec1e60b4730326b4d8ad8a2c9cba51743b59f4925b8ca8f15da",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728669610,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x281ac26aebe2550310abc45273b408bfab889c4d12050a86cf5e67618fc7f1ad",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNzKrw9BvF9HVAhJfE3wvATzmCgB5ArzDHBSYoLLnN6Px",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Grants Council is to oversee the evaluation and approval of projects for Governance Fund grants, ensuring they align with the season's intent andthe mission requests.  \n\nKey responsibilities include:\n\n1. Grant Evaluation: Reviewing and approving grant applications that further the goals of The Collective.\n2. Ensuring transparency by publishing reports, tracking milestone progress, and maintaining open communication with the community.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Grants Council keeps an updated communication thread here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/s5-grants-council-communication-thread/8034\n\nTo make RF6 voters life easier we compiled all our impact data here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/rf6-season-5-grants-council-report/9018"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x51db40daa615eebfb2421d705f3f494aa4044d5e217d82d63c6d6f09a306aedd",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728927756,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0d3820"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x48b9fc4fd1fa1de3cb0071ecd43c27a0c24d8fd7f86861a76073600e34d341f9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYEvdk1YF39VKF4br6UzVz1v14QM3smBpChnTcZTTAH2d",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The WalletConnect Network is used to allow the user of any wallet that is on the network to participate in governance. https://explorer.walletconnect.com/.\nIn September 2024, users from over 25 different wallets have used this tooling to participate in the Optimism voting for Season 5 including Metamask mobile, Rainbow, Candide, Trust Wallet, Ledger Live, BitGet, Binance Web3Wallet and OKX wallet - which ensures users can retain choice over where they keep their assets and how they participate in voting. \nBecause WalletConnect is built for both desktop and mobile, users can vote from their mobile devices - over 25% of the connections provided by the network in the last 30 days have come from mobile voters. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of the WalletConnect Network, with respect to voting, are the voters and the Optimism Development team. The voter is able to choose the wallet that they want to use when participating in governance. This ensures that users are not constrained to a small number of wallets.\nThe simplified integration process, tried and tested by over 6000 different applications also means the Optimism development team can easily offer this connectivity to their voters with minimal technical work ensuring compatibility with the widest range of wallets. \n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x525d5e28c05702e4ac0370ae46dd3c5acb49053f467dfcceb4bc05467dddd95c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728923602,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x604045aaf89932382c171101509227d2ec51a0fbb67e2ae5954ab4284cdd75a1",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmby7ruuCgS2ReuSXxccWuJjJAwojyqjjDa1P5597L5VCx",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Optimystics Tools has supported Optimism Governance by providing and maintaining essential infrastructure for decentralized decision-making over the past year:\n\n1. Initial Toolset: Our core tools have facilitated weekly Optimism Fractal events, enabling consistent governance experimentation and community building.\n\n2. Respect Infrastructure: We've maintained and upgraded the system for distributing Respect tokens, enabling a decentralized distribution amongst leading builders and governance enthusiasts.\n\n3. Council Support: Our tools have enabled the weekly formation and operation of the Optimism Fractal council, demonstrating scalable governance models and creating a well-organized governance body for the Collective.\n\nThis consistent infrastructure has allowed for the release of next-generation tools like ORDAO, Fractalgram, and the Respect Games app. It\u2019s enabled a community-driven effort with multiple development teams contributing to a growing toolkit of fractal governance tooling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Builders, leaders, delegates, and other key stakeholders in the Collective have used our tools at Optimism Fractal events to earn Respect and contribute to decentralized decision-making experiments.\n\n2. Our open-source infrastructure has served as a foundation for further governance innovations on Optimism, empowering researchers and developers interested in decentralized governance.\n\n3. Our tools have provided models and insights that could enhance various governance processes, including the Token House, Citizens' House, RetroFunding, and the Anti-Capture Commission.\n\n4. Other groups like the ZAO Fractal have adopted processes to engage, govern, and grow their communities on the Superchain. \n\nOur tools have created a vibrant testbed for governance innovations, benefiting anyone interested in exploring and contributing to decentralized decision-making processes on Optimism, and providing valuable data and experiences that can inform the evolution of the Collective's governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x52de3ee93782b4927db17ba78bdc34dd2e4ad0e7da711a87bbd9193a2947f573",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728793522,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x36872c5262768e36e1b4df4289272c543720e6f4d6942c4cc298d0f966db2620",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSTxETgqsUkjNr5E7vu8QpxBafWrXDnhK7pe9cvKKHZMk",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until Sep 18th, there were over 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our modular tool allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nDeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects & any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project; e.g. you can quickly see that 2 RF4 Badgeholders, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passport Holders, 1 RF5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged during the review period. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The OP community (esp. delegates) can support projects that are adding value to the Superchain Community. While unable to participate in Retro Funding directly, through DeVouch, they can lend their credibility to them, and leave a comment about the project using our extremely easy to use UX. [Try it out!](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf6)\n\nVoters & reviewers in Retro Funding programs are able to incorporate the wisdom of the crowds. \n\nWe helped the Foundation prevent imposters. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5. If impersonation occurred, the project would have seen the tweet, flagged it on DeVouch and reported it.\n\nProjects have a simple way to prove their legitimacy in an industry ripe with scams. Giveth also ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise & growthepie alongside projects that are making irl impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x532335fe1cb82d751adc9ae8489cfc82d8623b50f1a3770e02f70f1996483427",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728888452,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x061924"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5e0e74a1b6847a6e5d91cec5386f08c849c1caf5c4205f931ad448b293c51d47",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVbymEYJKotgdxUzERjYyMUbVEMQye1fTD5QGoiejtcqi",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Ethereans Protocol allows a more decentralized and transparent framework for governance. Our Organizations product enables anyone to create fully decentralized DAOs on Optimism, reducing dependence on centralized entities like the Foundation to set funding parameters. These DAOs can manage treasuries, vote on proposals, and automate token actions through on-chain factory contracts, allowing governance to be handled directly by the community. With our modular tooling, communities can actively participate in shaping funding rounds through decentralized voting mechanisms, ensuring that decision-making is fair, transparent, and inclusive. By utilizing Ethereans' Organizations, Optimism\u2019s RPGF process can evolve to reflect its ethos of decentralization, granting more influence and ownership to participants. This will not only improve the fairness of funding decisions but also foster innovation in governance models, positioning Optimism as a leader in decentralized governance"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of Ethereans Protocol\u2019s infrastructure and tooling are governance participants within the Optimism ecosystem who seek a decentralized and transparent governance process:\n\nDAO Founders & Builders \u2013 Our Organizations product enables them to create and manage decentralized governance structures without technical expertise, eliminating the need for central control.\n\nToken Holders & Voters \u2013 Token holders can participate in decision-making through on-chain voting, ensuring their voices are heard and proposals are recorded immutably.\n\nRPGF Participants \u2013 Contributors and grantees benefit from a fair funding process governed by decentralized DAOs, prioritizing community input and engagement.\n\nOptimism Delegates \u2013 Delegates can leverage our tooling to automate and streamline governance processes\n\nWith this infrastructure, Ethereans Protocol promotes decentralized decision-making, accountability, and community participation across all layers of governance in Optimism."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5394d57ca9c6ee3bb4e13c5fdb8ed60eb62ecaef711212ae991b03c29be88df5",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728930952,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x07fef0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8b63a8d02ea3796f6a0de7d31d589c8972dc5abfd267a4a8cff69dfd3b1fd04a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSPRkoMgmbiiYEtdiwLmXgJ7usG4xQKrQiN3Zaa5Tmb1h",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Successfully completed a token house governance growth mission titled [Integrate Optimism Governance into University Module], and hosted governance workshops, community calls, and events throughout the year for Seasons 5 (S5) and 6 (S6)."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "We successfully completed a significant governance mission, positioning Optimism as the first university-level blockchain course in Costa Rica.\n\nOur efforts have enhanced the governance process by fostering community engagement and education within the Optimism ecosystem in the country, through the \"Integrate Optimism Governance into University Module\" mission. Not to mention that this module can now be replicated anywhere anytime. Our work has positioned Optimism and is attracting attention from other universities and organizations\n\nWe organized gov workshops, community calls, and events throughout the year [OP Days] This initiative has increased participation in governance, missions, and the forum.\n\nBy facilitating hands-on experiences, we empowered students to collaborate on innovative solutions, enriching the governance framework with diverse perspectives.\n\nCreating the next generation of Optimism leaders, ensuring a robust future for the ecosystem!\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x541874c330d4e0e1c9001982a1dbd512719519f97e53b062d474b02ca5b99942",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728710802,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x903e374e6261e72a75fd51b98dc1fb63042c66be897d2d621466fbf0845cee7d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTr1uEZDVLgd9a49or745Vbx612HNnAWcS4YKpvTyte5R",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery Project discovery"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x54f36de9bcf7d3fda4d12f9901f87276e307d7a8eca9f37ccf2b799384d0b82a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728667591,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x566894d2491013706374ae05f9f0daa5f24796de69418b0b1afa10b877578549",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNuWiTBzH2SJM9gbKMEVNQfsDw6bFnoUrbmBNafi5QT1v",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the council. In Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where the Foundation multisig was removed from the Upgrade multisig, and the Security Council became the sole signer. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x56049fb1e50528c74ed1aa666b4b5dee458c1772243934ad449ffd8779de9893",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728723936,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd37a520af32996a831ae032a60d0d039892beee61b3b177777444a92b0e61c39",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSvAjst51EJTXhywiGahtcRSCnYBs8F8zK7SYg7SyyWCy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until September 18th, there were about 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our tool, similar to Metrics Garden, allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n\nAlso, Giveth ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise & growthepie (supporting OP Governance) alongside projects that are making real world impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF. Projects\u2019 order of appearance in the rounds could be changed by using our GIVpower governance system on OP mainnet. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "DeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects and any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project. For example, you can quickly see that 2 RF 4 Badgeholder, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passports, 1 RF 5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nFlagging projects is especially helpful. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5 to ensure there were no imposters posing to be them in the round. If there would have been an imposter, the project would have seen the tweet, been able to flag it on DeVouch and report it to the Foundation.\n\nOn the fundraising side, Giveth enabled EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise, growthepie, and several other OP Governance-related projects to collect much needed funds to continue their work in the Collective.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x570dade598f9ab44f47ec74a5cd1e49a2e1d73b29f649f3fcd5374b8557ed974",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728862426,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x057788"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x916f6255ae44902f7686cc2fa6f762e22a1d69b815f00769201becfa6b8764ae",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmeBquKnG2CiGjMdGp5Cwgggx2b8ZSG3nPwigQCVYFetTR",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The **Delegate Match Farcaster Frame** is designed to improve accessibility in Optimism governance by helping OP token holders find active delegates who align with their values and vision. The tool streamlines the process, allowing users to take an 11-question survey and match with active, values-aligned delegates, increasing the overall votable OP supply. [Landing page](https://delegatematch.xyz/)\n\nLeveraging Farcaster\u2019s 650K registered users and 60-100K daily active users, Delegate Match boosts exposure to the OP delegation process. Our Farcaster Frame provides a seamless experience, enabling users to make an informed decision and delegate their tokens in just five minutes. By integrating the Ethereum Attestation Service, Delegate Match supports delegate reputation-building. It provides OP holders and delegates a low-cost, high-impact, innovative delegation tool. [Onchain Metrics](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/rJaRn0UJJe)\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of **Delegate Match** are OP token holders who aren\u2019t too engaged in governance and OP delegates with active delegations. Holders can easily find and delegate or redelegate to active delegates who align with their values. OP delegates, particularly underrepresented ones, benefit from increased visibility to grow their delegations based on values alignment rather than popularity. By encouraging broader participation, Delegate Match helps decentralize governance and promotes greater equity among delegates, enabling them to play a more meaningful role in Optimism's decision-making.\n\n\nThis product, built for Optimism governance, is currently in its **MVP** stage. Our next steps include improving the user experience, enhancing impact tracking, and launching a marketing campaign to increase the overall votable OP supply. Funding will ensure we gain traction and continue the development [Vision and Features Roadmap](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/HJaVrJw1ye)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x57f27415af99fedfa7a6a959b3b92b6e4c7bf3fa96c8ca23794348b5638cc362",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728888200,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x14afcfca7a32226f8e993fefc5ee3f4ac3ae1c62a03486ed213faadc8b30fb45",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmc43bWsXGPXcKcoeUL77TrAC7otF6QqMT3dtPwHujxdU9",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the Security Council. \n\nIn Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, as part of this upgrade the owner of the L2ProxyAdmin contract was reassigned from the Foundation to the Security Council.\n\nAs part of Phase 1, the signing threshold for the Security Council was increased from 4 to 10. Throughout Season 6, the Security Council continued it's streak of meeting quorum on all signing ceremonies. \n\nAs part of Phase 1, the role of Guardian was reassigned from the Foundation to a new Guardian Safe with the Security Council Safe as its sole owner, moving Optimism closer to satisfying the 1 week exit window required for Stage 1. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n\nThe Security Council continues to be responsive and efficient in all tasks that require attention. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5875d6649b0fb241c31fa6610c55663053dfa8533b2374939e1be22aa9d94805",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728680972,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x07a02270e0367cc269699073b6228615a7336c7b043c390fd0b4574befecea1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTCsskKvMGNcEWN3zMuBxxxjdS2k1ARmE77sihaECbQyv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n \nRelevant Documentation:\nAnticapture Commission Mandate: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n\nAnticapture Commission Communication Thread:  https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/9\n\n\nSeason 6 Internal Operating Procedures: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-s6-internal-operating-procedures-iop/8637\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During S6 Governance (VC #25 to #28), ACC voted on the Dolomite Network upgrade proposal. ACC held discussions and shared feedback to the Foundation on the Dolomite Upgrade Proposal on certain technical aspects of the upgrade that the ACC members felt could have been better implemented. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/20 ) \n\nDuring S6 voting cycles, few Delegates encountered voting issues on the Agora UI, resulting in wrongly cast votes during a mission request vote. The ACC held internal discussions on the issue and took it up with the Agora team and worked towards resolving the issue. \n\n\nThe ACC also held a call to discuss the Accelerated Decentralization Proposal for Optimism with GFX Labs and the Foundation. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/accelerated-decentralization-proposal-for-optimism/8875/32 ) \n \nSince the Start of Season 6 of Governance, votable supply has increased by 7.31%, from 89.4m OP to 96m OP.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x58aaeec26c3bb0a2e4d3bfd21086ab3683e63425966ab48b467f5e27f615bad0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857127,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2888"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x24a2f1b3f0b48aae4e3d2a04b649edbf254028ddf33da7fa3f8981e5bf47800a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbRQr7yrhgXGLi4Cn5j2ueRvLgBAKdD8BitFoWZautFxv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Gitcoin developed the voting interfaces for Retrofunding 4 & Retrofunding 5, which were used by badgeholders to allocate funds during those rounds.\n\nFor RF4, we worked closely with Open Source Observer and Optimism to implement new metrics-based discovery, selection, and weighting. Our solution allowed users to filter and evaluate projects based on various impact metrics. \n\nFor both RF 4 & RF5, we created a user-friendly interface for governance participants to allocate their votes. \n\nThese tools are primarily used within Optimism Governance to support the Retroactive Public Goods Funding process, which is a crucial part of Optimism's governance model. They aim to make the process of discovering, evaluating, and voting for projects more efficient, transparent, and user-friendly for governance participants."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The direct benefits are the Optimism badgeholders and recipients of Retrofunding. During RF4, 108 out of 133 badgeholders participated. $10M OP tokens were allocated to 207 projects. \n\nThough RF5 is still ongoing at the time of this application, participation is high. Badgeholders are expected to allocate between 2-8m OP tokens to up to 89 projects.\n\nThe team has also integrated these features into EasyRetroPGF.xyz, which makes them available to a wider range of users involved in Optimism's governance processes. The SUNNYS Awards have also been built on this same technology!"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x59718022161d39195c341d8c9a36f744c9070f73e0ba8d52553d594380aa8460",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728925061,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0338f1"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x203b65166c5175077e72c68696bd77e6628807c18f4f369268bf339565591c3f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXoCNyR32F4j6Vov9nrqa8VXyqhjtJRYQbuviQpFKA4e1",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "DeepDAO provides the most comprehensive analysis of different components of Optimism governance:\n\n- Treasury, including trends over time, tokens, assets and composition (OP vs stables, majors, and others).\n\n-  Token, including governance performance influence on the OP token price.\n\n- Voter Trends: multiple metrics of quality and intensity of governance participation in the Collective. Successful proposals, avg. votes per proposal, and others, in multiple timeframes. We also categorize voters based on their governance score to understand participant quality.\n\n- Delegation, including intensity, and quantity of involvement across voting power, delegators, total votes, and voting periods.\n\n- Delegate Coalitions, tracking governance activity of power groups of up to 6 addresses. Together with Delegation, this provides deep analysis of decentralization within Optimism governance.\n\n- Voters Ecosystem, measuring the Collective voters involvement in other DAOs, including competing DAOs. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "New Participants: DeepDAO helps new entrants to the DAO ecosystem discover the OP Collective, ensuring they do not face information asymmetry compared to experienced participants.\n\nDelegates use DeepDAO to stay updated on OP Collective activities. Our analytics dashboard offers extensive information on the DAO's well-being.\n\nBuilders: DeepDAO makes it easy for builders to identify and approach the right delegates for feedback. (using the Delegation, and Coalitions dashboards).\n\nTooling Providers: DeepDAO aggregates information across various tooling providers and includes a tools page listing all DAO tools available to the Optimism Collective.\n\nOP Collective: Our data on coalitions, governance segmentation and voter trends provides multiple indicators of the DAO\u2019s decentralization, governance resilience and security. The Collective benefits immensely from a free resource like DeepDAO.\n\nInvestors, journalists, researchers: 1000s of media articles and academic papers quote DeepDAO data.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5b43678e6a928195c347b5e5939421bcdec3ef490c95741a161941eec7b1068c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928597,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x1c8c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8b4ffe238987a6fb5c645e342bccb72271f34c2b897f275ba7b6f901b60843e0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYLzpriwN3ufqrjPLc6tZe4tKtwDrFDYLscmR6yR4oxMX",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "- Streamlined the Retro Funding application process using human expertise and digital tools.\n- Matched eligible projects with the appropriate Retro Funding rounds.\n- Guided projects in creating strong, Optimism-aligned applications, reducing the burden on reviewers.\n- Enhanced transparency and accessibility in the funding process, enabling more informed capital allocation.\n- Helped prioritize high-impact projects aligned with Optimism\u2019s governance goals."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "- **Practically Supported Retro Funding Applicants**: Improved application quality and alignment with Optimism\u2019s goals. Projects received either free consultations over telegram group, or commission only (zero payment upfront), increasing their chances of success.\n- **Streamlined the process for the Optimism Grants Council**: Received well-crafted proposals, reducing time spent on lower-quality submissions.\n- **Provided Value for Governance Delegates & Badgeholders**: Presented clear, impactful applications for more informed decisions supporting long-term goals.\n- **Spread Governance Participation to the Broader Optimism Ecosystem**: Benefited from efficient capital allocation, supporting "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5c7ff1a009703968b264e8f8d5124910059040bc5b4612d4255347f148ea47f0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856192,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x07a02270e0367cc269699073b6228615a7336c7b043c390fd0b4574befecea1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTCsskKvMGNcEWN3zMuBxxxjdS2k1ARmE77sihaECbQyv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n \nRelevant Documentation:\nAnticapture Commission Mandate: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n\nAnticapture Commission Communication Thread:  https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/9\n\n\nSeason 6 Internal Operating Procedures: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-s6-internal-operating-procedures-iop/8637\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During S6 Governance (VC #25 to #28), ACC voted on the Dolomite Network upgrade proposal. ACC held discussions and shared feedback to the Foundation on the Dolomite Upgrade Proposal on certain technical aspects of the upgrade that the ACC members felt could have been better implemented. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/20 ) \n\nDuring S6 voting cycles, few Delegates encountered voting issues on the Agora UI, resulting in wrongly cast votes during a mission request vote. The ACC held internal discussions on the issue and took it up with the Agora team and worked towards resolving the issue. \n\n\nThe ACC also held a call to discuss the Accelerated Decentralization Proposal for Optimism with GFX Labs and the Foundation. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/accelerated-decentralization-proposal-for-optimism/8875/32 ) \n \nSince the Start of Season 6 of Governance, votable supply has increased by 7.31%, from 89.4m OP to 96m OP.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5e48b0805bb33aa1db47a1aec5a9ed9054500392a9142afeea8b72aac176b85c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728673373,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5d694af04d6b25e855751e88d4331674852fa6428ff8975ee2e0822f4b0f51f7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNzKrw9BvF9HVAhJfE3wvATzmCgB5ArzDHBSYoLLnN6Px",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Grants Council is to oversee the evaluation and approval of projects for Governance Fund grants, ensuring they align with the season's intent andthe mission requests.  \n\nKey responsibilities include:\n\n1. Grant Evaluation: Reviewing and approving grant applications that further the goals of The Collective.\n2. Ensuring transparency by publishing reports, tracking milestone progress, and maintaining open communication with the community.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Grants Council keeps an updated communication thread here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/s5-grants-council-communication-thread/8034\n\nTo make RF6 voters life easier we compiled all our impact data here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/rf6-season-5-grants-council-report/9018"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5e9a17d55b1a8be9a17681a82616845858004c6757f01a845b8ecd7e7a71ff09",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728930728,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03c940"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5891cf9f8826ad546a1327d3d697bc7a0b9600c20088fcb29ff64a51de27a5b9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZk7QPjbkVKxchcJmqmfV3J6C82EYrPjwmgBxyJo48SdV",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The **Delegate Match Farcaster Frame** is designed to improve accessibility in Optimism governance by helping OP token holders find active delegates who align with their values and vision. The tool streamlines the process, allowing users to take an 11-question survey and match with active, values-aligned delegates, increasing the overall votable OP supply. [Landing page](https://delegatematch.xyz/)\n\nLeveraging Farcaster\u2019s 650K registered users and 60-100K daily active users, Delegate Match boosts exposure to the OP delegation process. Our Farcaster Frame provides a seamless experience, enabling users to make an informed decision and delegate their tokens in just five minutes. By integrating the Ethereum Attestation Service, Delegate Match supports delegate reputation-building. It provides OP holders and delegates a low-cost, high-impact, innovative delegation tool. [Onchain Metrics](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/rJaRn0UJJe)\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of **Delegate Match** are OP token holders who aren\u2019t too engaged in governance and OP delegates with active delegations. Holders can easily find and delegate or redelegate to active delegates who align with their values. OP delegates, particularly underrepresented ones, benefit from increased visibility to grow their delegations based on values alignment rather than popularity. By encouraging broader participation, Delegate Match helps decentralize governance and promotes greater equity among delegates, enabling them to play a more meaningful role in Optimism's decision-making.\n\nWe have a solid foundation and are passionately engaged in exploring innovative solutions in this uncharted territory. Our focus includes critical inquiries into user experience, impact tracking, and outreach strategies so that delegation is informed, accessible, accountable, and efficient for all stakeholders. Delve into our [Vision and Insights](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/HJaVrJw1ye)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5f6ad1289f540a34df701800e3c093b764f83fb2bae04bccc89a147f11759e2f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856875,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x5fea88070a451114868f840b035b61a4967c8d1a77475b6ddf9eefde37d8365b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837870,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8a8ad640cd39d6004a2f178709055b364ea24a28fe08d71989182ce2b32a5c20",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTaLq3TDK6zS3KjAr1RYyFfHau8xm2qkAZWWh3qrS6Ark",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Impact Garden is used to gather standardized information on a project's impact to the Optimism Collective beyond that being self reported by applicants. The information collected is linked to the reputation of the person providing the testimonial enabling advanced weighting by the consumer of the data. Higher reputation in the Collective, can mean your testimonial is more relevant in decisions.\n\nFor Round 5, Impact Garden gathered over 100 testimonials for 35+ projects in the round. These testimonials were used by Badgeholders during the review process particularly to determine if projects were in the right sub-category and for additional information. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The audience benefiting the most from the data created by Impact Garden are Badgeholders. \n\nThrough the generation of new data in a standardized format we're bridging the gap and giving numbers, projects and contributions a context about their impact to others within the Collective. This has looked like additional data for Badgeholders in the review process and voting.  "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6017e31f2a04030f37a34207299d2f154b21d774a930cf2b084c7b58d03824f9",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728771057,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2e4b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd7ca34c2adcbad30140ae875be09dac2ebeb32715748f17f4ed37bccd213ac8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmV9ChcAGGFLkSbiyNxTiMyvakRZh9HyBsN4B94xFkbZRf",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "EthStaker's core mission is to support solo staking and the health of the beacon chain. We persue this mission through a variety of efforts including (1) providing world-class, free technical support and staking education, (2) organizing and hosting live and virtual events, (3) stewardship of grants for beneficial ecosystem contributors, (4) providing industry research and communication for the most critical topics, and now (5) developing open source staking software. Today we kick off an audit process of the new version of the Staking Deposit CLI.. You can learn more about the newly developed ethstaker-deposit-cli here."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Solo stakers who have received support on their staking set ups, used our tools, and the Ethereum community at large. EthStaker spearheaded the push to increase client diversity to create a more stable Ethereum network for everybody."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6023480205c8c7eb56ed2089526be236bd2683fb029e10ee23ee0b1af91cb8a4",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929488,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0acc5b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xe6dd99dd1f03c7ed0c82a1b89a5ea9a140dc4039a3c3bb8895d240972793bb33",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXKpBiGRnKoigEpTGjNEhtudLMHDr5of2pt6b1JsNbWs3",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "**Discord Praise Bot:**\n\nAllows users to praise one another within their community for contributions, which are then stored and minted as on-chain attestations on Optimism Network.\n\nFacilitates community recognition and builds trust through transparent records of contributions.\nSince Oct 1st, 2023 to Sep 18th, 2024, We had a total of 642 Praises. Each one a statement of gratitude, as well as reputational data. \n\n200+ Active users \n\n\n\n**Praise on Farcaster:**\n\nIntegrates Praise\u2019s attestation capabilities onto Farcaster. Users can tag @givepraise to publicly appreciate other Farcaster accounts.\n\nFarcaster Frame Praise Attestations lowers the barrier to entry for creating user reputation, contributing to proof of uniqueness and reputation scores across the Web3 ecosystem.\n\n236 attestations minted since the launch on Praise Farcaster bot (within 2 weeks)\n\n76 Unique users minted attestations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "**Active Participants in Optimism Governance:**\n\nDelegates & Badgeholders:\n\nCan easily show gratitude\nCan help community members build onchain reputation. \n\nEngaged Community Members:\nGain visibility and reputation through peer recognition.\nBoosts motivation to participate in governance activities.\nBetter vibes\n\n**Individuals Verifying Reputations and Identities:**\n\nOnchain Attestations:\nProvide a transparent and verifiable record of contributions.\nAid in assessing community members' reputations.\n\nTrust Building:\nHelp users make informed decisions within governance.\nLower the barrier to entry for new contributors seeking to build trust.\n\nOverall Impact:\nSimplified the process of acknowledging contributions and verifying reputations.\nStrengthened engagement and collaboration within the Optimism governance ecosystem."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x605b21336fc8f23e4c963795a95da22abf5c7ac8e49fcc8f8dfe344b7f1f31f2",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728729056,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x60ce22961490e62e3b4f068c9a7592ced68ab89555bd4250fa46117edf6b8c8a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857757,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x045717"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xe29a5041a2df6258f481d148041217a8a127465462915e3aa4e18c2a8cadd343",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPoaqe5AHJgo6YZ9XTn2bbdLoeUzZtVmSSN3WC81Pkwt5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process.",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Yes verry support to Governance and we will verry like for all Optimism Governance project and Retro Funding Round, so now we add our project on Optimism with OP Funding round and Rewarded $OP for all qualify users. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Yes verry support to Governance and we will verry like for all Optimism Governance project and Retro Funding Round, so now we add our project on Optimism with OP Funding round and Rewarded $OP for all qualify users. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x60efd5b2ab055c8ce8425e10290f6e10e077ef2b822f630ce6a89e3b03aaa27d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857837,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x07a02270e0367cc269699073b6228615a7336c7b043c390fd0b4574befecea1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTCsskKvMGNcEWN3zMuBxxxjdS2k1ARmE77sihaECbQyv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n \nRelevant Documentation:\nAnticapture Commission Mandate: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n\nAnticapture Commission Communication Thread:  https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/9\n\n\nSeason 6 Internal Operating Procedures: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-s6-internal-operating-procedures-iop/8637\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During S6 Governance (VC #25 to #28), ACC voted on the Dolomite Network upgrade proposal. ACC held discussions and shared feedback to the Foundation on the Dolomite Upgrade Proposal on certain technical aspects of the upgrade that the ACC members felt could have been better implemented. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/20 ) \n\nDuring S6 voting cycles, few Delegates encountered voting issues on the Agora UI, resulting in wrongly cast votes during a mission request vote. The ACC held internal discussions on the issue and took it up with the Agora team and worked towards resolving the issue. \n\n\nThe ACC also held a call to discuss the Accelerated Decentralization Proposal for Optimism with GFX Labs and the Foundation. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/accelerated-decentralization-proposal-for-optimism/8875/32 ) \n \nSince the Start of Season 6 of Governance, votable supply has increased by 7.31%, from 89.4m OP to 96m OP.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x615761a99e3d9989e0fe658eae2b73c1a850e6303964f09507006d0a75603685",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728831995,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x623c46cd909893921be8739baa4eb52db59048b5ecbc6b696e81dd84df02c038",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728783482,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x35776320b6eef82c074b3a7b74ef7b22067dfe28a04af8c53e8c077ddff922be",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSvAjst51EJTXhywiGahtcRSCnYBs8F8zK7SYg7SyyWCy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until September 18th, there were about 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our tool, similar to Metrics Garden, allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n\nAlso, Giveth ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise & growthepie (supporting OP Governance) alongside projects that are making real world impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF. Projects\u2019 order of appearance in the rounds could be changed by using our GIVpower governance system on OP mainnet. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "DeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects and any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project. For example, you can quickly see that 2 RF 4 Badgeholder, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passports, 1 RF 5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nFlagging projects is especially helpful. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5 to ensure there were no imposters posing to be them in the round. If there would have been an imposter, the project would have seen the tweet, been able to flag it on DeVouch and report it to the Foundation.\n\nOn the fundraising side, Giveth enabled EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise, growthepie, and several other OP Governance-related projects to collect much needed funds to continue their work in the Collective.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x628d4123c5e317fc1579e8a77c29378e6fec510d9b567b0a3d60a990f3efcf59",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728826449,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x08aeb4bc57b33ae52cea98678c32d73456572b548760f7470da1631f85083645",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaSpvLBDr1hzD5cDfGWBztHoSJHfRJC2WZUHDMW2HpHDU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analysis measures the participation and behavior of Badgeholders in the Superchain ecosystem, specifically focusing on their transaction activities across networks like OP Mainnet, Base, Zora, and Mode. It also examines their engagement in decentralized applications (DEXs), token transfers, and social platforms like Farcaster. \n\nA key insight is the relatively low activity level of Badgeholders compared to Non-Badgeholders, particularly in areas like DEX trading and smart contract deployment. Additionally, the analysis tracks how Badgeholders' preferences for Ethereum transactions and limited cross-chain activity impact their overall engagement with Optimism's governance processes. \n\nThis helps identify where governance structures may need to be adjusted to include better and activate Badgeholders, ensuring their participation grows alongside the broader ecosystem.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Collective has benefitted most from this analysis, gaining valuable insights into Badgeholder behavior that inform strategies to increase engagement. For example, understanding that Badgeholders are more active on Ethereum but less engaged with smart contract deployment helps the Collective target these users with specific governance initiatives. \n\nFurthermore, the findings around Farcaster connections show the importance of social engagement within this group, which can shape future governance outreach and participation efforts. The insights have also helped governance teams refine their strategies for promoting cross-chain activity and diversifying user engagement. This research will also guide the future selection of new Badgeholders for the Citizen House by identifying gaps and ensuring the House becomes more inclusive and representative of the entire user profile within the Collective, promoting a well-rounded governance structure.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x62bcd3ebcac2cbc98e6c18ab4b93f6e178e7700be89c9038be2e1e201aab60e0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728739206,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x06be135bacb0befa9a0d9af56fa01288537a786efc3cc659347b92204d8bae2e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmR1PZ2BkGTTXQuxr1oKmqkxk7mVmPSAcDNnWYXSxt8ZGZ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Impact Evaluation Framework has been used to inform Badgeholders voting in Retro3 by supporting the creation of Lists, providing context into the Collective for new voters inspired metrics generated for Round 4 and onwards for projects contributing to the Collective. \n\nThe Metrics Garden Database, which has served to inform the creation of new Metrics Gardens has also informed the evaluation criteria for RetroRounds from Ecosystems such as libp2p and Filecoin which have enabled to fund downstream Optimism dependencies: https://www.notion.so/a60768062a2e4e5f8b4ea787e73d38b5?v=468228b4f651454aaf4296934a8a18bd\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The participants who have benefitted the most from the Impact Evaluation Framework have been Badgeholders who leveraged this tool to inform their voting in Round3.\n\nSome testimonials can be found here:\n- On Lists: https://gov.optimism.io/t/round-3-voting-rationale/7030/5\n- On Impact: https://gov.optimism.io/t/joans-rpgf3-reflections/7221\n- On Voting: https://x.com/brichis_/status/1732146910708806069?s=20\n- On Evaluation Criteria: https://github.com/0xyNaMu/RetroPGF3List_Methodology/tree/ContributorTracks"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x657e3d9a3f937d1f7b4049bf71dbeb623656386441be8d013fc847b1f6d2db6c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728682575,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf5519a31d49c637d8f00ff3c17fe9a685b159d2f46e6799a53860ff42b2a79b0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQwMxbJLBbPU6r5x1yDHkUaxUPuv9LupckcKkPM32Fu4K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\n[Reflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation](https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x658ea3c1167735cca669cf02af5208326767afbbcb82d30d43641fecf7f59bc2",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728744207,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0a0137"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x32bb4268b277d90be3b0e07ea72439026b72badae3d2a5306d96e339133917e7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmcqe5gRn5SBNWhQgrF9QJ12LPowzcgmP3emNQQ6419yoD",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Governance Vulnerability Discovery (Jan, 2024 - Oct 18, 2024)\nDuring the specified time period, we uncovered and reported a significant governance vulnerability related to voting power discrepancies within the Optimism governance framework. \n\nVulnerability Identification\nIn August 2024, we discovered a critical issue where certain addresses had disproportionately high voting power, exceeding their actual token holdings. This created the risk of skewing governance decisions and breaking the \"one token, one vote\" principle, which is foundational to decentralized governance. There was >200,000 OP which were double voted.\nThe vulnerability allows certain addresses to retain voting power for >200,000 OP even after selling the tokens, effectively doubling their influence. They could split their holdings to create multiple top 100 delegate spots for 0 token cost, further increasing their power, posing a zero-cost attack risk. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The vulnerability was reported promptly to the Optimism governance team, ensuring that the issue was addressed before it could materially impact governance outcomes in future voting cycles.\n\nCollaborative Resolution\nAfter reporting the issue, we worked with the Optimism team to clarify the problem and assist in formulating a fix. \nThe governance team implemented a fix that removed the inflated delegations and prevented such issues from happening in future voting cycles.\nThe prompt resolution and transparency around the issue maintained the integrity of the OP governance system\nToken House and RetroPGF Consideration\nThis discovery did not fall under a formal bounty program or RetroPGF framework, the Optimism governance team acknowledged the importance of the contribution and allowed for RPGF. This recognition emphasized the value of community-driven governance security efforts, even in the absence of formalized bounty structures."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x65d4ad584cb20ddc828b1a66de0e9dc692ef39303df4cd40fb615835fc991e41",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728889804,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x051b41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xdbd3808ca533593e4c0e1c91bb80670b523cd85440520f6e4a9ec6bc8179af0a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXi2fyGB1iLQ9iUtzrqXCmRwtkj22NjsjbA3WSUDApDw6",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The impact on this community is to increase the number of Optimse onchain through open media information about optimization developments such as grants, airdrops, retroactives. for example what happened yesterday (airdrop 5 OP), Partner (Layer 3), to Superchain activity."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Spreading the development of optimism information through the telegram channel (@airdropfinder) with 567k members. This can help spread widely to other OP communities and not only telegram, RPS1N spreads through social media accounts such as x (twitter)."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x65fad5486329a6f1e265621e766707da911becd6468ad9608621652d239865d5",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728762634,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03a9fb"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x37d3f04c6e4e793c886c169bb931cbb4e58c62af70445b3b0ae97cc4c25e6357",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmdo6JixGA8uebpWEA7cjPyjvggA31dj3YRTm7FFHiifGv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We have helped Optimism governance participants by aggregating and condensing the forum activity (and the limited snapshot data) so they can easily stay on top of what is occurring in the DAO. Users quickly get a newsfeed in both chronological and 'trending' orders, with each topic condensed in a structured format for easy readability.\nWe have also had our telegram governance assistant bot available during this time, helping get direct answers for governance participants quickly."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Governance participants who are new to Optimism and/or participating in multiple DAOs have benefited most from our tooling. This is because they do not have the historic context or understanding as someone who is deep in Optimism governance, so they use our tool to get a better understanding and to dive deeper into certain areas. E.g. we surface related content for each topic, so users can explore the history or related topics for a certain subject matter. Our governance assistant bot also quickly surfaces relevant information based on what users ask, e.g. 'what is rgpf and when is the next round?'."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x676542dbf991e332cee8d77468f136b49a9c99fa620fc2e29a5a19a72c3ef29a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728854715,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x67e7ad2bf7c76e9726f236e43d4d45ca9484c31a1efb5480375646230328f728",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728910098,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x5314"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5cc920bafc2587ed515fd206f9c9928427ef40a7403009729892e1d03871d820",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQKm6uEgDrXLT5XKj2Fomhf7W6BmcbyihunCUcFdHquKN",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We built this site in response to forum feedback, where many community members shared feeling overwhelmed by the constantly evolving nature of Optimism governance, in particular the many novel experiments around grant programs.\n\nWhile rapid iteration is good for innovation (yay!), it also made it more challenging to stay up-to-date without first having to \"navigate a maze of forum posts\". We made it easy to access all deadlines and changes to programs in one place.\n\nThis has been well received: In the period between Oct 2023 and Sept 2024, there have been 2.9K outbound link clicks from our site to the Charmverse Grants Council page, 1.1K clicks to the Foundation Mission Requests pages on GitHub, and 605 clicks to forum posts on Retro Funding Rounds."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our site has primarily been useful as tool for supporting those involved in grants processes, including the Grants Council, Retro Funding Rounds and (Foundation) Mission Requests.\n\nThe subscribers of our newsletter where we used to share weekly updates, before then focusing primarily on the website, include employees from OP Labs, OpenZeppelin and Wakeup Labs. \n\nThe teams behind grantee projects such as OpenZeppelin are those who likely benefited most from our overview of the current status of grant programs, upcoming deadlines, our grants calendar, and the changelog. They otherwise would have had a much higher workload by having to keep track of this information across a number of different channels (GitHub, Grants Council Charmverse page, Forum, ...)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x67f70235d198d82177cb3c96943193636fabda61798f3eb238c42515d217d6c7",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728676286,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xbb84f3a7463ca746831ce765bd83b33c13e55712c0b8d1c3e74096a120ca0527",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQwMxbJLBbPU6r5x1yDHkUaxUPuv9LupckcKkPM32Fu4K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\n[Reflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation](https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x68163b7a4cffdef804232bbccbf32471240cd0ca19bd60918fbf4608a21450f6",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837687,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0ce07d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2d19c8c56a93527fdcdc23b94931d8691008e0b02910e97b028f95c5ae7962db",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZLhQ5Q9fxc9F9Kvgi4JRSkMYMTwv87tYdKkaowRjKfJM",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Impact Calculator significantly enhanced the decision-making process for Retro Funding 4 by measuring the tangible real-world impact of each project, rather than relying on popularity metrics. This approach aligned with Optimism\u2019s mission to reward high-impact contributions to the ecosystem.\n\nBy converting raw data into quantifiable metrics, the tool enabled badgeholders to evaluate projects more objectively and efficiently, reducing assessment time while ensuring impactful projects receive recognition and funding.\n\nOur infrastructure and tooling support Optimism Governance by providing a transparent, data-driven evaluation framework, automating impact assessments, and ensuring fair resource allocation without subjective criteria\u2014advancing the governance goal of fostering sustainable growth."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Small builders have benefited the most from our infrastructure and tooling. They no longer need to compete with large, well-known projects for visibility. By creating impactful contributions, even on a smaller scale, they can access Retro Funding, which rewards based on real-world impact rather than recognition. This levels the playing field for those with fewer resources, enabling them to receive the funding they deserve.\n\nBadgeholders also benefit significantly from our tooling. We\u2019ve automated much of the data they previously had to review manually, streamlining their evaluation process. This allows them to assess projects more quickly and accurately, ensuring a fair and transparent voting process while maintaining the integrity of Optimism Governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x69b17781325f29bcedf54ed26df4a346171c6edefd111ea071175fb86c619a45",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857857,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x48a89eb05496e18fa2119e24cbbf6ddaa050d932121131d382e4132f1e277288",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmS4qcySi43RftMsK1cR84fufi3LACtj74mT5umEMQHvfC",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The core mandate of govNERDs is to streamline the proposal process by guiding proposals through key stages\u2014feedback, approval, and voting. We also manage onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House, ensuring participants have the support they need to engage effectively. Additionally, we provide forum moderation, ensuring that governance discussions remain high-quality and focused.\n\nFoundation Mission Request: Season 5 govNERDs\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs went beyond their mandate by taking over crucial governance tasks previously handled by the Foundation. We successfully managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and maintained clear communication about voting and veto cycles. Our additional contributions included:\n- Creation of a tracker for Missions v2.\n- Support in maintaining the Public Governance Fund Tracker.\n- Gathering feedback throughout the Season and flagging key issues to the Foundation.\n\nFor more, check the Impact Evaluation made by the Foundation: \nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734\n\nReward Split: \nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1zzsd7p2ECdHBnQQhWMt8ivArqfUIXNv713FjrCQ51mE\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6a8c461f29e9d113033952e4da69adf997b4d303de88bfd7c2023f023b38e52f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929038,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0acc5b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x91f37e8fe55fed5f9bc75cb5f2f4d9929767ee49ef97a78cdb956dac247e1676",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXKpBiGRnKoigEpTGjNEhtudLMHDr5of2pt6b1JsNbWs3",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "**Discord Praise Bot:**\n\nAllows users to praise one another within their community for contributions, which are then stored and minted as on-chain attestations on Optimism Network.\n\nFacilitates community recognition and builds trust through transparent records of contributions.\nSince Oct 1st, 2023 to Sep 18th, 2024, We had a total of 642 Praises. Each one a statement of gratitude, as well as reputational data. \n\n200+ Active users \n\n\n\n**Praise on Farcaster:**\n\nIntegrates Praise\u2019s attestation capabilities onto Farcaster. Users can tag @givepraise to publicly appreciate other Farcaster accounts.\n\nFarcaster Frame Praise Attestations lowers the barrier to entry for creating user reputation, contributing to proof of uniqueness and reputation scores across the Web3 ecosystem.\n\n236 attestations minted since the launch on Praise Farcaster bot (within 2 weeks)\n\n76 Unique users minted attestations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "**Active Participants in Optimism Governance:**\n\nDelegates & Badgeholders:\n\nCan easily show gratitude\nCan help community members build onchain reputation. \n\nEngaged Community Members:\nGain visibility and reputation through peer recognition.\nBoosts motivation to participate in governance activities.\nBetter vibes\n\n**Individuals Verifying Reputations and Identities:**\n\nOnchain Attestations:\nProvide a transparent and verifiable record of contributions.\nAid in assessing community members' reputations.\n\nTrust Building:\nHelp users make informed decisions within governance.\nLower the barrier to entry for new contributors seeking to build trust.\n\nOverall Impact:\nSimplified the process of acknowledging contributions and verifying reputations.\nStrengthened engagement and collaboration within the Optimism governance ecosystem."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6b222a6bb4ec73470381d88ae452489c3d8be2a6655ae05f909570e35d980181",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728839016,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xc76109f3f9d42956b2ab6c72aeb10d1340325ce097a539e0b17b957f63d6455a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVnnoeQDwF7fpR5yM9cRGpwHEb61xY52MkiY1C8Eu2q7c",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "- Data interoperability and transparency within the Collective: The Optimism Collective is one of the largest DAOs, with new artifacts being released continuously. This includes information on committees & councils, list of important initiatives, links to governance, list of voters, etc. Through EIP-4824, we have created an on-chain (and off-chain) source of truth on the Optimism Collective. New artifacts can be continuously added to the Collective's daoURI, making it comprehensive over time. \n\n- Better visibility for DAO-related EAS schemas on Optimism: Currently, there is no place where DAO-related EAS schemas can be listed and indexed, along with a description and additional context. We built a proof-of-concept DAO Schema Registry.\n\n- Visibility into grants. Working with OSO and Gitcoin, we have developed an initial data lake for grants across Web3, including Optimism's grants, combating grant farming and double dipping across ecosystems."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "- Governance tooling providers: More transparency and interoperability of data direclty benefit Snapshot, Snapshot X, and a variety of other governance tools, who utilize EIP-4824 to publish and handle DAO metadata.\n\n- New participants of the OP Collective: the daoURI is a useful piece of infrastructure for anyone who'd like to find info at a single location.\n\n- Delegates: More data transparency and standardization makes it easier for even high-context individuals to assess changes across the scope of a wide, decentralized organization."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6b885ba37dad344a4ff16cf9dca60983fd87c128ff1d48aa0065cc5c9028b4be",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728924217,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x065e2f"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4b52aa0c7d0cd9cdd007050fd09e7c3d4c029d21ee4e0c0105300603b5dd51b4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNbVpTAMwE8THPDsyeaZNbNWSSzwqVMEsiAHQJNcynkLW",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "As a social influencer, I have actively contributed to the governance of OP Stack by providing insightful analyses and interpretations of its strategies and governance plans. \n\nMy work includes a series of articles that demystify complex concepts related to OP Stack, highlighting its significance in the Ethereum Layer 2 ecosystem. \n\nThrough thorough research and clear explanations, I aim to make governance more accessible to a broader audience, fostering informed discussions and facilitating better understanding of the underlying technologies and their implications.\n\nDetail as follows\uff1a\n\nhttps://github.com/tmelhao/blocktech-demystified\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "I have over 100,000 readers across my media channels and have produced hundreds of articles related to technology analysis.\n\nI possess unique insights into the trends and developments in the Layer 2 industry, and I have closely followed and analyzed the technical iterations and market collaboration plans of OP Stack. \n\nMy goal is to help the market gain a more objective and comprehensive understanding of the industry value of OP Stack."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6cfcb87a3725c5e64b014b8460eee30a93a17bfb806ada44283a3489ee025e82",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728907685,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x065e2f"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4b52aa0c7d0cd9cdd007050fd09e7c3d4c029d21ee4e0c0105300603b5dd51b4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSDKfq4gbvEUF7GGeyjUEsdHwMzTnG6yhixpS9X3yuEF2",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "As a social influencer, I have actively contributed to the governance of OP Stack by providing insightful analyses and interpretations of its strategies and governance plans. \n\nMy work includes a series of articles that demystify complex concepts related to OP Stack, highlighting its significance in the Ethereum Layer 2 ecosystem. \n\nThrough thorough research and clear explanations, I aim to make governance more accessible to a broader audience, fostering informed discussions and facilitating better understanding of the underlying technologies and their implications."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "I have over 100,000 readers across my media channels and have produced hundreds of articles related to technology analysis.\n\nI possess unique insights into the trends and developments in the Layer 2 industry, and I have closely followed and analyzed the technical iterations and market collaboration plans of OP Stack. \n\nMy goal is to help the market gain a more objective and comprehensive understanding of the industry value of OP Stack."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6e1280bbdefb03da787b0893ac7d9b3b1ac9721bf1038f9ffd33b0775820f7d6",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928797,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x642c7e6881c1ccb99bc369bf1d472f1a7de53ffdb7087266c9a22c799fbd334b",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUph2v4gSYHLMWpTwBV21jPRJmPn7faLRutyrUjwjzdbc",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Fractal Democracy: We've pioneered implementation of fractal governance structures, providing a scalable model for decentralized decision-making that could enhance all Optimism governance.\n\nProsocial Game Experimentation: We\u2019ve designed and tested various iterations of onchain social games and consensus processes, fostering collaborative product and strategy development for collective decision-making processes on Optimism.\n\nGovernance Tool Development: We've facilitated discussions and demonstrations of various governance tools, supporting their development and integration into communities interested in them across the Optimism ecosystem and beyond.\n\nGovernance Knowledge Hub: We host and record discussions with diverse blockchain governance leaders, building a rich educational resource for governance innovation and strategy.\n\nOur consistent events have provided a stable environment for ongoing governance experimentation, contributing to the evolution of Optimism's governance landscape"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "1. Governance Innovation Incubation: By providing a regular forum for experimentation with 37 events since last October, we've accelerated the development and refinement of governance tools now used in Optimism Fractal and several other communities.\n\n2. Governance Education: Our events and videos have provided an accessible entry point for both newcomers and leaders across the Superchain to learn about and engage with advanced Optimism governance concepts.\n\n3. Prototype Testing: Our community has served as an initial testing ground for governance innovations before their wider implementation in Optimism Fractal or the broader Collective.\n\n4. Governance Laboratory: Our long-running event series serves as a platform for iterative improvements, constantly refining democratic processes and contributing to the evolution of the Optimism's governance mechanisms..\n\nThese improvements have strengthened Optimism's governance by fostering innovation, education, and cross-ecosystem collaboration."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6ea7f149472e251980d3dae9a88430564fbe4651f0fc1e38fa37932e340409b1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728931830,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5012c42cba7305878e8b089efe1e356e6b32812dfcec415a037920f62ad4c685",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcSHC9pgEbnPLdKpT12k4Q6Es2qaAEEpdb5DGGEFrkMG6",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Our work has supported these key governance processes and experiments:\n\n1. Community-Driven Agenda Setting: We pioneered Cagendas and OPTOPICS, two collaborative topic selection processes using onchain reputation tokens, enhancing community engagement in governance discussions and contributing to the development of more effective deliberation methods.\n\n2. Governance Education: Our events served as an interactive platform for newcomers and leaders across the Superchain to learn about and engage with Optimism's governance processes, including RetroFunding and missions.\n\n3. RetroPGF Evaluation: RetroPitches events provided a platform for public goods creators to showcase their work, supporting the RetroPGF Round 3 evaluation process by offering badge holders insights into projects' impacts.\n\nGovernance Tool Showcases: We provided a regular forum for developers to present governance-related tools and innovations, supporting the evolution of Optimism's governance infrastructure.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Our work has improved the performance of governance processes in several ways:\n\n1. Enhanced Participation: By providing an accessible entry point to governance discussions and pioneering novel agenda games, we've increased engagement in Optimism governance and developed scalable processes that can be used to facilitate other key governance meetings.\n\n2. Improved Information Flow: Our events and video content have created a more informed governance community, facilitating better decision-making and community knowledge in various governance processes.\n\n3. Cross-Community Collaboration: We facilitated discussions between various stakeholders in the Optimism ecosystem, including delegates, council members, and builders, fostering a more cohesive governance community.\n\n4. Governance Innovation Catalyst: By providing a platform for governance experiments and tool showcases, we've accelerated the development and adoption of innovative governance mechanisms within the Optimism ecosystem."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x6f87da6a5bb950127549435f478893fd35462a39df7b1b1dfc1e50bbfd14c863",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728675000,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0d523bd741d75c42131343e11691b7f8f97fd28f55fc626c342e4cd5a590441c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRVYgMhhA7PpnWW5KYtQMhXJBWAH5NxBxH9GYJ7TqjQNy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) met its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any single entity. It increased votable supply by 24% and initiated discussions that led to on-chain protocol upgrades. The ACC built its Internal Operating Procedures (IOP) from scratch, defining voting protocols, communication channels, and reporting processes. Regular Office Hours ensured direct community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were needed.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Votable Supply: Increased from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- Delegate Engagement: 165 of 269 approvals in key voting cycles.\n- Operational Development: Established IOP and refined governance processes.\n- Community Engagement: Held Office Hours every voting cycle.\n\nMore details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x700bc5ec5e8c0d1924fc9a413ceefc8beda917bdc02666a3ab3a69377a63f9ce",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728830972,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xafbdb7da88c946def2eceee8a27b7ee32c6cfcb936186d6f8b8fb348c1e8ee30",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYAM4fbd44C8n8oSCuLEgrE7yXm75KaLwq4k2jjYrDob5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Impact Garden is used to gather standardized information on a project's impact to the Optimism Collective beyond that being self reported by applicants. The information collected is linked to the reputation of the person providing the testimonial enabling advanced weighting by the consumer of the data. Higher reputation in the Collective, can mean your testimonial is more relevant in decisions.\n\nFor Round 5, Impact Garden gathered over 100 testimonials for 35+ projects in the round. These testimonials were used by Badgeholders during the review process particularly to determine if projects were in the right sub-category and for additional information. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The audience benefiting the most from the data created by Impact Garden are Badgeholders. \n\nThrough the generation of new data in a standardized format we're bridging the gap and giving numbers, projects and contributions a context about their impact to others within the Collective. This has looked like additional data for Badgeholders in the review process and voting. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x70423a2432b563cf49cd814ff84c34b55fe94d368a8369f3b6128eb4a048ac55",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728930270,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04d50d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x770053a5a51df4d8c261b17904ed109fe65e80ceb5b007d4baa77f5459f88899",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfX4PRL8eBJmvDDAavE35ERFb6U1trcmRLMpBW4QU83YQ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We have created templates for creating frames for delegating tokens. By doing so, we attracted more users from Warpcast and made it easier for delegates. More: https://x.com/zefirium_crypto/status/1795062923720573226 "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The tool is most useful for delegates who are actively creating content on Warpcast. Our tool also attracted good organic growth in Optimism, whose chain we were the first to implement in FrameMaker, and our template was the first to create a delegation pool in OP. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x70e4dd0749accfa47bf6d948f350871dddc37df69f4f6568cd622659bfcc9994",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728739174,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x755edb9db0478a8ffa015bdb54b2f24341219b1fe34f52f9477d965b7c65c060",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmV4rtBpq4mHsoQLx2nYir2ombp7k84GMxDDCGeLzKyvs9",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Each Badgeholder session has had a different focus given that the needs are matched according to the stage of RetroRounds and the current experiments being carried out:\n\n1. Workshops on the creation of lists for 3 different categories prior to RetroRound3. I designed and ran the workshops in a couple of them with the support of 2 other Badgeholders.\n2. Istanbul Meetup @ Onchain Summit where we gathered to 1) connect, 2) explore thoughts on lists and voting, 3) learn about projects such as Pairwise. Secured a place with the OP team, created merch, and coordinated with Badgeholders attending DevConnect. \n3. Badgies Workshopping @ Eth Denver: Coordinated the event, contacted the presenting teams, and led the session. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Each session has led to different improvements in the process and experiments of RetroRounds. \nFor the first two, the outcomes are described above. \n\nFor the 3 Session, here is some additional information:\n\nIn this session the following teams presented and received feedback from Badgeholders and the Foundation:\n1. EZKL - https://retrofunding.ezkl.xyz/\n2. Buidl Guild - Metrics Based Voting\n3. Agora \n4. Pairwise\n5. EasyRPGF\n\n This session particularly informed changes in the design of voting for Round 4, the release of EZKL's proving system for Retro3 results, among other things. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x71446e655849639cbb65a6b36b2c161c19b21c1e514841030145e77e64d020af",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856232,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x717480341a65055150566321db29978380345faeff4bcbdd3e93f54acfc3f1e4",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728865013,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x4bd4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x94adbf0f02934ffded83b06f180510e1d15edfdf7fbb1bd48d475d0203c6179c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmd6ziihVwEg8EB9cMkj92BUwrEPprbwY5FePweLzhcYqh",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "OSO's infrastructure was critical to Retro Funding 4, which used \"metrics-based voting\" instead of the more traditional \"project-based voting\" interface.\n\nMetrics-based voting had never been tried before -- let alone for hundreds of projects across various chains. The data infrastructure we built was able to respond to all of this complexity and power a successful voting experience. (The same infrastructure was also used to screen projects for eligibility and assist with open source licensing checks.)\n\nOnce the models were released, we posted an audit/bug bounty to the community. Fortunately, no issues were raised. Months later, there still have not been any. \ud83d\ude05"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "We believe our infrastructure has been most valuable for Citizens, the Foundation, and other long-term minded governance participants.\n\nAs the Superchain scales, it will become increasingly impossible for every participant to have a detailed understanding of every project or category of projects. Data is necessary not only to better leverage the time of experts and ordinary citizens but also to create a more even playing field for builders.\n\nBadgeholders had many positive things to say about the experience, from significant time savings to trusting that the distribution would be fairer / more meritocratic.\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x72de6e97869208155c5914f4aa04be65901a3bd83df39dd4936c8866f2b545e5",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728885872,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x14afcfca7a32226f8e993fefc5ee3f4ac3ae1c62a03486ed213faadc8b30fb45",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNuWiTBzH2SJM9gbKMEVNQfsDw6bFnoUrbmBNafi5QT1v",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the council. In Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where the Foundation multisig was removed from the Upgrade multisig, and the Security Council became the sole signer. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x73543d9891641bb794f4bb0448d4ba190198400b12416ad2d1aeb9db926502b7",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728751080,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x077495"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa262517720fc832e8575b2590e64e7558ba521637950d5ed8cf84d0993cc5d4a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTHLZmtdhk4UXomtCMxtxxHzmGMADAbbebacuNnuhXJzp",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We developed Pairwise for RF3, and introduced category voting to make the impact measurement in the Retro Funding more organic and manageable.\n\nIn RF3, 185 users engaged, 27 badgeholders using their key.\n\nIn RF4, we expanded into a community experiment using pseudonymous voting with zk-tech. This allowed all stakeholders\u2014badgeholders, token holders, recipients, and delegates\u2014to participate freely without pressure and promote project discovery. We also distributed 4,000 OP as rewards, a 100OP to 40 lucky winners. Here you can find the [final results](https://www.pairwise.vote/rf4-results), and our [blog conclusions](https://paragraph.xyz/@pairwise) for more details on our outcomes.\n\nThe feedback from RF4 was very positive, leading to an invite to build with Optimism for RF5. For this round, we developed a star rating system, enabling participants to assign stars to projects before comparing them. This system grouped projects into tiers, significantly reducing the number of comparisons."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main target when developing the product were badgeholders, who can use Pairwise, to rank Retro Funding projects in a fun way that promotes project discovery.\n\nHowever, the entire Optimism community that used the app discovered impactful projects, bringing more visibility to emerging initiatives.\n\nProjects benefited from this increased exposure to potential users. Pairwise also sparks discussions by comparing its results to official ones, fostering deeper insights and driving more meaningful participation and progress to decentralization.\n\nThe foundation\u2019s implementation of RetroFunding was clearly informed by our work and [feedback](https://gov.optimism.io/t/retropgf-round-3-feedback-thread/6177/150?u=griff). Enabling categorical voting, and ranking projects then adjusting percentages were done in Pairwise before they were considered to be implemented in RF5&RF6. Subtracting grant amounts and soliciting comments from badgeholders were also inspired by our work, but cut from scope."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x73b919c6d072045047d5247611ac54d937685d1e26b63da3bfb994e0f05ffadf",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728924647,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04af44"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x802a9e75b95414a35bf1e4a4196205ec47ef44c09a855a573ad80902a5c0388f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmdvKQUZKFm3LSgSxNRX29b8NtvAsqhtYK1RhvgTTNKPsC",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Our DAO has 159 unique members who have provided us with 131k OP votes. We follow new proposals every day and have participated in almost every vote.\n\nIn order to attract this number of users, we held various events and engaged in media outreach. We have also done a lot of work with CIS Influencers, so the number of participants and the amount has increased several times since PRGF3. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The number of active DAO participants increased from 93 to 159 and the amount from 38k to 131k OP. So we can confidently say that we have done a great job in increasing the decentralization of the network over the last year. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x73e9613c45fcc2525d2886636d1adbb74f9eba411514dab62dfcd5ce9c31de8a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728931814,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd07f121fdf782d92d1dbaf8599c1bd4547f6d966c373c2d44d5ba36387160ae0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTjuyCZiq7WTsZTWVzX8NU2EtHDJJ4f7qQKCWA1yMjgrb",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "1. Respect Game: We've refined this core process, enabling peer evaluation of governance contributions to Optimism and creating a decentralized reputation system crucial for governance.\n\n2. Decentralized Governance Structures: Our weekly council selection and proposal review processes, based on Respect earnings, demonstrate a practical model of decentralized decision-making.\n\n3. Governance Builder Showcases: We provide a regular forum for developers to present governance-related tools and innovations, while collaborating with others.\n\n4. Governance Education: Our events serve as an interactive platform for newcomers to engage with innovative Optimism governance processes.\n\n5. Stakeholder Collaboration: We foster connections between delegates, council members, and builders, creating a more cohesive governance ecosystem and facilitating knowledge exchange.\n\nThese consistent events create a stable environment for ongoing governance experimentation and refinement on Optimism."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "1. Enhanced Governance Participation: We've increased engagement in Optimism governance by providing a regular, accessible entry point, attracting over 50 leaders to actively participate in governance practices (and many more viewers).\n\n2. Decentralized Reputation: The Respect token earned at our events has created a nuanced measure of governance contributions, improving decision-making processes and impact measurement.\n\n3. Governance Development: By providing a stable platform for governance experimentation and connecting participants, we've enabled the development of several open-source governance tools and inspired other communities to build on Optimism with these tools.\n\n4. Scalable Governance Model: Our fractal approach has demonstrated how large-scale governance decisions can be made efficiently in a decentralized manner in all other aspects of Optimism governance.\n\nThese improvements have strengthened Optimism's governance, making it more effective, inclusive, and resilient."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7423015222fe718b5b2e9f9fa57ced5e349a9ead73139db1a1e49f28faf36431",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929427,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0acc5b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5f6f1dcc39e72bb1874f7cffbb939d9d18ac545c189dac50a59a5b340ae9f3ce",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXKpBiGRnKoigEpTGjNEhtudLMHDr5of2pt6b1JsNbWs3",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "**Discord Praise Bot:**\n\nAllows users to praise one another within their community for contributions, which are then stored and minted as on-chain attestations on Optimism Network.\n\nFacilitates community recognition and builds trust through transparent records of contributions.\nSince Oct 1st, 2023 to Sep 18th, 2024, We had a total of 642 Praises. Each one a statement of gratitude, as well as reputational data. \n\n200+ Active users \n\n\n\n**Praise on Farcaster:**\n\nIntegrates Praise\u2019s attestation capabilities onto Farcaster. Users can tag @givepraise to publicly appreciate other Farcaster accounts.\n\nFarcaster Frame Praise Attestations lowers the barrier to entry for creating user reputation, contributing to proof of uniqueness and reputation scores across the Web3 ecosystem.\n\n236 attestations minted since the launch on Praise Farcaster bot (within 2 weeks)\n\n76 Unique users minted attestations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "**Active Participants in Optimism Governance:**\n\nDelegates & Badgeholders:\n\nCan easily show gratitude\nCan help community members build onchain reputation. \n\nEngaged Community Members:\nGain visibility and reputation through peer recognition.\nBoosts motivation to participate in governance activities.\nBetter vibes\n\n**Individuals Verifying Reputations and Identities:**\n\nOnchain Attestations:\nProvide a transparent and verifiable record of contributions.\nAid in assessing community members' reputations.\n\nTrust Building:\nHelp users make informed decisions within governance.\nLower the barrier to entry for new contributors seeking to build trust.\n\nOverall Impact:\nSimplified the process of acknowledging contributions and verifying reputations.\nStrengthened engagement and collaboration within the Optimism governance ecosystem."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x752a15c680ce06b5b190c2c771aaa986ea406d4c223393284c69e42a94d4231b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728673321,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x16998b93e766294349ca51aacf532d50a04f0da023684921d98670d29f5ee8e2",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmePctGMRjZCgWSucdixULCPspC5tsxooyoxEN8k3uSm9k",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Grants Council is to oversee the evaluation and approval of projects for Governance Fund grants, ensuring they align with the season's intent andthe mission requests.  \n\nKey responsibilities include:\n\n1. Grant Evaluation: Reviewing and approving grant applications that further the goals of The Collective.\n2. Mission Creation: Developing and proposing Mission Requests aligned with the broader objectives of the Optimism Collective, targeting specific ecosystem needs (Intents).\n3. Ensuring transparency by publishing reports, tracking milestone progress, and maintaining open communication with the community.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Grants Council keeps an updated communication thread here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/s6-grants-council-communication-thread/8324\n\nTo make RF6 voters life easier we compiled all our impact data here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/mid-season-6-grants-council-report/9016\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x77842fdff2e8c13d953a3714018afafa9a9f50dd8f414c5daba33dd3e6975aa0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728729064,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xafbdb7da88c946def2eceee8a27b7ee32c6cfcb936186d6f8b8fb348c1e8ee30",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYAM4fbd44C8n8oSCuLEgrE7yXm75KaLwq4k2jjYrDob5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Impact Garden is used to gather standardized information on a project's impact to the Optimism Collective beyond that being self reported by applicants. The information collected is linked to the reputation of the person providing the testimonial enabling advanced weighting by the consumer of the data. Higher reputation in the Collective, can mean your testimonial is more relevant in decisions.\n\nFor Round 5, Impact Garden gathered over 100 testimonials for 35+ projects in the round. These testimonials were used by Badgeholders during the review process particularly to determine if projects were in the right sub-category and for additional information. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The audience benefiting the most from the data created by Impact Garden are Badgeholders. \n\nThrough the generation of new data in a standardized format we're bridging the gap and giving numbers, projects and contributions a context about their impact to others within the Collective. This has looked like additional data for Badgeholders in the review process and voting. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x77ab579d993a0f026b83f7389cba83298700fd53a6e7285f4bbfa8c54f55f8e7",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728854735,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5a63077cabc930af1ed712abc7e2e00d5badb61588076819ba5b193ecb0599f9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmf7yxRYi7SBffVDrmHiWwHdQkreAUR63wg8c7ZVnEZLuj",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. \n\nFoundation Mission Request: Season 5 govNERDs\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key gov responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. GovNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\nImpact Evaluation made by the Foundation: \nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734\n\nReward Split: \nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1zzsd7p2ECdHBnQQhWMt8ivArqfUIXNv713FjrCQ51mE\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x78888cd3c8dd368f66dfa0f3f79bc2c769b263ac1e2e590039d22549ec7dab30",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728678812,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x1c57"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x07a02270e0367cc269699073b6228615a7336c7b043c390fd0b4574befecea1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTCsskKvMGNcEWN3zMuBxxxjdS2k1ARmE77sihaECbQyv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n \nRelevant Documentation:\nAnticapture Commission Mandate: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n\nAnticapture Commission Communication Thread:  https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/9\n\n\nSeason 6 Internal Operating Procedures: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-s6-internal-operating-procedures-iop/8637\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During S6 Governance (VC #25 to #28), ACC voted on the Dolomite Network upgrade proposal. ACC held discussions and shared feedback to the Foundation on the Dolomite Upgrade Proposal on certain technical aspects of the upgrade that the ACC members felt could have been better implemented. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/20 ) \n\nDuring S6 voting cycles, few Delegates encountered voting issues on the Agora UI, resulting in wrongly cast votes during a mission request vote. The ACC held internal discussions on the issue and took it up with the Agora team and worked towards resolving the issue. \n\n\nThe ACC also held a call to discuss the Accelerated Decentralization Proposal for Optimism with GFX Labs and the Foundation. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/accelerated-decentralization-proposal-for-optimism/8875/32 ) \n \nSince the Start of Season 6 of Governance, votable supply has increased by 7.31%, from 89.4m OP to 96m OP.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7a03329820566d661d760b944f32d2014c37bd4d3c3b5dd725857da4b72969d1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728855431,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0949f0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2eaeef9af26fc8fee6f1bee26e2611a250c6fc75e7e9b66829c6b9b0c3e9b266",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPuDkNPfLyrLDa2EgTRKf72HJ37y8vZC9fN2E9KTPk6m4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "The report titled 3 Retrospective Funding Case Studies covered the Optimism Retro Funding Rounds 1-3 (the latest at the time of writing). We also had folks working with the superchain partake in our grant summit/operator gathering. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Those who are interested in better understanding grant programs relative to other programs. Those who want to partake in conversations pertaining to outputs, outcomes, and impact. Those who generally want to partake in discussions around how to improve capital allocation. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7a256458ee4390d64033c7f352d762fa632a63b445e795bac83b3a96c1fcba19",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728927760,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x3bb4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xe7d5134cc9ca444b96b907f1dd7ebe9320a743518ec19fc9c7f863f88a037a87",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQWUxvnKXgE5Scn3wPTCxB2dpmEgpWTXtqPYxSqvdRgyj",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "daospace\u2019s analytics monitors key aspects of Optimism Governance by tracking Protocol Upgrades, Mission Requests, and discussions from working groups like the Grants Council, the Developer Advisory Board, and the Token House. By highlighting significant weekly forum discussions such as RPGF rounds and technical advancements, we ensure that DAO members stay informed and can easily access the most important updates without missing key details.\n\nBy highlighting Protocol Upgrades and activities within the Token House, we help members understand proposed changes, governance decisions, and their impacts on the community. We spotlight contributions from key initiatives and committees, promoting transparency and informed participation in governance discussions.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Our analytics work has benefited the following key groups:\n\nDAO Members with Limited Time: We provide concise summaries of discussions like Protocol Upgrades, Mission Requests, and Token House activities, helping busy members stay informed. For example, MatthewB found our summaries \"very helpful\" for keeping up with topics. https://gov.optimism.io/t/optimism-forum-weekly-recap-april-29-may-5-2024/8067/2\n\nTopic Creators: Our highlights increase visibility and engagement for all discussions, helping topic creators gain more participation on their posts. Whether it's Security Council Nominations or technical proposals, our summaries amplify important contributions. Delegates like Liliop.eth thanked us for amplifying their efforts - https://gov.optimism.io/t/optimism-forum-weekly-recap-may-20-2024-may-26-2024/8214/2\n\nNew Members: Our summaries help newcomers understand the DAO's structure and key discussions, equipping them with the knowledge to engage in governance effectively.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7a5842771b7360a6c22e20ec7dc7b041bf1874efc62185c17eb9b55f9a5c5989",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728767225,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0cda2e"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb23033c01d75b52917aa5bd303b278d7920a43cb2664e28ac7f68b289dd26564",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbaQbUjSoSxuD3C8nKHiBjQswwqfdP2Nm1GFXUzpRRJwH",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "RetroPGF Hub serves as the central infrastructure and governance tool for Retro Funding, a vital element of the Citizens' House. It empowers the Optimism community to actively participate in governance, explore comprehensive information, and stay well-informed about all aspects of Retro Funding.\n\nOur platform offers detailed information on Retro Funding, including its foundational concepts, the historical context of each funding round, and in-depth insights into previously funded projects. This ensures governance participants have the knowledge they need to make informed decisions.\n\nAdditionally, we enhance community engagement by providing a space for feedback on builders' project ideas. This interaction fosters a continuous learning and improvement loop that benefits both the Optimism ecosystem and the builders contributing to it."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Several users, particularly new participants in the Retro Funding process, have greatly benefited from our infrastructure. Badgeholders, key in Retro Funding governance, are a primary group that benefits. Our platform enables them to easily participate, shape Retro Funding, and access critical project data, making research and discovery more efficient for governance participants within the Citizens' House.\n\nOur platform is also recognized as a trusted source for Retro Funding details, with referrals from platforms like retrofunding.optimism.io (Optimism Official) and optimism.curiahub.xyz (CuriaLabs), directing users to project details for each funding round. This streamlines access to key information for governance participants.\n\nUltimately, our platform supports governance within the Optimism ecosystem, benefiting individual users and the broader structure. Our infrastructure continues to strengthen the Citizens' House, enhancing its ability to effectively of Retro Funding."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7c017eb542b97933cb41485a4872fe191476275366ea55b66534d41f6e32ecd7",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728932094,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03c940"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5891cf9f8826ad546a1327d3d697bc7a0b9600c20088fcb29ff64a51de27a5b9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPyePGBAtcrBUTkGBT4eJ4PqQPk8HtbnuNedf17RaZaF9",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The **Delegate Match Farcaster Frame** is designed to improve accessibility in Optimism governance by helping OP token holders find active delegates who align with their values and vision. The tool streamlines the process, allowing users to take an 11-question survey and match with active, values-aligned delegates, increasing the overall votable OP supply. [Landing page](https://delegatematch.xyz/)\n\nLeveraging Farcaster\u2019s 650K registered users and 60-100K daily active users, Delegate Match boosts exposure to the OP delegation process. Our Farcaster Frame provides a seamless experience, enabling users to make an informed decision and delegate their tokens in just five minutes. By integrating the Ethereum Attestation Service, Delegate Match supports delegate reputation-building. It provides OP holders and delegates a low-cost, high-impact, innovative delegation tool. [Onchain Metrics](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/rJaRn0UJJe)\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of **Delegate Match** are OP token holders who aren\u2019t too engaged in governance and OP delegates with active delegations. Holders can easily find and delegate or redelegate to active delegates who align with their values. OP delegates, particularly underrepresented ones, benefit from increased visibility to grow their delegations based on values alignment rather than popularity. By encouraging broader participation, Delegate Match helps decentralize governance and promotes greater equity among delegates, enabling them to play a more meaningful role in Optimism's decision-making.\n\nWe have a solid foundation and are passionately engaged in exploring innovative solutions in this uncharted territory. Our impact included critical inquiries into user experience, impact tracking, and outreach strategies so that delegation is informed, accessible, accountable, and efficient for all stakeholders. Delve into our [Vision and Insights](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/HJaVrJw1ye)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7cd33b33b9613b99777adca81c61ca0014122882b85c76cb9a97d9ab3452a487",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728881016,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x245d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9b074b1f1782f2891c77ac6de16641cde3128bf3363f78e961a3b9f3da2cd393",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZVqa3vYSMCkYbDcW1vie11UqLTz4byt2TUZtR2Gwn665",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Our tool boosts governance participation by displaying active proposals in social feeds, making it easier for Delegates and Citizens to stay informed and participate in Optimism Governance. By integrating the alerts into mainstream platforms, our widget improves the accessibility of Optimism\u2019s governance infrastructure."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of our project are Delegates and Citizens involved in Optimism Governance. They benefit from instant access to active proposals directly in their social feeds, allowing them to stay informed and ensure they don\u2019t miss important votes."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7cfc058d21a44d62f3fe2d54a6124907e03e9f45b0d2f2a5d2f678909ead6908",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728674774,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5d694af04d6b25e855751e88d4331674852fa6428ff8975ee2e0822f4b0f51f7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNzKrw9BvF9HVAhJfE3wvATzmCgB5ArzDHBSYoLLnN6Px",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Grants Council is to oversee the evaluation and approval of projects for Governance Fund grants, ensuring they align with the season's intent andthe mission requests.  \n\nKey responsibilities include:\n\n1. Grant Evaluation: Reviewing and approving grant applications that further the goals of The Collective.\n2. Ensuring transparency by publishing reports, tracking milestone progress, and maintaining open communication with the community.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Grants Council keeps an updated communication thread here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/s5-grants-council-communication-thread/8034\n\nTo make RF6 voters life easier we compiled all our impact data here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/rf6-season-5-grants-council-report/9018"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7e3dd2a1a16c51177e08b3275cc2ae1b037450b499988d0042a7f9451d20125d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857547,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2888"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x59ad253f7fc52b131273a5c1dbd709c3cde2dbb13cd9d3b8bbaa687b5b684082",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRF4sLyGvDf1r1vPSj8Gd3R6T6xZhtjLYWWfTVuj5VR3K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Gitcoin developed the voting interfaces for Retrofunding 4 & Retrofunding 5, which were used by badgeholders to allocate funds during those rounds. We worked closely with Agora, who powered the API, and Optimism, who outlined the requirements and provided designs.\n\nFor RF4, we worked closely with Open Source Observer and Optimism to implement new metrics-based discovery, selection, and weighting. Our solution allowed users to filter and evaluate projects based on various impact metrics. \n\nFor both RF 4 & RF5, we created a user-friendly interface for governance participants to allocate their votes. \n\nThese tools are primarily used within Optimism Governance to support the Retroactive Public Goods Funding process, which is a crucial part of Optimism's governance model. They aim to make the process of discovering, evaluating, and voting for projects more efficient, transparent, and user-friendly for governance participants."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The direct benefits are the Optimism badgeholders and recipients of Retrofunding. During RF4, 108 out of 133 badgeholders participated. $10M OP tokens were allocated to 207 projects. \n\nThough RF5 is still ongoing at the time of this application, participation is high. Badgeholders are expected to allocate between 2-8m OP tokens to up to 89 projects.\n\nThe team has also integrated these features into EasyRetroPGF.xyz, which makes them available to a wider range of users involved in Optimism's governance processes. The SUNNYS Awards have also been built on this same technology!"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x7e62afcb4e9db7b0e5ffb0dbee7b90df9130a557fbf0a7df53b7b79f9b9d5d16",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728739198,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xafbdb7da88c946def2eceee8a27b7ee32c6cfcb936186d6f8b8fb348c1e8ee30",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYAM4fbd44C8n8oSCuLEgrE7yXm75KaLwq4k2jjYrDob5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Impact Garden is used to gather standardized information on a project's impact to the Optimism Collective beyond that being self reported by applicants. The information collected is linked to the reputation of the person providing the testimonial enabling advanced weighting by the consumer of the data. Higher reputation in the Collective, can mean your testimonial is more relevant in decisions.\n\nFor Round 5, Impact Garden gathered over 100 testimonials for 35+ projects in the round. These testimonials were used by Badgeholders during the review process particularly to determine if projects were in the right sub-category and for additional information. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The audience benefiting the most from the data created by Impact Garden are Badgeholders. \n\nThrough the generation of new data in a standardized format we're bridging the gap and giving numbers, projects and contributions a context about their impact to others within the Collective. This has looked like additional data for Badgeholders in the review process and voting. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x808d79c93f07ec4911a14f4d04d481163cb8d6dace026ae8b080bb64235d8829",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728687565,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0d34af"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcc896c9583980a57e072fe266eee83dcbfb38f4a0fb6ca7473dedb850cd574d7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaEkYB1Fa9FMFoyun9y27y5qDADgJxzUYZPgFVBtTZgxy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "A Persian Telegram account can help in various aspects of Optimism Governance analytics work. It can be used to gather and analyze data on public sentiment, opinions, and feedback related to governance policies and decisions. This data can provide valuable insights into the levels of optimism or pessimism within the community regarding governance initiatives. Additionally, a Persian Telegram account can serve as a platform for engaging with the Persian-speaking community, gathering qualitative data, and promoting transparency and open communication within the governance process."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The benefit of a Persian Telegram channel for OP blockchain is the ability to engage directly with the Persian-speaking community interested in blockchain technology and cryptocurrency. The channel can be used to provide updates on OP blockchain developments, share educational content about blockchain technology in Persian, and create a community of like-minded individuals. By doing so, OP blockchain can strengthen its presence and credibility within the Persian-speaking market and potentially attract new users and investors. Additionally, the company can use the channel to gather feedback and insights from the Persian-speaking audience to improve its products and services. Overall, the benefit lies in establishing a strong and interactive presence within the Persian-speaking blockchain community."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x811f917b1b74956a86cef2f6da1c7d54c65cb328fac8284ad724e8433b62de2b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728923420,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xec6e00b86121671a4e49709cf1f03d42dee81187756fe0b2a2143bd369aa63b5",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmby7ruuCgS2ReuSXxccWuJjJAwojyqjjDa1P5597L5VCx",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Optimystics Tools has supported Optimism Governance by providing and maintaining essential infrastructure for decentralized decision-making over the past year:\n\n1. Initial Toolset: Our core tools have facilitated weekly Optimism Fractal events, enabling consistent governance experimentation and community building.\n\n2. Respect Infrastructure: We've maintained and upgraded the system for distributing Respect tokens, enabling a decentralized distribution amongst leading builders and governance enthusiasts.\n\n3. Council Support: Our tools have enabled the weekly formation and operation of the Optimism Fractal council, demonstrating scalable governance models and creating a well-organized governance body for the Collective.\n\nThis consistent infrastructure has allowed for the release of next-generation tools like ORDAO, Fractalgram, and the Respect Games app. It\u2019s enabled a community-driven effort with multiple development teams contributing to a growing toolkit of fractal governance tooling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "1. Builders, leaders, delegates, and other key stakeholders in the Collective have used our tools at Optimism Fractal events to earn Respect and contribute to decentralized decision-making experiments.\n\n2. Our open-source infrastructure has served as a foundation for further governance innovations on Optimism, empowering researchers and developers interested in decentralized governance.\n\n3. Our tools have provided models and insights that could enhance various governance processes, including the Token House, Citizens' House, RetroFunding, and the Anti-Capture Commission.\n\n4. Other groups like the ZAO Fractal have adopted processes to engage, govern, and grow their communities on the Superchain. \n\nOur tools have created a vibrant testbed for governance innovations, benefiting anyone interested in exploring and contributing to decentralized decision-making processes on Optimism, and providing valuable data and experiences that can inform the evolution of the Collective's governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x82783c8ea0cfd3f24730f210996efcc8e64855159e190f2dc430d176021b1733",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728931745,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03eb26"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xc1ec6c3f1ba7316d4f7788ca6f54fad2054712daec57f9e77b84f4113be71cd0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmU5QWdsN4HhWgwKoWGCLrBhYD3v8c2eeoZFFAXTss7pAp",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Introducing to the public community, such as optimism/airdrop events. Maybe this makes it easier to get to know new people. I am one of the admins in the community . Hopefully it can embrace all those new to onchain optimism "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Everyone who follows. Sometimes do giveaways. Introduce a new onchain project, like that. asia airdrop community. \n\nSupporting advancing introducing . We also have inter-community and are very well connected.Known and familiar"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8519e1dc9f5022319efabffaafd37889498590bfbd8ffc87f6b4c9a9fc75d657",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728932006,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x07c067"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0b9634f6835dea08d354d38346cf75199f0418847a4bbef31f24fd150a20d1ff",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmR1tWPyQXfnMoxeCGrmYwbCLDWFTymVhq4prnm7ECRwQF",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "During this period, we introduced decentralized voting and analytics tools that have made governance processes more accessible and transparent. These tools empowered community members to actively participate in governance, which helped increase the number of informed and engaged participants within the OP ecosystem. The workshops and interactive sessions held during these events also provided a platform for new governance leaders to emerge, which has contributed to a more diverse and resilient governance structure.\n\nWe gathered valuable feedback and insights from participants, which we analyzed and shared with the  community. This data has informed the ongoing development and refinement of OP governance frameworks, supporting greater accountability and responsiveness within the governance processes. By actively involving the community in this period, our projects have helped lay a stronger foundation for a collaborative and adaptive governance environment on Optimism."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Our facilitation work during Lagos Blockchain Week and the Base Onchain Buildathon has progressively improved the performance of governance processes by introducing tools and gathering insights that make governance more inclusive, transparent, and efficient. With the hackathon projects on beta, participants will have more accessible means to engage with governance, fostering greater understanding and involvement.\n\nAs we continue gathering feedback and refining these tools, we are actively contributing to the evolution of Optimism's governance frameworks. This ongoing process enables us to identify and address governance challenges in real time, which gradually enhances accountability and responsiveness. By iterating on these insights, we are moving towards a more data-driven governance environment that aligns better with community needs, ultimately contributing to a more dynamic and effective governance structure within Optimism."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8ab1382ee4c26e8b4d03ebc18a10d2da38ba9fc2b8ffaf2ce23065ba13663b2e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728667892,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xe10ca64de4a24a02413c35943fd5717fcfbb638a3a0726ed4a9e30f325bc014b",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNuWiTBzH2SJM9gbKMEVNQfsDw6bFnoUrbmBNafi5QT1v",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the council. In Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where the Foundation multisig was removed from the Upgrade multisig, and the Security Council became the sole signer. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8b1a39da06635169f87b06c99d0836328dfa18a97fda490e559826b52ee8293b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728676431,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8b74c81699afb5c840d8417d5b493bc90598465dd8ba1da3456f09dff792b2dd",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728831684,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf6cb09298cba874d30ce0c249b55929169927664398879532b16ae1974f8106b",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYAM4fbd44C8n8oSCuLEgrE7yXm75KaLwq4k2jjYrDob5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Impact Garden is used to gather standardized information on a project's impact to the Optimism Collective beyond that being self reported by applicants. The information collected is linked to the reputation of the person providing the testimonial enabling advanced weighting by the consumer of the data. Higher reputation in the Collective, can mean your testimonial is more relevant in decisions.\n\nFor Round 5, Impact Garden gathered over 100 testimonials for 35+ projects in the round. These testimonials were used by Badgeholders during the review process particularly to determine if projects were in the right sub-category and for additional information. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The audience benefiting the most from the data created by Impact Garden are Badgeholders. \n\nThrough the generation of new data in a standardized format we're bridging the gap and giving numbers, projects and contributions a context about their impact to others within the Collective. This has looked like additional data for Badgeholders in the review process and voting. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8c778c89a26877bb90f7b53651c9f897f7169d16d5a479c93c83edeee61a1855",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728678824,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x1c57"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8d402469d2681f25023a01407e8d511b9d26e91d8c31e81966d870dd2bc3b9b9",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728931818,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x642c7e6881c1ccb99bc369bf1d472f1a7de53ffdb7087266c9a22c799fbd334b",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUph2v4gSYHLMWpTwBV21jPRJmPn7faLRutyrUjwjzdbc",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Fractal Democracy: We've pioneered implementation of fractal governance structures, providing a scalable model for decentralized decision-making that could enhance all Optimism governance.\n\nProsocial Game Experimentation: We\u2019ve designed and tested various iterations of onchain social games and consensus processes, fostering collaborative product and strategy development for collective decision-making processes on Optimism.\n\nGovernance Tool Development: We've facilitated discussions and demonstrations of various governance tools, supporting their development and integration into communities interested in them across the Optimism ecosystem and beyond.\n\nGovernance Knowledge Hub: We host and record discussions with diverse blockchain governance leaders, building a rich educational resource for governance innovation and strategy.\n\nOur consistent events have provided a stable environment for ongoing governance experimentation, contributing to the evolution of Optimism's governance landscape"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "1. Governance Innovation Incubation: By providing a regular forum for experimentation with 37 events since last October, we've accelerated the development and refinement of governance tools now used in Optimism Fractal and several other communities.\n\n2. Governance Education: Our events and videos have provided an accessible entry point for both newcomers and leaders across the Superchain to learn about and engage with advanced Optimism governance concepts.\n\n3. Prototype Testing: Our community has served as an initial testing ground for governance innovations before their wider implementation in Optimism Fractal or the broader Collective.\n\n4. Governance Laboratory: Our long-running event series serves as a platform for iterative improvements, constantly refining democratic processes and contributing to the evolution of the Optimism's governance mechanisms..\n\nThese improvements have strengthened Optimism's governance by fostering innovation, education, and cross-ecosystem collaboration."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8d7010d7b8bcb3ced633b2b5c454f2cfba178b91b75c38c1f5038d0d72f1f9dd",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728766989,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0cda2e"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb23033c01d75b52917aa5bd303b278d7920a43cb2664e28ac7f68b289dd26564",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbaQbUjSoSxuD3C8nKHiBjQswwqfdP2Nm1GFXUzpRRJwH",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "RetroPGF Hub serves as the central infrastructure and governance tool for Retro Funding, a vital element of the Citizens' House. It empowers the Optimism community to actively participate in governance, explore comprehensive information, and stay well-informed about all aspects of Retro Funding.\n\nOur platform offers detailed information on Retro Funding, including its foundational concepts, the historical context of each funding round, and in-depth insights into previously funded projects. This ensures governance participants have the knowledge they need to make informed decisions.\n\nAdditionally, we enhance community engagement by providing a space for feedback on builders' project ideas. This interaction fosters a continuous learning and improvement loop that benefits both the Optimism ecosystem and the builders contributing to it."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Several users, particularly new participants in the Retro Funding process, have greatly benefited from our infrastructure. Badgeholders, key in Retro Funding governance, are a primary group that benefits. Our platform enables them to easily participate, shape Retro Funding, and access critical project data, making research and discovery more efficient for governance participants within the Citizens' House.\n\nOur platform is also recognized as a trusted source for Retro Funding details, with referrals from platforms like retrofunding.optimism.io (Optimism Official) and optimism.curiahub.xyz (CuriaLabs), directing users to project details for each funding round. This streamlines access to key information for governance participants.\n\nUltimately, our platform supports governance within the Optimism ecosystem, benefiting individual users and the broader structure. Our infrastructure continues to strengthen the Citizens' House, enhancing its ability to effectively of Retro Funding."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8d7a8c522276a95300fb9d3d2c3d3f76c4e7badb9bdad7f5bc301a192b734589",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728682519,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0f6705fa3f25bfb2f0b6ba4ffbabf02710c777947273b9d3947ea29a249d8ba7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQwMxbJLBbPU6r5x1yDHkUaxUPuv9LupckcKkPM32Fu4K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\n[Reflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation](https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8ef4ff5351c03a77d62cd88e08b019a53e27280b2b854f2a499ee03b3d8e9970",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728681738,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xfaa8062e77fd624737f9e7ee5ae48e9434d31433713d425efbaee35f3945d338",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQwMxbJLBbPU6r5x1yDHkUaxUPuv9LupckcKkPM32Fu4K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\n[Reflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation](https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8f83051510cf65f41a65c6a44a2fa1ea11d9fb1b939a2ba56028066fcea55dfc",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728742847,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0a0137"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x32bb4268b277d90be3b0e07ea72439026b72badae3d2a5306d96e339133917e7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmcqe5gRn5SBNWhQgrF9QJ12LPowzcgmP3emNQQ6419yoD",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Governance Vulnerability Discovery (Jan, 2024 - Oct 18, 2024)\nDuring the specified time period, we uncovered and reported a significant governance vulnerability related to voting power discrepancies within the Optimism governance framework. \n\nVulnerability Identification\nIn August 2024, we discovered a critical issue where certain addresses had disproportionately high voting power, exceeding their actual token holdings. This created the risk of skewing governance decisions and breaking the \"one token, one vote\" principle, which is foundational to decentralized governance. There was >200,000 OP which were double voted.\nThe vulnerability allows certain addresses to retain voting power for >200,000 OP even after selling the tokens, effectively doubling their influence. They could split their holdings to create multiple top 100 delegate spots for 0 token cost, further increasing their power, posing a zero-cost attack risk. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The vulnerability was reported promptly to the Optimism governance team, ensuring that the issue was addressed before it could materially impact governance outcomes in future voting cycles.\n\nCollaborative Resolution\nAfter reporting the issue, we worked with the Optimism team to clarify the problem and assist in formulating a fix. \nThe governance team implemented a fix that removed the inflated delegations and prevented such issues from happening in future voting cycles.\nThe prompt resolution and transparency around the issue maintained the integrity of the OP governance system\nToken House and RetroPGF Consideration\nThis discovery did not fall under a formal bounty program or RetroPGF framework, the Optimism governance team acknowledged the importance of the contribution and allowed for RPGF. This recognition emphasized the value of community-driven governance security efforts, even in the absence of formalized bounty structures."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x8f86175d7148863c6d4cdf89ceb87b051d9fe6ccf73214f4128a9b6c1dfc85c1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857849,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x90a62a63c25857208db3701aad9586d937c20caac71735621a1b099775a099d9",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728735223,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x94133880f1202f23baf17dca05f2a2fbd5ce215302ea6d3f4beb0fab18d26283",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856201,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x941df870ad815531f0bb1a932816799e61d92fb6d1fc2190318cf9c3513dffa3",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728887012,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4099ac09c65e46b2f27978d9b5daba7aa7d014fe8cba4169b181080da246fa35",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPgjEdDvDMsTSgv21RuJCHyZSTGaZGudX1EbV89vtpVHE",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures\n\nThe responsiveness and engagement of Security Council members exceeded expectations. Security Council members attended monthly calls, often running through signing ceremony playbooks with the OP Labs team. By the end of Season 5, the Security Council had proven it's ability to carry out required tasks and was in a position to transition from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where it would be the only signer required in order to execute a protocol upgrade. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9441a3e22580d95de3f5c0e00b826dda2e2d45ef5a06f166b08771e43f038c65",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728721527,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xfc9d9f7299072ce15b5d5cd11d16230a2383c0d5e7cd4d72f7cb135275579d8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSvAjst51EJTXhywiGahtcRSCnYBs8F8zK7SYg7SyyWCy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until September 18th, there were about 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our tool, similar to Metrics Garden, allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n\nAlso, Giveth ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise & growthepie (supporting OP Governance) alongside projects that are making real world impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF. Projects\u2019 order of appearance in the rounds could be changed by using our GIVpower governance system on OP mainnet. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "DeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects and any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project. For example, you can quickly see that 2 RF 4 Badgeholder, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passports, 1 RF 5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nFlagging projects is especially helpful. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5 to ensure there were no imposters posing to be them in the round. If there would have been an imposter, the project would have seen the tweet, been able to flag it on DeVouch and report it to the Foundation.\n\nOn the fundraising side, Giveth enabled EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise, growthepie, and several other OP Governance-related projects to collect much needed funds to continue their work in the Collective.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x944b9ab52043115acd42554edf927c63c95fd244c7d6584f048ab7126ddcae53",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837679,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0ce07d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcdd4b6445288c5bebd951191d673a7aecefbbf6be1cacf4f2a96bcba9c356c33",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRTb1gtuxYNvue67dGwAXDFAWKNiJfTERHfEwC3Nz38Zs",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Builder Ideas plays a crucial role in supporting Optimism Governance by providing a dedicated platform where actionable ideas for builders can be posted by the Optimism Foundation, OP Labs, Coinbase, and other core developments. This platform fosters a culture of open collaboration, empowering developers to contribute meaningfully to the collective goals of the Optimism ecosystem.\n\nInitially, ideas were managed through GitHub Issues in the ecosystem contributions repository, which was unstructured and difficult to navigate. Developers faced challenges in discovering and submitting potential projects, which hindered engagement and contributions.\n\nTo address this, in collaboration with the Optimism Foundation, we redesigned the platform, transitioning from GitHub to a dedicated website. This move significantly improved accessibility, making it easier for developers to explore governance initiatives, submit their contributions, and enhance the overall impact of the Optimism Collective."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our platform primarily benefits builders and developers by providing a centralized space where they can easily browse project ideas curated by the Optimism Foundation and other core development teams. By selecting ideas from the platform, developers can contribute to meaningful projects and apply for Retro Funding, creating a pathway to gain recognition and seek financial support for their projects. This fosters a more inclusive and accessible ecosystem for developer contributions.\n\nIn addition to benefiting builders, the platform significantly aids the Optimism Foundation by offering a structured way to list potential projects and track contributors willing to execute these ideas. This improved organization enables the Foundation to efficiently match talent with opportunities, ultimately boosting both the number and quality of contributions across the Superchain. The increased engagement from builders accelerates ecosystem growth and advances the goals of Optimism Governance."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9617b140df0c106fa3c3db0b6b8adb4025725350bfd786c0bdc5fe7041985b6b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856224,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9644643b273eea3c33b365d59f56069ac26775291d45f4758eefcfdaf4eecdd7",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728680960,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xbb84f3a7463ca746831ce765bd83b33c13e55712c0b8d1c3e74096a120ca0527",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQwMxbJLBbPU6r5x1yDHkUaxUPuv9LupckcKkPM32Fu4K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\n[Reflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation](https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x96b2064cfd8c96d7d6c3f52caca942368ab30ae504491afe7bc871eb46bc5f6b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728930278,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04d50d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xfc09c906c1c96cc2b481ce3bc5bc93d3d43cc4d56fd0e2f99cc05a2fbc78face",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qme5EewQE8B7yp3ke1NeTBjV52ryiUVGmuTs3MdXhJ5d4Q",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "- Expanding the governance participant pool \n- Calls have been made with the community about the importance of governance participation and increasing audience trust \n- Five calls were conducted with the community "
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "- Over the past few months, I have been able to increase our DAO by several times (this applies to both participants and pool size) - (36\u043a -> 136k OP / 40 people -> 160+ ) (https://vote.optimism.io/delegates/0x03dde7b6c372bc6c748ae1af65497b74a70492fa)\n- Increasing community involvement in management\n- I also continue to publicize the importance of delegation and increase the incremental impact\n- Many of my trainees have gotten drops for delegating and participating in the superchain ecosystem"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x975b5fb523b80355c85887c0128b5ef3ae71997fed29c65a204609ead167f423",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728667515,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0e6810b99b7c063ed00cf321f74b8d40a7945c471c6d2b70939d32fa1316fba7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQdPhcxChaAq5h4MJR8XScebDysxukQK1t5bCKSfZFGNg",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x98ec56a9c7f577817dbce0f0a6a85859f77fd28ce78d0191f77030041e78ea23",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728926198,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0acc5b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf09498aa7a9e39a7a9bcde96bef9ba52e9c34ba8178cf90f080ac973b88cd19d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmeL4bx179UJJeWi4WhGEWs5nScsEMUBfrwTuPUYxLdAtp",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Superchain Attestation Explorer provides a more user-friendly and accessible way for badge holders to review and verify user reputations. While existing EAS attestation explorers present raw and inclusive data, the Superchain Attestation Explorer refines this by focusing on the most useful attestation services for governance.\n\nDisplaying key attestation data in a more digestible format allows badge holders to evaluate contributions and trustworthiness within the ecosystem efficiently, enhancing decision-making during critical governance processes like RetroFunding.\n\nCurrently, the explorer showcases eight core attestation services, including six on Optimism network and two on BASE. This integration across multiple chains positions the explorer as a Superchain attestation tool, reinforcing its role as an essential infrastructure for reviewing OP attestations:\n\n\nPraise Discord Bot\nRegen Score\nOptimist\nPassport Score\nPraise on Farcaster\nCoordinape\nDeVouch\nMetrics Garden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of the Superchain Attestation Explorer are badge holders and governance participants involved in the Retro Funding process. Specifically, OP Citizens and delegates rely on the tool to efficiently review user reputations and contributions within the Optimism ecosystem. \n\nBy offering a more readable interface than raw data explorers like EAS, the Attestation Explorer helps these participants make more informed decisions during governance activities.\n\nIn addition, the tool helps Retro Funding voters better assess contributors' impact and credibility, ensuring that governance rewards are distributed based on verified, high-quality contributions. \nAs the platform expands to include new services across Optimism and BASE, the broader Superchain governance community will also benefit from easier cross-chain attestation visibility."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x997cea0c093ba8245a06bd9816d4b5b009db5d3ac30d4dac660fbd92b56d5a6f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728680980,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9b568ab201301ab9b0a9afb94add29f9b010578acdd4743aba8d21b7b8458abf",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728852040,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x07a02270e0367cc269699073b6228615a7336c7b043c390fd0b4574befecea1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTCsskKvMGNcEWN3zMuBxxxjdS2k1ARmE77sihaECbQyv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n \nRelevant Documentation:\nAnticapture Commission Mandate: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n\nAnticapture Commission Communication Thread:  https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/9\n\n\nSeason 6 Internal Operating Procedures: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-s6-internal-operating-procedures-iop/8637\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During S6 Governance (VC #25 to #28), ACC voted on the Dolomite Network upgrade proposal. ACC held discussions and shared feedback to the Foundation on the Dolomite Upgrade Proposal on certain technical aspects of the upgrade that the ACC members felt could have been better implemented. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/20 ) \n\nDuring S6 voting cycles, few Delegates encountered voting issues on the Agora UI, resulting in wrongly cast votes during a mission request vote. The ACC held internal discussions on the issue and took it up with the Agora team and worked towards resolving the issue. \n\n\nThe ACC also held a call to discuss the Accelerated Decentralization Proposal for Optimism with GFX Labs and the Foundation. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/accelerated-decentralization-proposal-for-optimism/8875/32 ) \n \nSince the Start of Season 6 of Governance, votable supply has increased by 7.31%, from 89.4m OP to 96m OP.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9c27989919d7e3ad7f1a49d438580162e916d1093c4d7ee98228097433b7c830",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728789898,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2a7741e308dcd63767341589aa4b6d52b41c3af95170537e52248cd58dd7dab1",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSvAjst51EJTXhywiGahtcRSCnYBs8F8zK7SYg7SyyWCy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until September 18th, there were about 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our tool, similar to Metrics Garden, allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n\nAlso, Giveth ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise & growthepie (supporting OP Governance) alongside projects that are making real world impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF. Projects\u2019 order of appearance in the rounds could be changed by using our GIVpower governance system on OP mainnet. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "DeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects and any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project. For example, you can quickly see that 2 RF 4 Badgeholder, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passports, 1 RF 5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nFlagging projects is especially helpful. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5 to ensure there were no imposters posing to be them in the round. If there would have been an imposter, the project would have seen the tweet, been able to flag it on DeVouch and report it to the Foundation.\n\nOn the fundraising side, Giveth enabled EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise, growthepie, and several other OP Governance-related projects to collect much needed funds to continue their work in the Collective.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9d5d111aeaf059e96473230efd6dcf81dfc8c8dec07f67d4bba1e0e68c87cd1e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728888785,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4776c7cc4b248472758e9f111d0f705d4cc7042d9dea575bb53e6da9419a3c0d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmecufzGiYejjr8dBxyX9V3e8B8AB31ykYqPBDGZpoauc6",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "- Data interoperability and transparency within the Collective: The Optimism Collective is one of the largest DAOs, with new artifacts being released continuously. Through EIP-4824, we have created an on-chain (and off-chain) source of truth on the Optimism Collective. New artifacts can be continuously added to the Collective's daoURI, making it comprehensive over time. \n\n- Better visibility for DAO-related EAS schemas on Optimism: Currently, there is no place where DAO-related EAS schemas can be listed and indexed, along with a description and additional context. We built a proof-of-concept DAO Schema Registry.\n\n- Visibility into grants. Working with OSO and Gitcoin, we have developed an initial data lake for grants across Web3, including Optimism's grants, combating grant farming and double dipping across ecosystems."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "- Governance tooling providers: More transparency and interoperability of data direclty benefit Snapshot, Snapshot X, and a variety of other governance tools, who utilize EIP-4824 to publish and handle DAO metadata.\n\n- New participants of the OP Collective: the daoURI is a useful piece of infrastructure for anyone who'd like to find info at a single location.\n\n- Delegates: More data transparency and standardization makes it easier for even high-context individuals to assess changes across the scope of a wide, decentralized organization.\n\n- Grantees: Our work on grants management improves the odds of genuine projects' access to capital. It also helps the Optimism Collective reward contributions more efficiently."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0x9f35d751f2d3f5ea7ea2a2dad9abf0f6d408271b4130936f88493bc1688f632d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856859,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd9dd636dac5d307af119d18779df8aeecc5c8879a1e8b46edef428987c584f06",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXL89B7fJbPoGVQE7VLHUX1CJfTdr5z8Rd4fgtAkw8udf",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team's mandate is to:\n\n1. Reduce the Foundation's workload in governance operations\n2. Onboard and mentor new contributors and delegates to the Collective\n3. Facilitate efficient governance processes across Token House, Grants Council, and Citizens House\n\nOur mission is detailed in the Optimism Contribution Path: https://community.optimism.io/contribute/contribution-path/govnerds\n\nFor more information about the govNERD Maintainers, please refer to the Foundation Mission Request:\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/182\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team has surpassed its mandate through targeted actions and measurable outcomes:\n\n- Significantly reducing the Foundation\u2019s workload in governance operations, with expectations of increased responsibilities next season as a testament to our effectiveness.\n- Directly mentoring 4 govNERDs-in-training and guiding approximately 10 wannabe-govNERDs, creating a pipeline of  contributors to the Collective.\n- Serving as Lead Reviewer in the Application Review process for Retro Funding Rounds 5 and 6.\n- Boost governance participation with 100% of Token House proposals meeting quorum by distributing +21 voting cycle announcements.\n\nReward split:\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1V8q1NqqGazQgbduK3dMv1tzMjQU9OxkUj4YINe_mEas\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa0580288a9dc23b1c08e799c1e533b7e42981cbe80ff81cd35e12f22a7fea33c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728826465,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf28aed7abdfa614dc86241ad037081d21c10670934f2e1701d1f8306b9609e07",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmP3nVUn9qAAzPuEqmEFhs9AnfDH77RBF8HemQDePR77Gv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "My work focused on improving mission request tracking, enhancing process clarity, and boosting efficiency. The dashboard allowed delegates to easily learn how to apply, how much to ask for, and monitor progress, ensuring informed decision-making. For grant applicants, it simplified aligning applications with mission requests, so they knew exactly which request to apply for, reducing confusion.\n\nThe tool also proved invaluable for voters during the voting process. It provided a clear, intent-wise snapshot of all mission requests, allowing them to see the big picture of budget allocation and compare the asks of different requests. This eliminated the need to manually navigate through each forum link, saving time and reducing overwhelm. Voters could quickly assess and compare the status and requests, ensuring more efficient and informed decision-making without getting lost in the complexity of multiple mission requests scattered across the forum.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "70+ visitors (delegates, applicants, voters) leveraged the dashboard for tracking, aligning proposals, and efficiently comparing mission requests for allocating budget intent-wise.\nThe dashboard\u2019s clarity and structure increased engagement across all stakeholders, from mission requests to voting outcomes.\nA simplified and transparent mission tracking system made the governance process easier for new participants.\nImproved proposal alignment enhanced the quality and effectiveness of applications, making the process more efficient and impactful for all involved.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa1664c2695d76687e58951671ed159622210b7c1963c1f275d9808f73fff8062",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728869530,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcf20ed439ded4b410bd0a4173084e1d782d187d453022ad75e08b6e58b04f14d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSTxETgqsUkjNr5E7vu8QpxBafWrXDnhK7pe9cvKKHZMk",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until Sep 18th, there were over 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our modular tool allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nDeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects & any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project; e.g. you can quickly see that 2 RF4 Badgeholders, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passport Holders, 1 RF5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged during the review period. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The OP community (esp. delegates) can support projects that are adding value to the Superchain Community. While unable to participate in Retro Funding directly, through DeVouch, they can lend their credibility to them, and leave a comment about the project using our extremely easy to use UX. [Try it out!](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf6)\n\nVoters & reviewers in Retro Funding programs are able to incorporate the wisdom of the crowds. \n\nWe helped the Foundation prevent imposters. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5. If impersonation occurred, the project would have seen the tweet, flagged it on DeVouch and reported it.\n\nProjects have a simple way to prove their legitimacy in an industry ripe with scams. Giveth also ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise & growthepie alongside projects that are making irl impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa32ee554780ed85f5cfcdb2df6a5207b498d3209cc539f0d3e04d32f5f15a303",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728735239,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x06be135bacb0befa9a0d9af56fa01288537a786efc3cc659347b92204d8bae2e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmR1PZ2BkGTTXQuxr1oKmqkxk7mVmPSAcDNnWYXSxt8ZGZ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Impact Evaluation Framework has been used to inform Badgeholders voting in Retro3 by supporting the creation of Lists, providing context into the Collective for new voters inspired metrics generated for Round 4 and onwards for projects contributing to the Collective. \n\nThe Metrics Garden Database, which has served to inform the creation of new Metrics Gardens has also informed the evaluation criteria for RetroRounds from Ecosystems such as libp2p and Filecoin which have enabled to fund downstream Optimism dependencies: https://www.notion.so/a60768062a2e4e5f8b4ea787e73d38b5?v=468228b4f651454aaf4296934a8a18bd\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The participants who have benefitted the most from the Impact Evaluation Framework have been Badgeholders who leveraged this tool to inform their voting in Round3.\n\nSome testimonials can be found here:\n- On Lists: https://gov.optimism.io/t/round-3-voting-rationale/7030/5\n- On Impact: https://gov.optimism.io/t/joans-rpgf3-reflections/7221\n- On Voting: https://x.com/brichis_/status/1732146910708806069?s=20\n- On Evaluation Criteria: https://github.com/0xyNaMu/RetroPGF3List_Methodology/tree/ContributorTracks"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa40261cd78b004c9e9d043fb109db9df66f286c871558b71a5c27850f1426644",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728889580,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x051b41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa636873848ff33b155a0400e2ed51a443573b64a1eee8e7c6b6f2907a5a97d1f",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXi2fyGB1iLQ9iUtzrqXCmRwtkj22NjsjbA3WSUDApDw6",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The impact on this community is to increase the number of Optimse onchain through open media information about optimization developments such as grants, airdrops, retroactives. for example what happened yesterday (airdrop 5 OP), Partner (Layer 3), to Superchain activity."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Spreading the development of optimism information through the telegram channel (@airdropfinder) with 567k members. This can help spread widely to other OP communities and not only telegram, RPS1N spreads through social media accounts such as x (twitter)."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa4c06b0df45ea3cf4797ad8738377f7ea42410e56e7ca2ff94813ad73fdf81f4",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728792594,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03607f"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x7804f90e449ed76dda49075d8acff485830234815add93170bcf31df070bd5e4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVAV3W4wFer33e8DnLUsMBostDsrhtQTyotUtsTKYuBQh",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analysis identifies the characteristics of the fund distribution methods used in the Optimism Collective\u2019s grant programs by comparing them with other grant programs. We analyze distribution patterns, such as the size of grants, the number of recipients, decision-making processes, and how evenly resources are allocated, highlighting how Optimism\u2019s fund distribution differs from other governance models. We have found that Optimism provides relatively larger grants, supports a greater number of recipients, and shows less variation in the amount granted per recipient. We also examine how effective Optimism\u2019s governance structure is in promoting fair and impactful public goods funding. Additionally, we expect this analysis to lead to the proposal of new types of grants and the measurement and evaluation of impact based on data, contributing to more effective funding practices."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of our analytical work are decision-makers involved in Optimism Collective\u2019s grant distribution, as well as those looking to improve grant allocation models and governance mechanisms. By providing insights into fund distribution patterns and the effectiveness of different governance mechanisms, we support these stakeholders in making evidence-based decisions. This will enable the Optimism Collective to contribute to the Optimism ecosystem, the Ethereum ecosystem, and real-world public goods, making true public goods funding a reality through evidence-based decision-making. Our research helps contributors make informed decisions."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa4e4618bc2faa690d2369cd24e0f57ff5bc8d8c4a7a94e4ce8112cd8bb9ef865",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929713,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03c940"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x916f6255ae44902f7686cc2fa6f762e22a1d69b815f00769201becfa6b8764ae",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZk7QPjbkVKxchcJmqmfV3J6C82EYrPjwmgBxyJo48SdV",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The **Delegate Match Farcaster Frame** is designed to improve accessibility in Optimism governance by helping OP token holders find active delegates who align with their values and vision. The tool streamlines the process, allowing users to take an 11-question survey and match with active, values-aligned delegates, increasing the overall votable OP supply. [Landing page](https://delegatematch.xyz/)\n\nLeveraging Farcaster\u2019s 650K registered users and 60-100K daily active users, Delegate Match boosts exposure to the OP delegation process. Our Farcaster Frame provides a seamless experience, enabling users to make an informed decision and delegate their tokens in just five minutes. By integrating the Ethereum Attestation Service, Delegate Match supports delegate reputation-building. It provides OP holders and delegates a low-cost, high-impact, innovative delegation tool. [Onchain Metrics](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/rJaRn0UJJe)\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of **Delegate Match** are OP token holders who aren\u2019t too engaged in governance and OP delegates with active delegations. Holders can easily find and delegate or redelegate to active delegates who align with their values. OP delegates, particularly underrepresented ones, benefit from increased visibility to grow their delegations based on values alignment rather than popularity. By encouraging broader participation, Delegate Match helps decentralize governance and promotes greater equity among delegates, enabling them to play a more meaningful role in Optimism's decision-making.\n\nWe have a solid foundation and are passionately engaged in exploring innovative solutions in this uncharted territory. Our focus includes critical inquiries into user experience, impact tracking, and outreach strategies so that delegation is informed, accessible, accountable, and efficient for all stakeholders. Delve into our [Vision and Insights](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/HJaVrJw1ye)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa4feb5f5036165d54fb6d97775190af6bc4b5d93a32ae42e9a7e1ac2f0b2f10f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728670285,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb8cc7c0f9b46f7683c167c77ca0ccfb4a5a100eea6172b537e6d8ba263f3a00c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQdPhcxChaAq5h4MJR8XScebDysxukQK1t5bCKSfZFGNg",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5 the Optimism Security Council was setup and members were ratified. The responsibilities are set out in the Security Council Charter. During Phase 0, the Security Council carried out its required responsibilities without any issues.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council successfully completed rehearsals, and was responsible for signing the following upgrades:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 6 \u2014 Multi-Chain Prep\n\u2705 SC signing: April 8 - April 11\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed April 11 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 4\n\u2705 SC signing: Feb 22 - Feb 26\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed Feb 26 with 13/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa62f887a4def118482c65d61bbf5e55d75d28925efb5207268aea95486bca8fd",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837843,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1cfa24a1212d4b707b48d7b35795fedd3497654e7278e464943e395cf21ed801",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTdFgUswEpM51G1m2CzDRuSy53ppqu7RSiySpDZB8jHHU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Each Badgeholder session has had a different focus given that the needs are matched according to the stage of RetroRounds and the current experiments being carried out:\n\n1. Workshops on the creation of lists for 3 different categories prior to RetroRound3. I designed and ran the workshops in a couple of them with the support of 2 other Badgeholders.\n2. Istanbul Meetup @ Onchain Summit where we gathered to 1) connect, 2) explore thoughts on lists and voting, 3) learn about projects such as Pairwise. Secured a place with the OP team, created merch, and coordinated with Badgeholders attending DevConnect. \n3. Badgies Workshopping @ Eth Denver: Coordinated the event, contacted the presenting teams, and led the session. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Each session has led to different improvements in the process and experiments of RetroRounds. \nFor the first two, the outcomes are described above. \n\nFor the 3 Session, here is some additional information:\n\nIn this session the following teams presented and received feedback from Badgeholders and the Foundation:\n1. EZKL - https://retrofunding.ezkl.xyz/\n2. Buidl Guild - Metrics Based Voting\n3. Agora \n4. Pairwise\n5. EasyRPGF\n\n This session particularly informed changes in the design of voting for Round 4, the release of EZKL's proving system for Retro3 results, among other things.  "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa8efee097b86228d4aeb02e7de11024761a740081ec36b9855e3af25f3a84584",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856216,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd9dd636dac5d307af119d18779df8aeecc5c8879a1e8b46edef428987c584f06",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXL89B7fJbPoGVQE7VLHUX1CJfTdr5z8Rd4fgtAkw8udf",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team's mandate is to:\n\n1. Reduce the Foundation's workload in governance operations\n2. Onboard and mentor new contributors and delegates to the Collective\n3. Facilitate efficient governance processes across Token House, Grants Council, and Citizens House\n\nOur mission is detailed in the Optimism Contribution Path: https://community.optimism.io/contribute/contribution-path/govnerds\n\nFor more information about the govNERD Maintainers, please refer to the Foundation Mission Request:\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/182\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team has surpassed its mandate through targeted actions and measurable outcomes:\n\n- Significantly reducing the Foundation\u2019s workload in governance operations, with expectations of increased responsibilities next season as a testament to our effectiveness.\n- Directly mentoring 4 govNERDs-in-training and guiding approximately 10 wannabe-govNERDs, creating a pipeline of  contributors to the Collective.\n- Serving as Lead Reviewer in the Application Review process for Retro Funding Rounds 5 and 6.\n- Boost governance participation with 100% of Token House proposals meeting quorum by distributing +21 voting cycle announcements.\n\nReward split:\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1V8q1NqqGazQgbduK3dMv1tzMjQU9OxkUj4YINe_mEas\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa9078ee0d9cc9b87f7e1bc2194804a11e84d978f276786f8df41d4361a438823",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728851351,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf5519a31d49c637d8f00ff3c17fe9a685b159d2f46e6799a53860ff42b2a79b0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNTck9VBVraFkLhmZegbmcdKn84JjXFrp3dwZkvEeuRQC",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. \n\nFoundation Mission Request: Season 5 govNERDs\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\nReflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation: https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xa9988c1f926cd84a3b6942f1aa61ce0c1e4dec133b43275c359287e06b86e432",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728712969,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xabbb321b6544b6b9ae33bb6f938cc5188358a34b2e235bcc3e7237595eb6f847",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728831991,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xabc3d06ea850e55aaa1100cbb69285d3374bf54bb1832ff8277ce105813b18be",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728854738,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xad2dbec33c89a3dd8e07217e751450ae9ed7b5abfbd97511aae32d34cea7b0f4",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929730,
    "round": "5",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0846b0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xfd007f36ebbc3e853cb75721f7f4c6f12f8e98629831648018130bfa430f826e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmetcT7oT6dBdBfjtKM1Qz9QffakzZFCKQP8HyMDyuqyi2",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 5,
      "category": "OP Stack Research & Development",
      "subcategory": [
        "Security audits specifically on the OP Stack or its components."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How has your project advanced the development of the OP Stack?",
          "answer": "Cantina/Spearbit has advanced the development of the OP Stack by providing critical security audits and reviews to ensure the robustness and safety of its components. Our team has conducted multiple audits of the OP Stack, including security reviews of Optimism's EAS, which are crucial for cross-chain functionality and gas optimization. Through these audits, we have identified vulnerabilities, suggested optimizations, and collaborated with Optimism team to ensure that the OP Stack is secure and resilient.\n\nAdditionally, our continuous monitoring, advisory services, and incident response support help maintain the OP Stack's reliability, safeguarding its smart contracts and infrastructure.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited the most from your work on the OP Stack and how?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of our work on the OP Stack have been developers and projects building within the Optimism ecosystem, as well as the broader Optimism community. By conducting thorough security audits, we have ensured that developers can deploy secure smart contracts, reducing the risk of exploits and vulnerabilities.\n\nProjects like Omni-x and Decent.xyz, which rely on cross-chain capabilities and transaction efficiency, have directly benefited from our security reviews, enabling them to operate safely and scale their solutions across multiple chains.\n\nOur work has enhanced trust and reliability in the OP Stack, making it safer for both developers and users."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xade73ddd005a79fe8fb0589cfacd0439f49cbc972a274c1f99d4c84e6a01dfe1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728890020,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x051b41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xdbd3808ca533593e4c0e1c91bb80670b523cd85440520f6e4a9ec6bc8179af0a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVWc1Ftz7Pf8mTdkVqdFNhHHTgPWuSebLmHfu8rusrLmG",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The impact on this community is to increase the number of Optimse onchain through open media information about optimization developments such as grants, airdrops, retroactives. for example what happened yesterday (airdrop 5 OP), Partner (Layer3), to Superchain activity."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Spreading the development of optimism information through the telegram channel (@airdropfinder) with 567k members. This can help spread widely to other OP communities and not only telegram, RPS1N spreads through social media accounts such as x (twitter)."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xae57faba48315cd7fc519b30563dfbfaca0a66b3bc79a4a753f3449f00a74ec0",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728826159,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2888b2d5735a0844dd9bdc4ac4ec022be0a26fa886d8329727a49d69741262d0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYvFqHnPV1Yyk8HRztMtAEAt4nmKPn6kafuAp22DvP2pX",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "The numbaNERDs Program measures several key aspects of Optimism Governance:\n\nGrant Utilization: Tracking how funds are used by recipients and whether milestones are met, ensuring proper fund allocation.\n\nGrants Misuse: Validating reports of misuse through the grants misuse reporting policy, ensuring accountability and corrective actions.\n\nContributor Validation: Ensuring data accuracy by having numbaNERDs validate key reports for governance decisions.\n\nGovernance Accountability: Monitoring protocol adherence to governance rules and enforcing consequences for violations.\n\nData Infrastructure: Building analytics infrastructure for various protocols, initially on OP Mainnet, and later expanding to early Superchain members.\n\nThese analytics strengthen transparency, accountability, and decision-making across Optimism\u2019s governance.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The numbaNERDs Program has significantly advanced governance-related analytics, data infrastructure, and transparency within the Optimism ecosystem, fostering growth and enabling informed decision-making. With 95 bounties completed and 3 grants misuse reports validated by numbaNERDs, the collective contributions of the numbaNERDs community have propelled Optimism's data infrastructure to excel beyond any other protocol in the blockchain ecosystem.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xae5d07d59320602eaac8c3ae58780cbbaf67ddd929d8b77d5cc545b7ce6c5f01",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728907035,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x5314"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0a5b755e094eeeb5bc3f8f1b26b781b2be0906f2bc86144768a566141e45caa4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQKm6uEgDrXLT5XKj2Fomhf7W6BmcbyihunCUcFdHquKN",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We built this site in response to forum feedback, where many community members shared feeling overwhelmed by the constantly evolving nature of Optimism governance, in particular the many novel experiments around grant programs.\n\nWhile rapid iteration is good for innovation (yay!), it also made it more challenging to stay up-to-date without first having to \"navigate a maze of forum posts\". We made it easy to access all deadlines and changes to programs in one place.\n\nThis has been well received: In the period between Oct 2023 and Sept 2024, there have been 2.9K outbound link clicks from our site to the Charmverse Grants Council page, 1.1K clicks to the Foundation Mission Requests pages on GitHub, and 605 clicks to forum posts on Retro Funding Rounds."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our site has primarily been useful as tool for supporting those involved in grants processes, including the Grants Council, Retro Funding Rounds and (Foundation) Mission Requests.\n\nThe subscribers of our newsletter where we used to share weekly updates, before then focusing primarily on the website, include employees from OP Labs, OpenZeppelin and Wakeup Labs. \n\nThe teams behind grantee projects such as OpenZeppelin are those who likely benefited most from our overview of the current status of grant programs, upcoming deadlines, our grants calendar, and the changelog. They otherwise would have had a much higher workload by having to keep track of this information across a number of different channels (GitHub, Grants Council Charmverse page, Forum, ...)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xae6596b0be66c41676b5ec157dd7ceeca762e9239cf14408ad262f516071c778",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728722588,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x21b3c7ce936e446c7e3b1abbe638b5c08f07ada3f0022b8f855fe30e6303c4b1",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSvAjst51EJTXhywiGahtcRSCnYBs8F8zK7SYg7SyyWCy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until September 18th, there were about 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our tool, similar to Metrics Garden, allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n\nAlso, Giveth ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise & growthepie (supporting OP Governance) alongside projects that are making real world impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF. Projects\u2019 order of appearance in the rounds could be changed by using our GIVpower governance system on OP mainnet. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "DeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects and any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project. For example, you can quickly see that 2 RF 4 Badgeholder, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passports, 1 RF 5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nFlagging projects is especially helpful. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5 to ensure there were no imposters posing to be them in the round. If there would have been an imposter, the project would have seen the tweet, been able to flag it on DeVouch and report it to the Foundation.\n\nOn the fundraising side, Giveth enabled EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise, growthepie, and several other OP Governance-related projects to collect much needed funds to continue their work in the Collective.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xaec8925a77cecde3ac9f5411547c1386fb118795fdfa1e34d61fed7814c8570c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728906251,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x7cc91dac66e954c8efb4db0d67a92702049b9122e88764cf31f172b1d7c31beb",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXL89B7fJbPoGVQE7VLHUX1CJfTdr5z8Rd4fgtAkw8udf",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team's mandate is to:\n\n1. Reduce the Foundation's workload in governance operations\n2. Onboard and mentor new contributors and delegates to the Collective\n3. Facilitate efficient governance processes across Token House, Grants Council, and Citizens House\n\nOur mission is detailed in the Optimism Contribution Path: https://community.optimism.io/contribute/contribution-path/govnerds\n\nFor more information about the govNERD Maintainers, please refer to the Foundation Mission Request:\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/182\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team has surpassed its mandate through targeted actions and measurable outcomes:\n\n- Significantly reducing the Foundation\u2019s workload in governance operations, with expectations of increased responsibilities next season as a testament to our effectiveness.\n- Directly mentoring 4 govNERDs-in-training and guiding approximately 10 wannabe-govNERDs, creating a pipeline of  contributors to the Collective.\n- Serving as Lead Reviewer in the Application Review process for Retro Funding Rounds 5 and 6.\n- Boost governance participation with 100% of Token House proposals meeting quorum by distributing +21 voting cycle announcements.\n\nReward split:\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1V8q1NqqGazQgbduK3dMv1tzMjQU9OxkUj4YINe_mEas\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xaef231721bdcdcb42b88a2547eb3355df9903c5290898afb19b6af0917ce62ee",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728869362,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd04ba29a85a79934a456db660e08fa31a5290ef57ec47419f2170e48406c1c30",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSTxETgqsUkjNr5E7vu8QpxBafWrXDnhK7pe9cvKKHZMk",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until Sep 18th, there were over 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our modular tool allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nDeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects & any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project; e.g. you can quickly see that 2 RF4 Badgeholders, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passport Holders, 1 RF5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged during the review period. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The OP community (esp. delegates) can support projects that are adding value to the Superchain Community. While unable to participate in Retro Funding directly, through DeVouch, they can lend their credibility to them, and leave a comment about the project using our extremely easy to use UX. [Try it out!](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf6)\n\nVoters & reviewers in Retro Funding programs are able to incorporate the wisdom of the crowds. \n\nWe helped the Foundation prevent imposters. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5. If impersonation occurred, the project would have seen the tweet, flagged it on DeVouch and reported it.\n\nProjects have a simple way to prove their legitimacy in an industry ripe with scams. Giveth also ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise & growthepie alongside projects that are making irl impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xaf86cbee4545b57ff1633dd3eea132c45e9dad6543dabfd00900e575339c2e7a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728751221,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xc15e6abe75012efb2ad84ac6b69c0d27d5eb70f78506f44931250c935cf4de65",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaDePjTTYmem5A2yEJUBjhkboGpj5hyk6MCT8XC6eVQEU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our work measures the concentration of power within Optimism Collective using the Concentration of Power Index (CPI), which assesses power dynamics across delegates and governance bodies like Houses, Councils, and Committees (HCC). \n\nFor example, we analyzed the voting power of delegates in the Token House and the influence of the Citizens\u2019 House, Grants Council, Security Counci & Committeesl. Using this data, the CPI helps evaluate decentralization trends and power shifts over time, such as the reduction in CPI from 329.25 to 80.90 across multiple governance seasons. \n\nThis analysis also highlights the interplay between individual voting power and collective influence, offering a more comprehensive view of decision-making within the governance structure. Our metrics provide a clear understanding of how power shifts with different members being appointed/elected in various HCCs.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Collective community, including delegates & governance bodies  has benefited most from this analysis. It was also a requirement raised through a Foundation Mission Request which emphasised the importance of developing such a metric.\n\nFor instance, delegates can use CPI insights to understand the balance of power and make more informed decisions. Governance bodies like the Citizens\u2019 House and Token House also benefit by identifying areas where power is concentrated, allowing them to make policy adjustments that promote decentralization and ensure fairer representation across the ecosystem. \n\nAdditionally, community\u2019s leaders can leverage this data to track the effectiveness of decentralization efforts and proactively address emerging governance challenges. The broader community gains from this transparency, enabling more inclusive participation and fostering trust in the governance system.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb0f6cd7555a8d890fe8b5c3724146122297bae07660b7460ff5476028ae21207",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857865,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd9dd636dac5d307af119d18779df8aeecc5c8879a1e8b46edef428987c584f06",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXL89B7fJbPoGVQE7VLHUX1CJfTdr5z8Rd4fgtAkw8udf",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team's mandate is to:\n\n1. Reduce the Foundation's workload in governance operations\n2. Onboard and mentor new contributors and delegates to the Collective\n3. Facilitate efficient governance processes across Token House, Grants Council, and Citizens House\n\nOur mission is detailed in the Optimism Contribution Path: https://community.optimism.io/contribute/contribution-path/govnerds\n\nFor more information about the govNERD Maintainers, please refer to the Foundation Mission Request:\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/182\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team has surpassed its mandate through targeted actions and measurable outcomes:\n\n- Significantly reducing the Foundation\u2019s workload in governance operations, with expectations of increased responsibilities next season as a testament to our effectiveness.\n- Directly mentoring 4 govNERDs-in-training and guiding approximately 10 wannabe-govNERDs, creating a pipeline of  contributors to the Collective.\n- Serving as Lead Reviewer in the Application Review process for Retro Funding Rounds 5 and 6.\n- Boost governance participation with 100% of Token House proposals meeting quorum by distributing +21 voting cycle announcements.\n\nReward split:\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1V8q1NqqGazQgbduK3dMv1tzMjQU9OxkUj4YINe_mEas\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb1fc8380a73b4b16835410f027b407c77d5a4d508702bdf23f932e1c5630652c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728674581,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0d523bd741d75c42131343e11691b7f8f97fd28f55fc626c342e4cd5a590441c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbJy3eWk3GPQWjJsMLffSWzVFSTDwE2jQrwVFZuZPKjwT",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\n**Relevant Documentation:**\n* [Anticapture Commission Charter](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889)\n* [Anticapture Commission Communication Thread](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501)\n* [Season 5 Retrospective](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108)\n* [Internal Operating Procedures](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348)\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) met its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any single entity. It increased votable supply by 24% and **initiated discussions that led to on-chain protocol upgrades.** The ACC built its Internal Operating Procedures (IOP) from scratch, defining voting protocols, communication channels, and reporting processes. Regular Office Hours ensured direct community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were needed.\n\n**Key Impacts:**\n* **Votable Supply:** Increased from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n* **Delegate Engagement:** 165 of 269 approvals in key voting cycles.\n* **Operational Development:** Established IOP and refined governance processes.\n* **Community Engagement:** Held Office Hours every voting cycle.\n\n*More details [here.](https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108)* \n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb4fd2c79292cfb2eed6485e09531e393c95010e1c855162bef4ac7b62963c26d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728831862,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8a8ad640cd39d6004a2f178709055b364ea24a28fe08d71989182ce2b32a5c20",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYAM4fbd44C8n8oSCuLEgrE7yXm75KaLwq4k2jjYrDob5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Impact Garden is used to gather standardized information on a project's impact to the Optimism Collective beyond that being self reported by applicants. The information collected is linked to the reputation of the person providing the testimonial enabling advanced weighting by the consumer of the data. Higher reputation in the Collective, can mean your testimonial is more relevant in decisions.\n\nFor Round 5, Impact Garden gathered over 100 testimonials for 35+ projects in the round. These testimonials were used by Badgeholders during the review process particularly to determine if projects were in the right sub-category and for additional information. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The audience benefiting the most from the data created by Impact Garden are Badgeholders. \n\nThrough the generation of new data in a standardized format we're bridging the gap and giving numbers, projects and contributions a context about their impact to others within the Collective. This has looked like additional data for Badgeholders in the review process and voting. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xb82d01823f3da667cc48bd2c7f8eb0e57a88ec401f969e26fc1c0e0c1a6e267f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728926188,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0acc5b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x28113bebf105894bed1c7a58e0a302bd0f6e6e0a5ad24936983b89b309cd5a9e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXKpBiGRnKoigEpTGjNEhtudLMHDr5of2pt6b1JsNbWs3",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "**Discord Praise Bot:**\n\nAllows users to praise one another within their community for contributions, which are then stored and minted as on-chain attestations on Optimism Network.\n\nFacilitates community recognition and builds trust through transparent records of contributions.\nSince Oct 1st, 2023 to Sep 18th, 2024, We had a total of 642 Praises. Each one a statement of gratitude, as well as reputational data. \n\n200+ Active users \n\n\n\n**Praise on Farcaster:**\n\nIntegrates Praise\u2019s attestation capabilities onto Farcaster. Users can tag @givepraise to publicly appreciate other Farcaster accounts.\n\nFarcaster Frame Praise Attestations lowers the barrier to entry for creating user reputation, contributing to proof of uniqueness and reputation scores across the Web3 ecosystem.\n\n236 attestations minted since the launch on Praise Farcaster bot (within 2 weeks)\n\n76 Unique users minted attestations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "**Active Participants in Optimism Governance:**\n\nDelegates & Badgeholders:\n\nCan easily show gratitude\nCan help community members build onchain reputation. \n\nEngaged Community Members:\nGain visibility and reputation through peer recognition.\nBoosts motivation to participate in governance activities.\nBetter vibes\n\n**Individuals Verifying Reputations and Identities:**\n\nOnchain Attestations:\nProvide a transparent and verifiable record of contributions.\nAid in assessing community members' reputations.\n\nTrust Building:\nHelp users make informed decisions within governance.\nLower the barrier to entry for new contributors seeking to build trust.\n\nOverall Impact:\nSimplified the process of acknowledging contributions and verifying reputations.\nStrengthened engagement and collaboration within the Optimism governance ecosystem."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xba960a2c3c700fa7d19a9c734982b0b35bd064639e1418347270eddab448bf91",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728922135,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x14a3"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4c5822eb6c284edefe4ee6d802f9a5a5d62d93909d60cf33a89b03a9f0bcd49e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSf5KetpgXCDQeGNFDj6BApj2g3A5YkpvENodTekeGYJo",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "GovScore did 3 big things\n1. Inspired delegates to be more active and do things like vote with reason onchain\n2. Showed delegators who were delegating to inactive delegates good solutions for a new delegate based on onchain voting history\n3. Gave delegates a quick and verifiable way to share their involvement\n\nTestimonials:\nhttps://x.com/AYOHTUNDE/status/1772735052943647118\nhttps://x.com/brichis_/status/1785719170035859594\nhttps://x.com/Latruit15580494/status/1794249332654547151"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Token Holders - Token holders who delegate got a quick way to evaluate if their delegate was powerful in relation to other delegates, participating in governance often, and if they were voting with reason onchain\n\nActive Delegates - Active delegates with .5%< of total voting power now had a leaderboard with their name towards the top. They could show token holders looking to delegate that they were active and transparent\n\nOP Governance - GovScore has a positive pressure on delegates to participate and also encourages decentralization of voting power by ranking those with less voting power higher in the ranking."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xbbd1db90ac753eff306b3d7d9f0e773b494a4cfe29833c89fb5ebb1fb74df52d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728852048,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xbd66a74d9a6ec0791b96a5f09bbaeebf41c43daa18a7ad5bf6c6cd72eed2e647",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837671,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0ce07d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb23033c01d75b52917aa5bd303b278d7920a43cb2664e28ac7f68b289dd26564",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbaQbUjSoSxuD3C8nKHiBjQswwqfdP2Nm1GFXUzpRRJwH",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "RetroPGF Hub serves as the central infrastructure and governance tool for Retro Funding, a vital element of the Citizens' House. It empowers the Optimism community to actively participate in governance, explore comprehensive information, and stay well-informed about all aspects of Retro Funding.\n\nOur platform offers detailed information on Retro Funding, including its foundational concepts, the historical context of each funding round, and in-depth insights into previously funded projects. This ensures governance participants have the knowledge they need to make informed decisions.\n\nAdditionally, we enhance community engagement by providing a space for feedback on builders' project ideas. This interaction fosters a continuous learning and improvement loop that benefits both the Optimism ecosystem and the builders contributing to it."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Several users, particularly new participants in the Retro Funding process, have greatly benefited from our infrastructure. Badgeholders, key in Retro Funding governance, are a primary group that benefits. Our platform enables them to easily participate, shape Retro Funding, and access critical project data, making research and discovery more efficient for governance participants within the Citizens' House.\n\nOur platform is also recognized as a trusted source for Retro Funding details, with referrals from platforms like retrofunding.optimism.io (Optimism Official) and optimism.curiahub.xyz (CuriaLabs), directing users to project details for each funding round. This streamlines access to key information for governance participants.\n\nUltimately, our platform supports governance within the Optimism ecosystem, benefiting individual users and the broader structure. Our infrastructure continues to strengthen the Citizens' House, enhancing its ability to effectively of Retro Funding."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xbd8bff5721d5b89b9429a7aa4ec6b9f5c7dbfbd656fca71c7c5c4fcd95e5766d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728767235,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0cda2e"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcdd4b6445288c5bebd951191d673a7aecefbbf6be1cacf4f2a96bcba9c356c33",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfUcZ8dKJdHM6G4sL1PqXiyis6ZorUkUrk4fr2MjvANy6",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Builder Ideas provides a streamlined platform for Optimism Governance and the Optimism Foundation to post actionable ideas for builders, fostering a culture of open collaboration and empowering developers to contribute meaningfully to the Collective. Initially, these ideas were managed through GitHub Issues within the ecosystem contributions repository, which proved to be unorganized and difficult to navigate. This lack of structure made it challenging for developers to discover and share potential projects. \n\nIn collaboration with the Optimism Foundation, our team undertook a redesign, transitioning the platform to a dedicated website. This shift significantly enhanced accessibility, making it easier for developers to engage with governance initiatives, submit contributions, and amplify the overall impact of the Collective\u2019s goals."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our platform primarily benefits builders and developers by providing a centralized space where they can easily browse project ideas curated by the Optimism Foundation. By picking ideas from the platform, developers can not only contribute to meaningful projects but also apply for Retro Funding, creating a pathway for them to gain recognition and financial support for their work. This fosters a more inclusive and accessible ecosystem for developer contributions.\n\nIn addition to benefiting builders, the platform significantly aids the Optimism Foundation. It offers a structured way to list potential projects and track contributors who are willing to execute on these ideas. This improved organization helps the Foundation efficiently match talent with opportunities, ultimately boosting the number and quality of contributions across the Superchain. The increased engagement from builders accelerates the ecosystem's growth and furthers the goals of Optimism Governance.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xbfcc01ce81edc4facace2f8dd29f1b105e86e19e7b7a9657b5a921205d970b5f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728674754,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0be4c8ea3f67eed040f1acfcb05b4f0243b7a844d568ec29d78cdd80d0a7c041",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQwMxbJLBbPU6r5x1yDHkUaxUPuv9LupckcKkPM32Fu4K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\n[Reflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation](https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc0936ba5eabc494adc39b4baf9decc08584172bbec4ae74a2913fc2b66a95d81",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728789954,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x36872c5262768e36e1b4df4289272c543720e6f4d6942c4cc298d0f966db2620",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSvAjst51EJTXhywiGahtcRSCnYBs8F8zK7SYg7SyyWCy",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until September 18th, there were about 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our tool, similar to Metrics Garden, allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n\nAlso, Giveth ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise & growthepie (supporting OP Governance) alongside projects that are making real world impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF. Projects\u2019 order of appearance in the rounds could be changed by using our GIVpower governance system on OP mainnet. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "DeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects and any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project. For example, you can quickly see that 2 RF 4 Badgeholder, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passports, 1 RF 5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nFlagging projects is especially helpful. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5 to ensure there were no imposters posing to be them in the round. If there would have been an imposter, the project would have seen the tweet, been able to flag it on DeVouch and report it to the Foundation.\n\nOn the fundraising side, Giveth enabled EAS, Pairwise, DAOstar, Praise, growthepie, and several other OP Governance-related projects to collect much needed funds to continue their work in the Collective.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc0d4141f541eea01f5b1b89e24235736fcdf96f8d53e3f106b4bda2f3bad2386",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728781153,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033af1"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x20c48e3724b45b4b28b188245ebe4082124cc8e91f8491a8579bb9b595a85902",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmd1xXjnMDgJPZvGLzurV9FobuTxcCrj5BQFzDiE5AKttk",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process.",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Sunny GPT has supported Optimism Governance by making complex governance processes more accessible to a broader audience. It has empowered creators, artists, and newcomers to the ecosystem by providing easy-to-understand explanations of voting, grant applications, and governance tools. By offering clear insights and breaking down technical jargon, Sunny GPT has contributed to increased participation and engagement in Optimism governance. It bridges the gap between governance structures and the community, enabling more people to contribute meaningfully to decision-making processes."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Sunny GPT has primarily benefited creators and newcomers within the Optimism Collective, helping them better understand governance processes. Individuals like Chris Carella, a key member of the Optimism Collective, have shown interest and tested the bot. Through Sunny GPT, these participants are able to navigate governance tools, grants, and voting with more confidence, ultimately contributing to more inclusive and informed decision-making in the community."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc3034da2d27de939dd2c913311b0cc0de805a8fd25d6cd65f2a87b79d9d3737f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929002,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd07f121fdf782d92d1dbaf8599c1bd4547f6d966c373c2d44d5ba36387160ae0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTjuyCZiq7WTsZTWVzX8NU2EtHDJJ4f7qQKCWA1yMjgrb",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "1. Respect Game: We've refined this core process, enabling peer evaluation of governance contributions to Optimism and creating a decentralized reputation system crucial for governance.\n\n2. Decentralized Governance Structures: Our weekly council selection and proposal review processes, based on Respect earnings, demonstrate a practical model of decentralized decision-making.\n\n3. Governance Builder Showcases: We provide a regular forum for developers to present governance-related tools and innovations, while collaborating with others.\n\n4. Governance Education: Our events serve as an interactive platform for newcomers to engage with innovative Optimism governance processes.\n\n5. Stakeholder Collaboration: We foster connections between delegates, council members, and builders, creating a more cohesive governance ecosystem and facilitating knowledge exchange.\n\nThese consistent events create a stable environment for ongoing governance experimentation and refinement on Optimism."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "1. Enhanced Governance Participation: We've increased engagement in Optimism governance by providing a regular, accessible entry point, attracting over 50 leaders to actively participate in governance practices (and many more viewers).\n\n2. Decentralized Reputation: The Respect token earned at our events has created a nuanced measure of governance contributions, improving decision-making processes and impact measurement.\n\n3. Governance Development: By providing a stable platform for governance experimentation and connecting participants, we've enabled the development of several open-source governance tools and inspired other communities to build on Optimism with these tools.\n\n4. Scalable Governance Model: Our fractal approach has demonstrated how large-scale governance decisions can be made efficiently in a decentralized manner in all other aspects of Optimism governance.\n\nThese improvements have strengthened Optimism's governance, making it more effective, inclusive, and resilient."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc480c26ab4b89516bc99dfe94a434f682d088dfe89f183b353dc97a45ad2cb63",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728886469,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x051b41"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xa50a3c90eb1080c26d5a664107c95f3e57391774fd5bb896e394510353a0b359",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNsCqK2FS4UbwP22Z2gWHuNstzfP1BQe2tmVwTrrPMwHK",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The impact on this community is to increase the number of Optimse onchain through open media information about optimization developments such as grants, airdrops, retroactives. for example what happened yesterday (airdrop 5 OP), Partner (Layer 3), to Superchain activity."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Spreading the development of optimism information through the telegram channel (@airdropfinder) with 567k members. This can help spread widely to other OP communities and not only telegram, RPS1N spreads through social media accounts such as x (twitter)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc481e61cda5204ca07637ee6da17c1371a787517a5b63abe3c8c8d4efe368c90",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728924655,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04af44"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x770053a5a51df4d8c261b17904ed109fe65e80ceb5b007d4baa77f5459f88899",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfX4PRL8eBJmvDDAavE35ERFb6U1trcmRLMpBW4QU83YQ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We have created templates for creating frames for delegating tokens. By doing so, we attracted more users from Warpcast and made it easier for delegates. More: https://x.com/zefirium_crypto/status/1795062923720573226 "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The tool is most useful for delegates who are actively creating content on Warpcast. Our tool also attracted good organic growth in Optimism, whose chain we were the first to implement in FrameMaker, and our template was the first to create a delegation pool in OP. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc54c946a16ff6418baa606306b23d1318a924744991c5ad728d93d8de8c5cb0d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728766997,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0cda2e"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcdd4b6445288c5bebd951191d673a7aecefbbf6be1cacf4f2a96bcba9c356c33",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfUcZ8dKJdHM6G4sL1PqXiyis6ZorUkUrk4fr2MjvANy6",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Builder Ideas provides a streamlined platform for Optimism Governance and the Optimism Foundation to post actionable ideas for builders, fostering a culture of open collaboration and empowering developers to contribute meaningfully to the Collective. Initially, these ideas were managed through GitHub Issues within the ecosystem contributions repository, which proved to be unorganized and difficult to navigate. This lack of structure made it challenging for developers to discover and share potential projects. \n\nIn collaboration with the Optimism Foundation, our team undertook a redesign, transitioning the platform to a dedicated website. This shift significantly enhanced accessibility, making it easier for developers to engage with governance initiatives, submit contributions, and amplify the overall impact of the Collective\u2019s goals."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our platform primarily benefits builders and developers by providing a centralized space where they can easily browse project ideas curated by the Optimism Foundation. By picking ideas from the platform, developers can not only contribute to meaningful projects but also apply for Retro Funding, creating a pathway for them to gain recognition and financial support for their work. This fosters a more inclusive and accessible ecosystem for developer contributions.\n\nIn addition to benefiting builders, the platform significantly aids the Optimism Foundation. It offers a structured way to list potential projects and track contributors who are willing to execute on these ideas. This improved organization helps the Foundation efficiently match talent with opportunities, ultimately boosting the number and quality of contributions across the Superchain. The increased engagement from builders accelerates the ecosystem's growth and furthers the goals of Optimism Governance.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc5fdd92834501d4e39b2afbf7f5cd1979478ef5439c2cd99d5b2bb3fecf915b5",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728739186,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc62e05371e381c552feed68b224f77b9db776fece0d4973675edd63f0c25a60a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728840444,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x081505"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x3901584315bdba11e5fd9c3f9adb1500a6388bfabad78720d140d39e851cbb07",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVnnoeQDwF7fpR5yM9cRGpwHEb61xY52MkiY1C8Eu2q7c",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "- Data interoperability and transparency within the Collective: The Optimism Collective is one of the largest DAOs, with new artifacts being released continuously. This includes information on committees & councils, list of important initiatives, links to governance, list of voters, etc. Through EIP-4824, we have created an on-chain (and off-chain) source of truth on the Optimism Collective. New artifacts can be continuously added to the Collective's daoURI, making it comprehensive over time. \n\n- Better visibility for DAO-related EAS schemas on Optimism: Currently, there is no place where DAO-related EAS schemas can be listed and indexed, along with a description and additional context. We built a proof-of-concept DAO Schema Registry.\n\n- Visibility into grants. Working with OSO and Gitcoin, we have developed an initial data lake for grants across Web3, including Optimism's grants, combating grant farming and double dipping across ecosystems."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "- Governance tooling providers: More transparency and interoperability of data direclty benefit Snapshot, Snapshot X, and a variety of other governance tools, who utilize EIP-4824 to publish and handle DAO metadata.\n\n- New participants of the OP Collective: the daoURI is a useful piece of infrastructure for anyone who'd like to find info at a single location.\n\n- Delegates: More data transparency and standardization makes it easier for even high-context individuals to assess changes across the scope of a wide, decentralized organization."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc68d5a1b9170d4f560a4e7b18901e8cdcefca36667dd4d9559ea473020807594",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728924713,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2678"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9421ca676319001aa266d5c24626f2c4a8e7cfd07e58c0140524d0ee82609bac",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qme6WZvn4UUPit5AJuqra6KnfkYcSZijecku1gYaqweSeB",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "EAS is foundational in Retro Funding and governance processes by providing structured, verifiable attestations that enhance accountability, trust, and accelerate decision-making.\n\nIn Retro Funding, EAS is used to:\n- Provide unique IDs for projects and organizations\n- Capture and update project/org metadata\n- Log project submissions/applications to RF rounds\n- Record approvals/rejections of applications\n- Detail reward amounts\n\nEAS also supports governance roles and contributions by representing citizenship status separately from voting rights, issuing voting badges for Retro Rounds, attesting to contributors in retro rounds, and recognizing those who held governance roles like Grants Council members.\n\nView all schemas used by OP: https://docs.optimism.io/chain/identity/schemas\n\n*Note:* Archived schemas have been utilized for RetroPGF3, Season 4, and Optimist Profiles."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "EAS impacts all participants involved in the Retro Funding experience.\n\n**Governance Teams Overseeing Retro Funding**\nOP grants/governance teams rely on EAS for transparent and verifiable decision-making throughout the Retro Funding process. EAS enables them to operate more efficiently, experiment, build trust, and scale governance.\n\n**Retro Funding Participants**\nRF project creators, reviewers, and other participants use EAS when creating profiles, submitting applications, approving or rejecting projects, and updating metadata. EAS ensures these interactions are structured and verifiable for each step of the RF experience.\n\n**Governance Tooling & Analytic Providers**\nThese teams access EAS attestations to retrieve data, generate reports, and gain insights. These attestations make it easier to analyze RF activities and contribute to better decision-making.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc7b16a3ff005dd859dbdc549b237ccbdcbbdba52752b4c9ca37add34bbc8d18a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728853146,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0bbe0d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x7b38cb048e1eb77aa02a98b1cecd4ee346f293044370d2efa57a95d2ce55c3ef",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYA4ZGspNYmXYs1kpdUUkSf7XbM7dkpayW7FbWAErLtXo",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "We designed and facilitated the following deliberative process: \n\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/ratification-of-profit-definition-for-round-4/8312\n\nThe scope of work comprised a cooperation with the Optimism Foudation governances' team on the design of the mandate, the information materials, the design of the sessions, the design of the recruitment, the facilitation of the sessions, the reporting. \n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "Many participants and non-participants have stressed the value of the process and call for using it more often in other contexts. \n\nThis is particularly clear in the comments of the post on the governance proposal: https://gov.optimism.io/t/ratification-of-profit-definition-for-round-4/8312\n\nwhere it is clear the motivation of the community to participate in such a process.\n\nWhile not perfect, this first deliberative process has already brought an important impact to the governance of the collective. Its results show that it greatly increased the knowledge of the participants about the subject, and the trust of both participants and non-participants in their peers and the process. These are cornerstones of effective governance, showing the impact such a project can bring, especially for more complex or polemic topics. \n\nWe have also identified potential improvements that could increase again the value of further iterations of this project, should they be allowed to happen.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc810ed3d968e45a139193d57f08ab242c3bec9c37467c95c51b12b60cc874093",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728852056,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf5519a31d49c637d8f00ff3c17fe9a685b159d2f46e6799a53860ff42b2a79b0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmf7yxRYi7SBffVDrmHiWwHdQkreAUR63wg8c7ZVnEZLuj",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. \n\nFoundation Mission Request: Season 5 govNERDs\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key gov responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. GovNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\nImpact Evaluation made by the Foundation: \nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734\n\nReward Split: \nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1zzsd7p2ECdHBnQQhWMt8ivArqfUIXNv713FjrCQ51mE\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc8684644b232d73ab25ee0b2e06b6a4e0ccf1c3829aa544a59cf88dfb5b5d6df",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728868181,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x06adaf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2d3edf912507d5086108847262467f77af644445b67aa02d391a1f46f85b1de5",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSTxETgqsUkjNr5E7vu8QpxBafWrXDnhK7pe9cvKKHZMk",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Since Giveth\u2019s launch of DeVouch in June until Sep 18th, there were over 700 attestations made, with over 150 being for projects in Retro Funding 4 & 5. Our modular tool allows anyone to lend their credibility to projects that are applying for RetroFunding rounds, as well as fundraising on Gitcoin & Giveth. \n\nDeVouch is built in a modular way that allows any grant program to add their projects & any attestor groups to add their reputation. Our default UI allows badgeholders to see in a glance how many people of relevant reputation vouch for the project; e.g. you can quickly see that 2 RF4 Badgeholders, 3 OP Delegates, 11 Gitcoin Passport Holders, 1 RF5 Voter, & 1 Giveth Verifier all [vouched for EAS](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf5).\n\nEvery project that applied to RF4 & RF5, even those that were rejected, were able to be vouched for, or flagged during the review period. Many of the rejected projects were accurately flagged by the community on DeVouch. \n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The OP community (esp. delegates) can support projects that are adding value to the Superchain Community. While unable to participate in Retro Funding directly, through DeVouch, they can lend their credibility to them, and leave a comment about the project using our extremely easy to use UX. [Try it out!](https://devouch.xyz/?source=rf6)\n\nVoters & reviewers in Retro Funding programs are able to incorporate the wisdom of the crowds. \n\nWe helped the Foundation prevent imposters. DeVouch made tweets tagging every project that applied in RF5. If impersonation occurred, the project would have seen the tweet, flagged it on DeVouch and reported it.\n\nProjects have a simple way to prove their legitimacy in an industry ripe with scams. Giveth also ran 9 QF rounds (7 hosted on Superchain networks), raising over [$865k for projects](https://giveth.io/qf-archive) like EAS, Pairwise & growthepie alongside projects that are making irl impact like Palestine Children's Relief Fund or the EFF."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc88342bb1d646dcf83281905a5ff4b51783f1715deb91091a51694a5e416ffc3",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728739190,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xc8e43334ed7a362c2e338b0eef8f68a9ef64fe8deca0eb2a6b5168a36705da9f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728852472,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5a63077cabc930af1ed712abc7e2e00d5badb61588076819ba5b193ecb0599f9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmf7yxRYi7SBffVDrmHiWwHdQkreAUR63wg8c7ZVnEZLuj",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. \n\nFoundation Mission Request: Season 5 govNERDs\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key gov responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. GovNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\nImpact Evaluation made by the Foundation: \nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734\n\nReward Split: \nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1zzsd7p2ECdHBnQQhWMt8ivArqfUIXNv713FjrCQ51mE\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcaddfab49c766d04f0cc1305d53f65f4cf8b7b83e40a291b8b587352437779f5",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728829688,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x081505"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4efa19fb904485120b596e1346ed90435e790b4d52dc4d5c2f2d68fce227ba46",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVnnoeQDwF7fpR5yM9cRGpwHEb61xY52MkiY1C8Eu2q7c",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "- Data interoperability and transparency within the Collective: The Optimism Collective is one of the largest DAOs, with new artifacts being released continuously. This includes information on committees & councils, list of important initiatives, links to governance, list of voters, etc. Through EIP-4824, we have created an on-chain (and off-chain) source of truth on the Optimism Collective. New artifacts can be continuously added to the Collective's daoURI, making it comprehensive over time. \n\n- Better visibility for DAO-related EAS schemas on Optimism: Currently, there is no place where DAO-related EAS schemas can be listed and indexed, along with a description and additional context. We built a proof-of-concept DAO Schema Registry.\n\n- Visibility into grants. Working with OSO and Gitcoin, we have developed an initial data lake for grants across Web3, including Optimism's grants, combating grant farming and double dipping across ecosystems."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "- Governance tooling providers: More transparency and interoperability of data direclty benefit Snapshot, Snapshot X, and a variety of other governance tools, who utilize EIP-4824 to publish and handle DAO metadata.\n\n- New participants of the OP Collective: the daoURI is a useful piece of infrastructure for anyone who'd like to find info at a single location.\n\n- Delegates: More data transparency and standardization makes it easier for even high-context individuals to assess changes across the scope of a wide, decentralized organization."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcb680162e14c569aca9839b924908c28158ffc8b290b74497bb5a33f938d9775",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728904931,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x5314"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9956299dd587d6b16af54fba8a7fc1df643cd6a5f834236f070fff218cd79480",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmebpEnnzs36KUSCq2FpMEokzXz1GzBzYoXVDJBkq67EEY",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We built this site in response to forum feedback, where many community members shared feeling overwhelmed by the constantly evolving nature of Optimism governance, in particular the many novel experiments around grant programs.\n\nWhile rapid iteration is good for innovation (yay!), it also made it more challenging to stay up-to-date without first having to \"navigate a maze of forum posts\". We made it easy to access all deadlines and changes to programs in one place.\n\nThis has been well received: In the period between Oct 2023 and Sept 2024, there have been 2.9K outbound link clicks from our site to the Charmverse Grants Council page, 1.1K clicks to the Foundation Mission Requests pages on GitHub, and 605 clicks to forum posts on Retro Funding Rounds."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our site has primarily been useful as tool for supporting those involved in grants processes, including the Grants Council, Retro Funding Rounds and (Foundation) Mission Requests.\n\nThe subscribers of our newsletter through which we used to share weekly updates, before then focusing primarily on the website, include employees from OP Labs, OpenZeppelin and Wakeup Labs. \n\nThe teams behind grantee projects such as OpenZeppelin are those who likely benefited most from our overview of the current status of grant programs, upcoming deadlines, and the changelog. They otherwise would have had a much higher workload by having to keep track of this information across a number of different channels (GitHub, Grants Council Charmverse page, Forum, ...)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcb779e32712d53633a328d2b6eddb17e4ea02e084ad78a11b30566df84461d64",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728682551,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x23f3806790b93a2e8e05253ba67825c3c2a9994efd5eefbf29963bc7c8fdb19b",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQwMxbJLBbPU6r5x1yDHkUaxUPuv9LupckcKkPM32Fu4K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs successfully reduced the Foundation\u2019s workload by taking over key governance responsibilities. We managed Voting Cycle Roundups, drafted vote copy, and handled announcements for voting and veto cycles, making the governance process more efficient. govNERDs also ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods during the first season of Citizen\u2019s House governance and maintained the Token House and Citizens\u2019 House Onboarding Hubs. Additionally, our efforts in monitoring the forum, answering community questions, and providing feedback in retrospectives significantly enhanced delegate and Citizen experiences. This performance exceeded our mandate by streamlining operations and setting the stage for an open contribution path in Season 6.\n\n[Reflection on the contributions of govNERDs in Season 5 made by the Foundation](https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcbcdc5e7d0f3c779f89eb04b39cc3629275bfb2da9d2c490f57b6f37628dd7c8",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728851343,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x1c27fe9033e06a58907bca6b76b661c5b1c09a092af805d5c3c93af19fd6da8e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcc81335c14ecee9941bc25b420f2a17dc72b5282b508b214a1200aae80b32edf",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728826457,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xc15e6abe75012efb2ad84ac6b69c0d27d5eb70f78506f44931250c935cf4de65",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaDePjTTYmem5A2yEJUBjhkboGpj5hyk6MCT8XC6eVQEU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our work measures the concentration of power within Optimism Collective using the Concentration of Power Index (CPI), which assesses power dynamics across delegates and governance bodies like Houses, Councils, and Committees (HCC). \n\nFor example, we analyzed the voting power of delegates in the Token House and the influence of the Citizens\u2019 House, Grants Council, Security Counci & Committeesl. Using this data, the CPI helps evaluate decentralization trends and power shifts over time, such as the reduction in CPI from 329.25 to 80.90 across multiple governance seasons. \n\nThis analysis also highlights the interplay between individual voting power and collective influence, offering a more comprehensive view of decision-making within the governance structure. Our metrics provide a clear understanding of how power shifts with different members being appointed/elected in various HCCs.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Collective community, including delegates & governance bodies  has benefited most from this analysis. It was also a requirement raised through a Foundation Mission Request which emphasised the importance of developing such a metric.\n\nFor instance, delegates can use CPI insights to understand the balance of power and make more informed decisions. Governance bodies like the Citizens\u2019 House and Token House also benefit by identifying areas where power is concentrated, allowing them to make policy adjustments that promote decentralization and ensure fairer representation across the ecosystem. \n\nAdditionally, community\u2019s leaders can leverage this data to track the effectiveness of decentralization efforts and proactively address emerging governance challenges. The broader community gains from this transparency, enabling more inclusive participation and fostering trust in the governance system.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcefc0732360f17723874394290eeece90f64626709c7ff01f746dba922dd13ec",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728681196,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcf358ee529ddccecd20697eb01ac881d9a5c4e1304e2899c1625177a4f1c7584",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728851335,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x07a02270e0367cc269699073b6228615a7336c7b043c390fd0b4574befecea1c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTCsskKvMGNcEWN3zMuBxxxjdS2k1ARmE77sihaECbQyv",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n \nRelevant Documentation:\nAnticapture Commission Mandate: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n\nAnticapture Commission Communication Thread:  https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/9\n\n\nSeason 6 Internal Operating Procedures: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-s6-internal-operating-procedures-iop/8637\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During S6 Governance (VC #25 to #28), ACC voted on the Dolomite Network upgrade proposal. ACC held discussions and shared feedback to the Foundation on the Dolomite Upgrade Proposal on certain technical aspects of the upgrade that the ACC members felt could have been better implemented. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501/20 ) \n\nDuring S6 voting cycles, few Delegates encountered voting issues on the Agora UI, resulting in wrongly cast votes during a mission request vote. The ACC held internal discussions on the issue and took it up with the Agora team and worked towards resolving the issue. \n\n\nThe ACC also held a call to discuss the Accelerated Decentralization Proposal for Optimism with GFX Labs and the Foundation. (Reference: https://gov.optimism.io/t/accelerated-decentralization-proposal-for-optimism/8875/32 ) \n \nSince the Start of Season 6 of Governance, votable supply has increased by 7.31%, from 89.4m OP to 96m OP.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xcf37e287dee110d950d7f3809ab01489433c4e6de44815441ed1dfeb6bf32714",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728885784,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x59fbd82d9d3fef55e6c065eacfe4ce53aadd79c3b0db1f4dbada1dcb1787dd9e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNuWiTBzH2SJM9gbKMEVNQfsDw6bFnoUrbmBNafi5QT1v",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the council. In Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where the Foundation multisig was removed from the Upgrade multisig, and the Security Council became the sole signer. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd0b7bdccc4667c2c78205c3c6f804c16351840bbecf3138754f14ed57de8819b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728843647,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x82f9767e3c227f26ae1b6eebdd5f611f291a12882afe5fe2b0bf9d177871db4b",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmT41wtjYDmGqgZxyb9J4AuETVL2DYCk5jGuz16dKXeX7K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "I\u2019m building a dashboard to visualize the total amount of grants committed, unlocked, and claimed. This allows OP stakeholders to easily track how grants are distributed, promoting greater transparency and efficiency in the grant distribution process.\n\nThe dashboard displays the total OP grants committed, unlocked, and claimed over time, along with a percentage breakdown of locked OP, unclaimed OP, and claimed OP.\n\nIt also includes a table listing grants, sorted by date and amount.\n\nSorting by amount helps identify any potentially suspicious or excessive OP grant distributions."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "My analytics primarily benefit the grant council by helping them determine whether the grants are being distributed correctly and unlocked on time.\n\nIt also benefit teams that wish to audit the grant distribution, such as NumbaNerd. This is especially useful for examining teams that have received excessive OP grants, ensuring transparency in the governance process.\n\nAs a result of my analytics work, I have identified two instances where 5M OP grants were awarded."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd0cb7048d7d7204f14a95cad824992f306958530f30f84e070745ef14f853468",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728927726,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03a5e0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xab465b8a7f2b6eccad619d2a44230f5d9c0f9723c1b45960e364007f53520785",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQfGTZ71ttuVkS9bf4afdR5eWMJM5jecyu7n3MUeEVVcN",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Using our OP Retro funding, we raised $115K from the Gitcoin network to fund OP governance (and other) projects and test a novel governance mechanism for OP. Tunable Quadratic Funding (\u201cTQF\u201d) engaged OP delegates and citizens in Quadratic Funding allocation decisions for funding OP ecosystem development.\n\nWe experimented with TQF in two Gitcoin rounds, demonstrating its ability to incorporate OP badgeholder and delegate preferences into QF allocations for externally-raised capital. In Spring 2024, we incorporated an OP delegate signal, as a test in amplifying OP voices. In August, we refined the OP TQF signals, which shifted normal QF distributions by $16,205 (53.8%) and focused them on 12 projects with strong ties to the OP ecosystem and its governance. \n\nFinally, this project demonstrated an ability to integrate OP community-driven preferences with Subject Matter Expert priorities, which we believe is a useful contribution to OP capital allocation and broader governance decisions.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The above work broadly benefited the Superchain by attracting token engineering projects and expertise to the ecosystem. Interestingly, many of the projects with the greatest TQF boosts also contributed specifically to OP capital allocation and broader governance capacity:\n\n- **Pairwise (94% boost):** Governance voting dApp optimizing decision-making and RetroPGF processes.\n\n- **GovGraph (169% boost):** Visualizes relationships between OP governance participants, enhancing transparency.\n\n- **Superchain Innovation Research (121% boost):** Research on Superchain tokenomics and governance.\n\n- **Breadchain Cooperative (63% boost):** PGF DAI mechanisms for community-driven funding.\n\n- **Inverter Network (53% boost):** Token programmability stack & no-code deployment panel, lowering barriers for token systems on OP.\n\n- **EVMcrispr (47.1% boost):** Simplifies smart contract interactions on EVM chains, making them more accessible.\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd19e211b8961f253d9b7107a840ac43d3f58ed119657624dfc1e507e114c5a3e",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929825,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03c940"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xb453360e874cb4200212b9e01fb44d7cf0cf5e905346b8d48807b4fd027e6792",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZk7QPjbkVKxchcJmqmfV3J6C82EYrPjwmgBxyJo48SdV",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The **Delegate Match Farcaster Frame** is designed to improve accessibility in Optimism governance by helping OP token holders find active delegates who align with their values and vision. The tool streamlines the process, allowing users to take an 11-question survey and match with active, values-aligned delegates, increasing the overall votable OP supply. [Landing page](https://delegatematch.xyz/)\n\nLeveraging Farcaster\u2019s 650K registered users and 60-100K daily active users, Delegate Match boosts exposure to the OP delegation process. Our Farcaster Frame provides a seamless experience, enabling users to make an informed decision and delegate their tokens in just five minutes. By integrating the Ethereum Attestation Service, Delegate Match supports delegate reputation-building. It provides OP holders and delegates a low-cost, high-impact, innovative delegation tool. [Onchain Metrics](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/rJaRn0UJJe)\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of **Delegate Match** are OP token holders who aren\u2019t too engaged in governance and OP delegates with active delegations. Holders can easily find and delegate or redelegate to active delegates who align with their values. OP delegates, particularly underrepresented ones, benefit from increased visibility to grow their delegations based on values alignment rather than popularity. By encouraging broader participation, Delegate Match helps decentralize governance and promotes greater equity among delegates, enabling them to play a more meaningful role in Optimism's decision-making.\n\nWe have a solid foundation and are passionately engaged in exploring innovative solutions in this uncharted territory. Our focus includes critical inquiries into user experience, impact tracking, and outreach strategies so that delegation is informed, accessible, accountable, and efficient for all stakeholders. Delve into our [Vision and Insights](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/HJaVrJw1ye)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd19e4850d1b11823345f82df504109bc459e5824ebefa962213e25bbaca592fa",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728854735,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd9dd636dac5d307af119d18779df8aeecc5c8879a1e8b46edef428987c584f06",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXL89B7fJbPoGVQE7VLHUX1CJfTdr5z8Rd4fgtAkw8udf",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team's mandate is to:\n\n1. Reduce the Foundation's workload in governance operations\n2. Onboard and mentor new contributors and delegates to the Collective\n3. Facilitate efficient governance processes across Token House, Grants Council, and Citizens House\n\nOur mission is detailed in the Optimism Contribution Path: https://community.optimism.io/contribute/contribution-path/govnerds\n\nFor more information about the govNERD Maintainers, please refer to the Foundation Mission Request:\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/182\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team has surpassed its mandate through targeted actions and measurable outcomes:\n\n- Significantly reducing the Foundation\u2019s workload in governance operations, with expectations of increased responsibilities next season as a testament to our effectiveness.\n- Directly mentoring 4 govNERDs-in-training and guiding approximately 10 wannabe-govNERDs, creating a pipeline of  contributors to the Collective.\n- Serving as Lead Reviewer in the Application Review process for Retro Funding Rounds 5 and 6.\n- Boost governance participation with 100% of Token House proposals meeting quorum by distributing +21 voting cycle announcements.\n\nReward split:\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1V8q1NqqGazQgbduK3dMv1tzMjQU9OxkUj4YINe_mEas\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd2aa5bcbd73b7310cae175b4da99d2001315a98f76eab613bcb239fdbbb307ce",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837862,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd4120ac98272e4c957b973eaa89459cef30f3762be5d5b2706db160f6a96b445",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728783362,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x035734"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x21dfa26b00e35c00d8fa5c824611cfc9f244937cd1b8c614c42445b55ec29747",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcbWJ8btrkiiGAq5bquHsZuxBxgCkNdfnVL3LCbauXBEL",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Increased Participation:\nThe initial support for Snapshot proposals and early onchain delegations, and the subsequent onchain integration has expanded the avenues for community participation. By offering an alternative to vote.optimism.io, we've broadened the choices available to voters, driving higher engagement in governance processes.\n\nStandardized Governance Experience:\nBy integrating the entire Optimism governance stack, Boardroom has provided a consistent and user-friendly governance experience for developers accessing standardized data and governance interactions via our APIs and SDK.  \n\nInformed Community:\nOur \"Weekly Recaps\" initiative has ensured that the Optimism community remains updated on key governance activities."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Governance participants across the Optimism ecosystem, including both token holders and delegates, have benefited most from Boardroom\u2019s infrastructure and tooling. Delegates can make more informed decisions using real-time data from Boardroom\u2019s integrated API and SDK. Additionally, token holders benefit from alternative voting platforms and more streamlined processes, increasing their participation in governance. Developers, too, experience improved workflows through standardized governance interactions, ensuring smooth operations across the Optimism stack."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd4355412917d0d64e00e9fd7e85a7cc2fa601bc3d27c489e064c3e25a97a2321",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728901870,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x5314"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9956299dd587d6b16af54fba8a7fc1df643cd6a5f834236f070fff218cd79480",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmSwWdPho7C4V2xnA681yahGypvHjXdvsEXZdC4G56XKF9",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We built this site in response to forum feedback, where many community members shared feeling overwhelmed by the constantly evolving nature of Optimism governance, in particular the many novel experiments around grant programs.\n\nWhile rapid iteration is good for innovation (yay!), it also made it more challenging to stay up-to-date without first having to \"navigate a maze of forum posts\". We made it easy to access all deadlines and changes to programs in one place.\n\nThis has been well received: In the period between Oct 2023 and Sept 2024, there have been 2.9K outbound link clicks from our site to the Charmverse Grants Council page, 1.1K clicks to the Foundation Mission Requests pages on GitHub, and 605 clicks to forum posts on Retro Funding Rounds."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our site has primarily been useful as tool for supporting those involved in grants processes, including the Grants Council, Retro Funding Rounds and (Foundation) Mission Requests.\n\nThe subscribers of our newsletter where we used to share weekly updates before focusing primarily on the website include employees from OP Labs, OpenZeppelin and Wakeup Labs. \n\nThose who benefited most from our overview of the current status of grant programs, upcoming deadlines, and the changelog have been grant applicants from projects like the aforementioned OpenZeppelin who otherwise would have had a much higher workload by having to keep track of this information across a number of different channels (GitHub, Grants Council Charmverse page, Forum, ...)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd435790e11a5ec7d0f8dcb57dc6870af1ce2636e410983d33310ec657af5485f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728906295,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x73eda01f2987457f3695b3b0c0f0bc9265f7583264c83416ae722a32ca1db488",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmXL89B7fJbPoGVQE7VLHUX1CJfTdr5z8Rd4fgtAkw8udf",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team's mandate is to:\n\n1. Reduce the Foundation's workload in governance operations\n2. Onboard and mentor new contributors and delegates to the Collective\n3. Facilitate efficient governance processes across Token House, Grants Council, and Citizens House\n\nOur mission is detailed in the Optimism Contribution Path: https://community.optimism.io/contribute/contribution-path/govnerds\n\nFor more information about the govNERD Maintainers, please refer to the Foundation Mission Request:\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/182\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The govNERD team has surpassed its mandate through targeted actions and measurable outcomes:\n\n- Significantly reducing the Foundation\u2019s workload in governance operations, with expectations of increased responsibilities next season as a testament to our effectiveness.\n- Directly mentoring 4 govNERDs-in-training and guiding approximately 10 wannabe-govNERDs, creating a pipeline of  contributors to the Collective.\n- Serving as Lead Reviewer in the Application Review process for Retro Funding Rounds 5 and 6.\n- Boost governance participation with 100% of Token House proposals meeting quorum by distributing +21 voting cycle announcements.\n\nReward split:\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1V8q1NqqGazQgbduK3dMv1tzMjQU9OxkUj4YINe_mEas\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd68e44708a322aaf9884e5d565a7023aff4da0490a408fd7eab356693a269345",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728830964,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd6ea984e2cc371c037035dff68d67bca54b9c36e3ff5d0290cf1f174cac7cfd4",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928047,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x82f9767e3c227f26ae1b6eebdd5f611f291a12882afe5fe2b0bf9d177871db4b",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmT41wtjYDmGqgZxyb9J4AuETVL2DYCk5jGuz16dKXeX7K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "I\u2019m building a dashboard to visualize the total amount of grants committed, unlocked, and claimed. This allows OP stakeholders to easily track how grants are distributed, promoting greater transparency and efficiency in the grant distribution process.\n\nThe dashboard displays the total OP grants committed, unlocked, and claimed over time, along with a percentage breakdown of locked OP, unclaimed OP, and claimed OP.\n\nIt also includes a table listing grants, sorted by date and amount.\n\nSorting by amount helps identify any potentially suspicious or excessive OP grant distributions."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "My analytics primarily benefit the grant council by helping them determine whether the grants are being distributed correctly and unlocked on time.\n\nIt also benefit teams that wish to audit the grant distribution, such as NumbaNerd. This is especially useful for examining teams that have received excessive OP grants, ensuring transparency in the governance process.\n\nAs a result of my analytics work, I have identified two instances where 5M OP grants were awarded."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xd88728d28bf64e0bc243c235cd2a7cab7a8b559edf6fe3bb6a3e28a4ce04e64c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728667635,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x434d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xce63d3df06f29c1ededacaeeb27346f5a0148e3d49f84b2bb6f2bc34f60a35d7",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmePctGMRjZCgWSucdixULCPspC5tsxooyoxEN8k3uSm9k",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Grants Council is to oversee the evaluation and approval of projects for Governance Fund grants, ensuring they align with the season's intent andthe mission requests.  \n\nKey responsibilities include:\n\n1. Grant Evaluation: Reviewing and approving grant applications that further the goals of The Collective.\n2. Mission Creation: Developing and proposing Mission Requests aligned with the broader objectives of the Optimism Collective, targeting specific ecosystem needs (Intents).\n3. Ensuring transparency by publishing reports, tracking milestone progress, and maintaining open communication with the community.\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Grants Council keeps an updated communication thread here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/s6-grants-council-communication-thread/8324\n\nTo make RF6 voters life easier we compiled all our impact data here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/mid-season-6-grants-council-report/9016\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xda6d77ebc6ab2df495a3b2d6584ad4d4bc2d99f1c44e492fa0db0eb72de9b486",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929331,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x1c8c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8b4ffe238987a6fb5c645e342bccb72271f34c2b897f275ba7b6f901b60843e0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbDYUMLw6YNbVoatGN9b9PZFwAAqupG68fZbS6KBPjCjW",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "- Streamlined the Retro Funding application process using human expertise and digital tools.\n- Matched eligible projects with the appropriate Retro Funding rounds.\n- Guided projects in creating strong, Optimism-aligned applications, reducing the burden on reviewers.\n- Enhanced transparency and accessibility in the funding process, enabling more informed capital allocation.\n- Helped prioritize high-impact projects aligned with Optimism\u2019s governance goals."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "- Practically Supported Retro Funding Applicants: Improved application quality and alignment with Optimism\u2019s goals. Projects received either free consultations over telegram group, or commission only (zero payment upfront), increasing their chances of success.\n\n- Streamlined the Process for the Optimism Grants Council: Received well-crafted proposals, reducing time spent on lower-quality submissions.\n\n- Provided Value for Governance Delegates & Badgeholders: Presented clear, impactful applications for more informed decisions supporting long-term goals.\n\n- Spread Governance Participation to the Broader Optimism Ecosystem: Benefited from efficient capital allocation, supporting "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xdcd97d56f824fafa3fc17330086bd6b77d2eb9ab3890147c48266b40c7214543",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728893446,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x05b997"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x62ba2574d6ddd4a3c464185ebf8f2bdf4079057388f14329d75be6e3cb0d4352",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmY5to6nJDQgKd6Gpe7Dj79zX1xWKhyuWJNSYscm2XPnNA",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Superchain.Eco contributed to Optimism Governance by providing easy to access analytics, custom dashboards and relevant research - distributed through our platform which welcomed over 10,000 unique users between Jan 1st, 2024, and Sept 18th, 2024.\n\nOur impact:\nOP Stack Chains insights: Tracked the governance and technical setup of all OP Stack Chains, delivering real-time insights (5k+ users).\n\nCitizens insights: Provided a breakdown of Optimism Collective Citizens and their cumulative rewards through the Citizen Retro program through our website (1k+ users).\n\nOptimism Ecosystem Map: Visually represented the organizational structure of Season 6, including councils and commissions, contributors, and total rewards. \n\nS6 Mission Dashboard: We tracked approved and rejected proposals, remaining budgets, and total requests across the Intents of Season 6.\n\nGovernance Research: We facilitate relevant research through a BountyCaster campaign. 16 submission / 4 winners rewarded and published.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The following Optimism Collective stakeholder group benefits most from our work:\n\nOP Delegates, Citizen and Contributors: Individuals involved in Optimism Collective operations leveraged our platform and resources to get a comprehensive overview of key Governance elements. \n\nOP Chain Contributors: Teams joining the Superchain leveraged our resources to get a better understanding of the Optimism Collective and its functioning, including the various Superchain programs. \n\nOnchain Builders: Our platform allowed builders to better understand how to contribute to Optimism and which programs they could participate in. \n\nOP Token holders and aspiring contributors: Our analytics work and platform allowed a wider audience to remain up to date with all Optimism Collective governance and Superchain developments. Our newsletter, insights and platform have provided context to over ~25K individuals. \n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xdfa6b689488e4fb52e6a788e347253a9ca0657e4efc242696a460b5d1ed76dc8",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728712693,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe02a838562a601703a36cc2629b71f82f8014f2740ad566fed4ee46ecbe5a382",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728868000,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0949f0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2eaeef9af26fc8fee6f1bee26e2611a250c6fc75e7e9b66829c6b9b0c3e9b266",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPuDkNPfLyrLDa2EgTRKf72HJ37y8vZC9fN2E9KTPk6m4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "The report titled 3 Retrospective Funding Case Studies covered the Optimism Retro Funding Rounds 1-3 (the latest at the time of writing). We also had folks working with the superchain partake in our grant summit/operator gathering. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "Those who are interested in better understanding grant programs relative to other programs. Those who want to partake in conversations pertaining to outputs, outcomes, and impact. Those who generally want to partake in discussions around how to improve capital allocation. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe22398736557557a5e059c1f158c385b98c26162d06ba3feea381d749ace1fab",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728867378,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x4bd4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x94adbf0f02934ffded83b06f180510e1d15edfdf7fbb1bd48d475d0203c6179c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmd6ziihVwEg8EB9cMkj92BUwrEPprbwY5FePweLzhcYqh",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "OSO's infrastructure was critical to Retro Funding 4, which used \"metrics-based voting\" instead of the more traditional \"project-based voting\" interface.\n\nMetrics-based voting had never been tried before -- let alone for hundreds of projects across various chains. The data infrastructure we built was able to respond to all of this complexity and power a successful voting experience. (The same infrastructure was also used to screen projects for eligibility and assist with open source licensing checks.)\n\nOnce the models were released, we posted an audit/bug bounty to the community. Fortunately, no issues were raised. Months later, there still have not been any. \ud83d\ude05"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "We believe our infrastructure has been most valuable for Citizens, the Foundation, and other long-term minded governance participants.\n\nAs the Superchain scales, it will become increasingly impossible for every participant to have a detailed understanding of every project or category of projects. Data is necessary not only to better leverage the time of experts and ordinary citizens but also to create a more even playing field for builders.\n\nBadgeholders had many positive things to say about the experience, from significant time savings to trusting that the distribution would be fairer / more meritocratic.\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe31d4d2786e12f2b98934cd43e861d1a56c4ad3f82d3e1299df825142151e72f",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728790721,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03607f"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8130eca1fac842e3218b238b1b1c2179e31206a99bfce8ae1a223de38071ba6e",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVAV3W4wFer33e8DnLUsMBostDsrhtQTyotUtsTKYuBQh",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analysis identifies the characteristics of the fund distribution methods used in the Optimism Collective\u2019s grant programs by comparing them with other grant programs. We analyze distribution patterns, such as the size of grants, the number of recipients, decision-making processes, and how evenly resources are allocated, highlighting how Optimism\u2019s fund distribution differs from other governance models. We have found that Optimism provides relatively larger grants, supports a greater number of recipients, and shows less variation in the amount granted per recipient. We also examine how effective Optimism\u2019s governance structure is in promoting fair and impactful public goods funding. Additionally, we expect this analysis to lead to the proposal of new types of grants and the measurement and evaluation of impact based on data, contributing to more effective funding practices."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of our analytical work are decision-makers involved in Optimism Collective\u2019s grant distribution, as well as those looking to improve grant allocation models and governance mechanisms. By providing insights into fund distribution patterns and the effectiveness of different governance mechanisms, we support these stakeholders in making evidence-based decisions. This will enable the Optimism Collective to contribute to the Optimism ecosystem, the Ethereum ecosystem, and real-world public goods, making true public goods funding a reality through evidence-based decision-making. Our research helps contributors make informed decisions."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe33dbbcefe3d8a7eaa48b95a26ea95d6d6fbd35f0ad36164d0d0f686c97133e3",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728907221,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x5314"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0a5b755e094eeeb5bc3f8f1b26b781b2be0906f2bc86144768a566141e45caa4",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUbhRgVWF3BzUWUiMMsm4YuykkXXDZWTMdo3nFshRhL37",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We built this site in response to forum feedback, where many community members shared feeling overwhelmed by the constantly evolving nature of Optimism governance, in particular the many novel experiments around grant programs.\n\nWhile rapid iteration is good for innovation (yay!), it also made it more challenging to stay up-to-date without first having to \"navigate a maze of forum posts\". We made it easy to access all deadlines and changes to programs in one place.\n\nThis has been well received: In the period between Oct 2023 and Sept 2024, there have been 2.9K outbound link clicks from our site to the Charmverse Grants Council page, 1.1K clicks to the Foundation Mission Requests pages on GitHub, and 605 clicks to forum posts on Retro Funding Rounds."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our site has primarily been useful as tool for supporting those involved in grants processes, including the Grants Council, Retro Funding Rounds and (Foundation) Mission Requests.\n\nThe subscribers of our newsletter where we used to share weekly updates, before then focusing primarily on the website which has much higher visitor numbers, include employees from OP Labs, OpenZeppelin and Wakeup Labs. \n\nThe teams behind grantee projects such as OpenZeppelin are those who likely benefited most from our overview of the current status of grant programs, upcoming deadlines, our grants calendar, and the changelog. They otherwise would have had a much higher workload by having to keep track of this information across a number of different channels (GitHub, Grants Council Charmverse page, Forum, ...)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe350166cd629459e7dbceada8de9e6f5e579d0b9ee542e8d33d7b726f8aa2a3d",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728931388,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x07fef0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8b63a8d02ea3796f6a0de7d31d589c8972dc5abfd267a4a8cff69dfd3b1fd04a",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRMQftpqQtXZeiFLHXZGXUWZrUkLBLbUNBaiRdDPqhHuU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "Successfully integrated optimism governance into Costa Rica University modules completing the token house governance growth mission titled [Integrate Optimism Governance into University Module], and hosted governance workshops, community calls, and events [OPDays] throughout the year for Seasons 5 (S5) and 6 (S6).\n.  \n  \nP.S.: This was a growth mission, and all tokens were distributed among the students. No compensation has yet been provided to the team. All OPDays were sponsored by inbest.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "We successfully completed a significant governance growth mission, positioning Optimism as the first university-level blockchain course in Costa Rica.\n.  \n  \nWe organized gov workshops, community calls, and events throughout the year [OP Days] This initiative has increased participation in governance, missions, and on the forum.\n.  \n  \nOur efforts have enhanced the governance process by fostering community engagement and education within the Optimism ecosystem in the country, through the \"Integrate Optimism Governance into University Module\" mission and the OPDays. Not to mention that this module can now be replicated anywhere anytime. Our work is now attracting attention from other universities and organizations\n.  \n  \nBy facilitating hands-on experiences, we empowered users and students to participate and collaborate, enriching the governance framework with diverse perspectives.\n.  \n  \nCreating the next generation of Optimism leaders, and ensuring a robust future for the ecosystem!\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe3aa732b584cc446aa48e8cc27ccfabbb04b071531314582fbd63f00f052d657",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728927606,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x507d"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x75431e7d1e8755db64454aa0005294cefda8b906b581c859c3e2fe3baf31ebea",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcfiPLCv89tUtbqj3iBsMZAfMQQMn8amYLuX8dfm6WfBz",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "The Mission Request Workshop helped facilitate the brainstorming of ideas as well as how to form those ideas into a Mission Request for Season 6.\n\nHere are some highlights of the ideas generated from the Mission Request Workshop which were then posted to the forum:\n- Bring developers to the Superchain by bootstrapping real-world payment ecosystems\n- Bring developers to the Superchain by encouraging experimental projects with micro-grants\n- Bring developers to the Superchain by facilitating easier tools to develop new products\n\nFull list can be viewed here on the forum:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/intent-3-mission-request-sponsorships/8405/10?u=jrocki"
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "The impact of this workshop and posting these ideas to the forum is open to interpretation but you can view the final list of Mission Requests for season 6 here:  \nhttps://app.charmverse.io/op-grants/mission-request-list-23238814302303523\n\nAnd you can track the conversations had on the forum (link above) after the ideas from the workshop were posted here: \nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/intent-3-mission-request-sponsorships/8405/10?u=jrocki\n\n\n\n\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe49c0c27006d8038eebea137f8901fbe332796b16c20aa36e3f1fe57b96d9601",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728832003,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8a8ad640cd39d6004a2f178709055b364ea24a28fe08d71989182ce2b32a5c20",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTaLq3TDK6zS3KjAr1RYyFfHau8xm2qkAZWWh3qrS6Ark",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Impact Garden is used to gather standardized information on a project's impact to the Optimism Collective beyond that being self reported by applicants. The information collected is linked to the reputation of the person providing the testimonial enabling advanced weighting by the consumer of the data. Higher reputation in the Collective, can mean your testimonial is more relevant in decisions.\n\nFor Round 5, Impact Garden gathered over 100 testimonials for 35+ projects in the round. These testimonials were used by Badgeholders during the review process particularly to determine if projects were in the right sub-category and for additional information. "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The audience benefiting the most from the data created by Impact Garden are Badgeholders. \n\nThrough the generation of new data in a standardized format we're bridging the gap and giving numbers, projects and contributions a context about their impact to others within the Collective. This has looked like additional data for Badgeholders in the review process and voting.  "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe61121bf56020cb1227363e420d1f30592a04c4f631bf5a6c6e755869df331e8",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728918551,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x058237"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd7f5a0320f10eb0b7575efa852b0e4e8340164fb45e1beb9a981c87243aefbdf",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcYM6AKKrjgWq3VHJE41ktdae7cRdmCCViV8yfxDxYztZ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "GovXS evaluated the voting design of Optimism Retro Funding across rounds 1\u20134, focusing on whether voters were incentivized to report their preferences truthfully. Our analysis revealed that none of the voting rules applied thus far are strategyproof! \nIn other words, voters could achieve better outcomes by not voting in line with their true preferences. To address this, we proposed two alternative solutions along with recommendations for implementation."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "a) Optimism Retro Funding \u2013  understand current flaws and get solutions to design a fair, strategyproof voting rule that upholds the integrity of retro funding.\nb) Optimism Retro Funding badgeholders, including experts and guest voters \u2013 understand how to participate without strategic incentives, so that voters can trust the voting outcomes to reflect all voters' true preferences.\nc) Optimism Retro Funding projects \u2013 trust in the voting process, and confidence that they will receive fair compensation based on transparent and objective assessments.\nd) Superchain ecosystem \u2013\u00a0Retro Funding aims to find the ground truth in funding allocation. If the voting rule provides voters with the wrong incentives, the results will be distorted, and Optimism Retro Funding cannot get any closer to reaching a fair, objective truth supporting \u201cImpact = Profit\u201d. Our analysis provides solutions to secure this vision long-term."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe76faebcbfdbdf50995e045d7ce5144f42eb42ea340298b87cca7eb876afcbe1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728854746,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe7c445973aa3b873528dd2dfbe5107c4a9e025205e0a71ff4b5425816df11852",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728930684,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03c940"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xed26259941502d8eeaf2b5de7696a4ac31e0035dac6a572e2f9da8cd1ab46bfc",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZk7QPjbkVKxchcJmqmfV3J6C82EYrPjwmgBxyJo48SdV",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The **Delegate Match Farcaster Frame** is designed to improve accessibility in Optimism governance by helping OP token holders find active delegates who align with their values and vision. The tool streamlines the process, allowing users to take an 11-question survey and match with active, values-aligned delegates, increasing the overall votable OP supply. [Landing page](https://delegatematch.xyz/)\n\nLeveraging Farcaster\u2019s 650K registered users and 60-100K daily active users, Delegate Match boosts exposure to the OP delegation process. Our Farcaster Frame provides a seamless experience, enabling users to make an informed decision and delegate their tokens in just five minutes. By integrating the Ethereum Attestation Service, Delegate Match supports delegate reputation-building. It provides OP holders and delegates a low-cost, high-impact, innovative delegation tool. [Onchain Metrics](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/rJaRn0UJJe)\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of **Delegate Match** are OP token holders who aren\u2019t too engaged in governance and OP delegates with active delegations. Holders can easily find and delegate or redelegate to active delegates who align with their values. OP delegates, particularly underrepresented ones, benefit from increased visibility to grow their delegations based on values alignment rather than popularity. By encouraging broader participation, Delegate Match helps decentralize governance and promotes greater equity among delegates, enabling them to play a more meaningful role in Optimism's decision-making.\n\nWe have a solid foundation and are passionately engaged in exploring innovative solutions in this uncharted territory. Our focus includes critical inquiries into user experience, impact tracking, and outreach strategies so that delegation is informed, accessible, accountable, and efficient for all stakeholders. Delve into our [Vision and Insights](https://hackmd.io/@Suede/HJaVrJw1ye)\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe7e31f8392b0c5678a97cc1b4f8e84e4da06e3b918ba94b2582cb60f197f6662",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728735215,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe848d4e43eb528f85c31b72eabec72f1dfc368c71e1a837daa576e96cb56862a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728929135,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0acc5b"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xf09498aa7a9e39a7a9bcde96bef9ba52e9c34ba8178cf90f080ac973b88cd19d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmQLkFLczDg53KJuLEUHnsD89dk7tZEj2beou9rFZ7dhC4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Superchain Attestation Explorer provides a user-friendly and accessible way to review and verify user reputations. While existing EAS attestation explorers present raw data, the Superchain Attestation Explorer refines this by focusing on the most useful attestation services for OP governance.\n\nDisplaying key attestation data in a more digestible format allows badgeholders & delegates to evaluate contributions and trustworthiness within the ecosystem efficiently, enhancing decision-making during critical governance processes like RetroFunding.\n\nPraise Discord Bot\nRegen Score\nOptimist\nPassport Score\nPraise on Farcaster\nCoordinape\nDeVouch\nMetrics Garden\n\nThe explorer showcases these eight core attestation services, including six on OP Mainnet and two on Base. This integration across multiple chains positions the explorer as a Superchain attestation tool, reinforcing its role as an essential infrastructure."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of the Superchain Attestation Explorer are governance participants involved in the Retro Funding process. Specifically, OP Citizens and delegates that rely on the tool to efficiently review user reputations and contributions within the Optimism ecosystem. \n\nBy offering a more readable interface than raw data explorers like EAS, the Attestation Explorer helps these participants make more informed decisions during governance activities.\n\nIn addition, the tool helps Retro Funding voters better assess contributors' impact and credibility, ensuring that governance rewards are distributed based on verified, high-quality contributions. \nThe broader Superchain community also benefits from easier cross-chain attestation visibility.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xe8641c96bc794d3238e6ec3240841bb39b91f039c484b83a0f074fb52b8d562a",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728910838,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x5314"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5cc920bafc2587ed515fd206f9c9928427ef40a7403009729892e1d03871d820",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmZRNuShduA4ApbMX8SYXJfEcNFYcEhwE2TEiDjssD4n8v",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We built this site in response to forum feedback, where many community members shared feeling overwhelmed by the constantly evolving nature of Optimism governance, in particular the many novel experiments around grant programs.\n\nWhile rapid iteration is good for innovation (yay!), it also made it more challenging to stay up-to-date without first having to \"navigate a maze of forum posts\". We made it easy to access all deadlines and changes to programs in one place.\n\nThis has been well received: In the period between Oct 2023 and Sept 2024, there have been 2.9K outbound link clicks from our site to the Charmverse Grants Council page, 1.1K clicks to the Foundation Mission Requests pages on GitHub, and 605 clicks to forum posts on Retro Funding Rounds."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Our site has primarily been useful as a tool for supporting those involved in grants processes, including the Grants Council, Retro Funding Rounds and (Foundation) Mission Requests.\n\nThe subscribers of our newsletter where we used to share weekly updates, before then focusing primarily on the website, include employees from OP Labs, OpenZeppelin and Wakeup Labs. \n\nThe teams behind grantee projects such as OpenZeppelin are those who likely benefited most from our overview of the current status of grant programs, upcoming deadlines, the changelog, and our grants calendar.\n\nWithout our site, they would have faced a much higher workload, having to keep track of this information across various channels (GitHub, the Grants Council Charmverse page, Forum, etc.)"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xea4404b5b3cf3a606121983089b00bf0ea3dcbef8532a941aa085d22d0eb384c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728710910,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x903e374e6261e72a75fd51b98dc1fb63042c66be897d2d621466fbf0845cee7d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmRu7tgbTkExnETY4M1MqoqzfJASFMVdZdYd38FTtaavNm",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "RetroList, a project discovery platform for OP Retro Funding, significantly supports Optimism governance by providing detailed analytics and accessible data across Retro Funding rounds 3 to 6.\n\nRetroList also offers detailed analytics for each round, including:\n- Project reward distribution across different reward groups\n- Project reward distribution by category\n- Public crowdsourcing lists for RetroPGF 3\n- Metrics distribution for Retro Funding 4\n- Open-source vs. closed-source project distribution for Retro Funding 4\n- Project reward breakdown by impact metrics for Retro Funding 4\n\nAdditionally, RetroList has provided an API that enables direct data queries by other projects like DeVouch and Impact Garden."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "Every stakeholder in the Retro Funding process benefits from RetroList, including:\n- Any user can discover Retro Funding projects and get inspiration to build on the Superchain.\n- Project owners have a UI to check if their project has gone through correctly.\n- Badgeholders, delegates, and the OP Foundation have access to the RetroList analytics, which has an impact on badgeholders' voting decisions and the design of future Retro Funding rounds.\n- Ecosystem projects have access to the API for querying project data within a few days after the sign-up period and maintain a stable schema.\n\nThe RetroList API has been used internally by the DeVouch and Impact Garden projects."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xebbcbd4d172b29cb7935a1372b2d17b1eb70c11e1d5a4bed2dc4974869100ce7",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728764644,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0d2947"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xcf183c566fd7ef4d4821e57c592f72fd610ac29d06cea516a269437a890be4ee",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmPYfBJS98aNbEAGf5kaW4MfDfxfvXy6p9R4oqKeZBoERd",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Our work specifically focused on assessing the robustness of voting mechanisms, which are a central aspect of Optimism's PGF efforts. The robustness of these mechanisms to conflict of interest and collusion were not quantitatively assessed previously, and therefore, it was not previously known how well the voting mechanism that we used would far in light of negative behaviors.  Our work sheds light on this, and elucidates the tradeoffs that need to be taken into account when deciding which voting mechanism to use when designing an RPG round."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The optimism ecosystem, and specifically, the round organizers and designers of PGF funding efforts  will benefit from this infrastructure and tooling. The recommendations provided in the articles surrounding the quantitative simulations as well as the developed simulation codebase can enable round organizers to choose both the correct voting mechanism as well as the appropriate parameters to achieve the desired tradeoff between voting mechanism efficiency and robustness to negative behaviors."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xebf5613bac605b69e6665ee526b00d31c1d440ae2424266fa1be5847f5d0c24b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728820924,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04dbb3"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xbe6777eb0f4b0a3028a889d55ff0e62402e4e5e77c197648c673f25380e076ca",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmULqgaezveGS8LDrBM3e724KdhYfhjCVm7b77uLxE78i5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "More info: https://shorturl.at/PCvaI\n\n### **API & Data Request**\n\nOur OP Governance Analytics Dashboard provides critical data and APIs to enhance governance transparency.  \n- **OP Labs**: Delivered voting data for all proposals since inception, including partial delegations.  \n- **Foundation Mission Teams**: Supported decentralization projects with CSVs and custom APIs.  \n- **OPDelegate.com**: Utilized our delegation API for querying delegation and partial delegation data.\n\n### **Audit of Governance Retro Reward Eligibility**\n\nWe audited Season 5 Retro Governance Participation Rewards, identifying discrepancies in delegate eligibility. Our findings led to adjustments by the Optimism Foundation to ensure fairness.  \n- [Results](https://gov.optimism.io/t/season-5-retro-governance-participation-rewards/8105/15)\n\n### **User Engagement**\n\n- **Users**: 2,292  \n- **Views**: 27,466  \n- **Avg. Engagement**: 3m 30s  \n- **Clicks to Agora**: 811  \n- **Delegators Using UI to delegate**: 130  "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of our **OP Governance Analytics Dashboard** are **delegates, governance participants, Optimism teams, and researchers** who rely on accurate, transparent data to make informed decisions.\n\n- **Delegates**: They benefit from detailed performance tracking and voting history, helping them monitor their participation and stay accountable to the community.\n  \n- **Governance Participants**: Citizens and other stakeholders leverage our real-time data on participation rates, voting power, and proposal outcomes, enabling more meaningful engagement in the governance process.\n\n- **Optimism Teams & Projects**: Teams like **OP Labs** and **OPDelegate.com** utilize our APIs and data to build dashboards, track decentralization, and analyze governance trends to enhance infrastructure.\n\n- **Researchers**: They use our comprehensive data to study governance performance, trends, and behaviors, contributing valuable insights for future improvements."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xec2f1a725428baebe11b109307de39e166cb7c19e94ffe3f2ae7c89073178c2b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728672935,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x3f57"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x36f3e2072476181ff1458a990ebcd9084f0b9b032dd72286e29af111cccc5ca3",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmbTpJT1LmeLoZ3t6tQNuwsHLabMWsJP4Kbzxbhxgeiujm",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Developer Advisory Board (DAB) was reelected in Season 6 with a provisional budget of 90,000 OP. [Our charter can be found in the initial budget proposal](https://gov.optimism.io/t/zach-obront-developer-advisory-board-operating-budget/8141), and includes supporting the Optimism ecosystem as follows:\n\n1. Help to ensure the safety of protocol upgrades. We do this by both (a) explicitly approving upgrades before they are allowed to move to a vote and (b) providing plain English summaries of all protocol upgrades to educate other voters.\n\n2. Support the Grants Council by providing detailed technical feedback on all Mission Requests, Mission Applications, and grant milestones.\n\n3. Bring an additional technical perspective to thinking about the vision of the OP ecosystem and what needs to happen to get there.\n\nMore details can be found in our [Internal Operating Procedures](https://gov.optimism.io/t/developer-advisory-board-s6-internal-operating-procedures/8558)."
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "- Provided detailed feedback on [139 mission requests](https://wbnns.notion.site/Developer-Advisory-Board-Impact-11acf4706b47808f8421c409b4c102c6?pvs=4) thus far (105 of which are within the round eligibility period), to aid in evaluation by the Grants Council. The GC Lead has provided an NPS score of 10/10 based on the value of our contributions.\n- Reviewed the Granite Hardfork, formally approved it, and prepared an [extensive and comprehensive non-technical summary](https://gov.optimism.io/t/upgrade-proposal-10-granite-network-upgrade/8733/21) to support other voters.\n- Provided feedback to the Foundation on important projects such as the Decentralization Roadmap and long term Product Vision.\n- Conducted multiple community calls throughout Season 6, [creating an open forum](https://gov.optimism.io/t/developer-advisory-board-feedback-ideas-thread/8580) to get feedback and ideas from the community."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xecc27b9fd79cae15291ee13e438944894d30d4b743000a2cca349a4b89813f84",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728927177,
    "round": "5",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0846b0"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xae469880176c01f05779551325c41f4077b7f0747a8011bfb8006c62c8824143",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmetcT7oT6dBdBfjtKM1Qz9QffakzZFCKQP8HyMDyuqyi2",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 5,
      "category": "OP Stack Research & Development",
      "subcategory": [
        "Security audits specifically on the OP Stack or its components."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How has your project advanced the development of the OP Stack?",
          "answer": "Cantina/Spearbit has advanced the development of the OP Stack by providing critical security audits and reviews to ensure the robustness and safety of its components. Our team has conducted multiple audits of the OP Stack, including security reviews of Optimism's EAS, which are crucial for cross-chain functionality and gas optimization. Through these audits, we have identified vulnerabilities, suggested optimizations, and collaborated with Optimism team to ensure that the OP Stack is secure and resilient.\n\nAdditionally, our continuous monitoring, advisory services, and incident response support help maintain the OP Stack's reliability, safeguarding its smart contracts and infrastructure.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited the most from your work on the OP Stack and how?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of our work on the OP Stack have been developers and projects building within the Optimism ecosystem, as well as the broader Optimism community. By conducting thorough security audits, we have ensured that developers can deploy secure smart contracts, reducing the risk of exploits and vulnerabilities.\n\nProjects like Omni-x and Decent.xyz, which rely on cross-chain capabilities and transaction efficiency, have directly benefited from our security reviews, enabling them to operate safely and scale their solutions across multiple chains.\n\nOur work has enhanced trust and reliability in the OP Stack, making it safer for both developers and users."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xed3c1510da0651ac111336c35b5f9b01f80212c0673835762c124ae1778f93e4",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728792568,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x03607f"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x8a41676fa3b270b1a986af6497900cecb517820f0c05cbdad791c6076d40e9e0",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVAV3W4wFer33e8DnLUsMBostDsrhtQTyotUtsTKYuBQh",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analysis identifies the characteristics of the fund distribution methods used in the Optimism Collective\u2019s grant programs by comparing them with other grant programs. We analyze distribution patterns, such as the size of grants, the number of recipients, decision-making processes, and how evenly resources are allocated, highlighting how Optimism\u2019s fund distribution differs from other governance models. We have found that Optimism provides relatively larger grants, supports a greater number of recipients, and shows less variation in the amount granted per recipient. We also examine how effective Optimism\u2019s governance structure is in promoting fair and impactful public goods funding. Additionally, we expect this analysis to lead to the proposal of new types of grants and the measurement and evaluation of impact based on data, contributing to more effective funding practices."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The main beneficiaries of our analytical work are decision-makers involved in Optimism Collective\u2019s grant distribution, as well as those looking to improve grant allocation models and governance mechanisms. By providing insights into fund distribution patterns and the effectiveness of different governance mechanisms, we support these stakeholders in making evidence-based decisions. This will enable the Optimism Collective to contribute to the Optimism ecosystem, the Ethereum ecosystem, and real-world public goods, making true public goods funding a reality through evidence-based decision-making. Our research helps contributors make informed decisions."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xeeb9fa9914d71517deec539e80c860548fa8fc99598faae5c11d36f1ab5b1d5c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728826143,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x08aeb4bc57b33ae52cea98678c32d73456572b548760f7470da1631f85083645",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaSpvLBDr1hzD5cDfGWBztHoSJHfRJC2WZUHDMW2HpHDU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our analysis measures the participation and behavior of Badgeholders in the Superchain ecosystem, specifically focusing on their transaction activities across networks like OP Mainnet, Base, Zora, and Mode. It also examines their engagement in decentralized applications (DEXs), token transfers, and social platforms like Farcaster. \n\nA key insight is the relatively low activity level of Badgeholders compared to Non-Badgeholders, particularly in areas like DEX trading and smart contract deployment. Additionally, the analysis tracks how Badgeholders' preferences for Ethereum transactions and limited cross-chain activity impact their overall engagement with Optimism's governance processes. \n\nThis helps identify where governance structures may need to be adjusted to include better and activate Badgeholders, ensuring their participation grows alongside the broader ecosystem.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Collective has benefitted most from this analysis, gaining valuable insights into Badgeholder behavior that inform strategies to increase engagement. For example, understanding that Badgeholders are more active on Ethereum but less engaged with smart contract deployment helps the Collective target these users with specific governance initiatives. \n\nFurthermore, the findings around Farcaster connections show the importance of social engagement within this group, which can shape future governance outreach and participation efforts. The insights have also helped governance teams refine their strategies for promoting cross-chain activity and diversifying user engagement. This research will also guide the future selection of new Badgeholders for the Citizen House by identifying gaps and ensuring the House becomes more inclusive and representative of the entire user profile within the Collective, promoting a well-rounded governance structure.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf0d15c1a35a44b513c5a5260db22b3255ff0a4de4657258f655e6e603cb73ac1",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728816377,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x04dbb3"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xbe6777eb0f4b0a3028a889d55ff0e62402e4e5e77c197648c673f25380e076ca",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmULqgaezveGS8LDrBM3e724KdhYfhjCVm7b77uLxE78i5",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "More info: https://shorturl.at/PCvaI\n\n### **API & Data Request**\n\nOur OP Governance Analytics Dashboard provides critical data and APIs to enhance governance transparency.  \n- **OP Labs**: Delivered voting data for all proposals since inception, including partial delegations.  \n- **Foundation Mission Teams**: Supported decentralization projects with CSVs and custom APIs.  \n- **OPDelegate.com**: Utilized our delegation API for querying delegation and partial delegation data.\n\n### **Audit of Governance Retro Reward Eligibility**\n\nWe audited Season 5 Retro Governance Participation Rewards, identifying discrepancies in delegate eligibility. Our findings led to adjustments by the Optimism Foundation to ensure fairness.  \n- [Results](https://gov.optimism.io/t/season-5-retro-governance-participation-rewards/8105/15)\n\n### **User Engagement**\n\n- **Users**: 2,292  \n- **Views**: 27,466  \n- **Avg. Engagement**: 3m 30s  \n- **Clicks to Agora**: 811  \n- **Delegators Using UI to delegate**: 130  "
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The primary beneficiaries of our **OP Governance Analytics Dashboard** are **delegates, governance participants, Optimism teams, and researchers** who rely on accurate, transparent data to make informed decisions.\n\n- **Delegates**: They benefit from detailed performance tracking and voting history, helping them monitor their participation and stay accountable to the community.\n  \n- **Governance Participants**: Citizens and other stakeholders leverage our real-time data on participation rates, voting power, and proposal outcomes, enabling more meaningful engagement in the governance process.\n\n- **Optimism Teams & Projects**: Teams like **OP Labs** and **OPDelegate.com** utilize our APIs and data to build dashboards, track decentralization, and analyze governance trends to enhance infrastructure.\n\n- **Researchers**: They use our comprehensive data to study governance performance, trends, and behaviors, contributing valuable insights for future improvements."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf21ec9cb593b7038658a65e33db8fb6f80de3564ba12d8f53ee3a563fd39a5a2",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728676298,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x0d523bd741d75c42131343e11691b7f8f97fd28f55fc626c342e4cd5a590441c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZ5aiU9cqKuMYQfS4LCBnCjoqyBW9HM2DQrd7VWErB7y",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) was created to prevent capture of the Token House by any single tokenholder or group, including protocols and OP Chains. It represents high-impact individual delegates and acts as a communication bridge between the Token House and Citizens' House, addressing imbalances in power and maintaining governance integrity.\n\nRelevant Documentation:\n- Anticapture Commission Charter\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission/6889\n- Anticapture Commission Communication Thread\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-communication-thread/7501\n- Season 5 Retrospective\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-retrospective-season-5/8108\n- Internal Operating Procedures\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/anticapture-commission-internal-operating-procedures/7348\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Anticapture Commission (ACC) fulfilled its Season 5 mandate by representing individual delegates and preventing capture of the Token House by any entity. It developed Internal Operating Procedures (IOP), defining voting protocols, communication methods, and reporting processes. The ACC held regular Office Hours to maintain community engagement, though no reports to the Citizens' House were required.\n\nKey Impacts:\n- Increased votable supply from 72.6M to 90M OP with a 10M OP delegation.\n- 165 of 269 delegate approvals from ACC members during key cycles.\n- Initiated discussions leading to on-chain governor upgrades.\n\nReward Split: \nA point system was used for the reward split, considering attendance at office hours, internal meetings, and voting on proposals not included in retro rewards with 20% allocated to the Lead due to the role\u2019s extra responsibilities.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1_4p_C7NQ-UjVXH5O0HXoSYIWKwJeN3JQX3NZZLLMTlc/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf36f66e2e292ac122909961299400a55f92a36c58e5c68d55b1885e6c8fe23e6",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728826151,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x02f2df"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xc15e6abe75012efb2ad84ac6b69c0d27d5eb70f78506f44931250c935cf4de65",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmaDePjTTYmem5A2yEJUBjhkboGpj5hyk6MCT8XC6eVQEU",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "Our work measures the concentration of power within Optimism Collective using the Concentration of Power Index (CPI), which assesses power dynamics across delegates and governance bodies like Houses, Councils, and Committees (HCC). \n\nFor example, we analyzed the voting power of delegates in the Token House and the influence of the Citizens\u2019 House, Grants Council, Security Counci & Committeesl. Using this data, the CPI helps evaluate decentralization trends and power shifts over time, such as the reduction in CPI from 329.25 to 80.90 across multiple governance seasons. \n\nThis analysis also highlights the interplay between individual voting power and collective influence, offering a more comprehensive view of decision-making within the governance structure. Our metrics provide a clear understanding of how power shifts with different members being appointed/elected in various HCCs.\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Collective community, including delegates & governance bodies  has benefited most from this analysis. It was also a requirement raised through a Foundation Mission Request which emphasised the importance of developing such a metric.\n\nFor instance, delegates can use CPI insights to understand the balance of power and make more informed decisions. Governance bodies like the Citizens\u2019 House and Token House also benefit by identifying areas where power is concentrated, allowing them to make policy adjustments that promote decentralization and ensure fairer representation across the ecosystem. \n\nAdditionally, community\u2019s leaders can leverage this data to track the effectiveness of decentralization efforts and proactively address emerging governance challenges. The broader community gains from this transparency, enabling more inclusive participation and fostering trust in the governance system.\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf41b2fd2cae647edfafdf30441d372a8ae5542cb6c4d2b13de31a8673659ab67",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728926580,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x033bdf"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x3c1c70006673f84a7c5ec28b52539b632413913b49ee25cdc3713f2e06f133cb",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTjuyCZiq7WTsZTWVzX8NU2EtHDJJ4f7qQKCWA1yMjgrb",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What governance processes or experiments did your facilitation work support and how?",
          "answer": "1. Respect Game: We've refined this core process, enabling peer evaluation of governance contributions to Optimism and creating a decentralized reputation system crucial for governance.\n\n2. Decentralized Governance Structures: Our weekly council selection and proposal review processes, based on Respect earnings, demonstrate a practical model of decentralized decision-making.\n\n3. Governance Builder Showcases: We provide a regular forum for developers to present governance-related tools and innovations, while collaborating with others.\n\n4. Governance Education: Our events serve as an interactive platform for newcomers to engage with innovative Optimism governance processes.\n\n5. Stakeholder Collaboration: We foster connections between delegates, council members, and builders, creating a more cohesive governance ecosystem and facilitating knowledge exchange.\n\nThese consistent events create a stable environment for ongoing governance experimentation and refinement on Optimism."
        },
        {
          "question": "How has your facilitation work improved the performance of the governance process or experiment?",
          "answer": "1. Enhanced Governance Participation: We've increased engagement in Optimism governance by providing a regular, accessible entry point, attracting over 50 leaders to actively participate in governance practices (and many more viewers).\n\n2. Decentralized Reputation: The Respect token earned at our events has created a nuanced measure of governance contributions, improving decision-making processes and impact measurement.\n\n3. Governance Development: By providing a stable platform for governance experimentation and connecting participants, we've enabled the development of several open-source governance tools and inspired other communities to build on Optimism with these tools.\n\n4. Scalable Governance Model: Our fractal approach has demonstrated how large-scale governance decisions can be made efficiently in a decentralized manner in all other aspects of Optimism governance.\n\nThese improvements have strengthened Optimism's governance, making it more effective, inclusive, and resilient."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf6a8700364c57bf5843d80be33701cb6ea32bf25c035caed5b8021cfee1bf7fe",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837369,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x71a31d4439ce5a9874393060e5ddcf16553963e56ed6e75da48757f101787257",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmR1PZ2BkGTTXQuxr1oKmqkxk7mVmPSAcDNnWYXSxt8ZGZ",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance",
        "Optimism Governance related analytics::Analyses of the performance of Optimism governance, including governance participation, grant allocation and more",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Grants Tooling::Tools which support the Token House mission process, including the operation of the grants council. Tools which power or support the Retro Funding process."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "The Impact Evaluation Framework has been used to inform Badgeholders voting in Retro3 by supporting the creation of Lists, providing context into the Collective for new voters inspired metrics generated for Round 4 and onwards for projects contributing to the Collective. \n\nThe Metrics Garden Database, which has served to inform the creation of new Metrics Gardens has also informed the evaluation criteria for RetroRounds from Ecosystems such as libp2p and Filecoin which have enabled to fund downstream Optimism dependencies: https://www.notion.so/a60768062a2e4e5f8b4ea787e73d38b5?v=468228b4f651454aaf4296934a8a18bd\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The participants who have benefitted the most from the Impact Evaluation Framework have been Badgeholders who leveraged this tool to inform their voting in Round3.\n\nSome testimonials can be found here:\n- On Lists: https://gov.optimism.io/t/round-3-voting-rationale/7030/5\n- On Impact: https://gov.optimism.io/t/joans-rpgf3-reflections/7221\n- On Voting: https://x.com/brichis_/status/1732146910708806069?s=20\n- On Evaluation Criteria: https://github.com/0xyNaMu/RetroPGF3List_Methodology/tree/ContributorTracks"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf7c15b9491f4f831f3277ecdf856a8f09e2b762d41153a899dd59a20887af3d4",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728931065,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xc1a1ec44bb8f7212ae086e18ce3584105c99e614b3306fa2848011d6eaada66d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmc43bWsXGPXcKcoeUL77TrAC7otF6QqMT3dtPwHujxdU9",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the Security Council. \n\nIn Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, as part of this upgrade the owner of the L2ProxyAdmin contract was reassigned from the Foundation to the Security Council.\n\nAs part of Phase 1, the signing threshold for the Security Council was increased from 4 to 10. Throughout Season 6, the Security Council continued it's streak of meeting quorum on all signing ceremonies. \n\nAs part of Phase 1, the role of Guardian was reassigned from the Foundation to a new Guardian Safe with the Security Council Safe as its sole owner, moving Optimism closer to satisfying the 1 week exit window required for Stage 1. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n\nThe Security Council continues to be responsive and efficient in all tasks that require attention. "
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xf8e61280e3edad6939317b7371effc1377baed305f70afc425a0e32aaa3cd34c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728857881,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x9e8711e19fdc19fb13fc5522c8663a78051ae1001632441a116b950ec1388c80",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmUpaWvqtVcYnwGnYewdgn4LBJwxUkJTdhBkXcpRXxUWE4",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Citizens House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering hight-context feedback from highly engaged Citizens during the design phase of RetroRounds in multiple levels and stages of the process. In the initial scope, members were expected to spend an average of 5 hours per Round/Season providing feedback, with work starting on April 1st for 6 months where feedback would be provided for Rounds 4 and 5 only.  \n\nThe work developed by the Citizens House Feedback Commission marks a significant step towards setting the foundations for the decentralization of the metagovernance design process.\n\nMore information on the initial scope of work for the Commission can be found here: \n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863 \n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n\n\n\n\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The Citizen\u2019s FC achieved it's mandate and initial scope of work by providing feedback to 8 documents for Rounds 4 and 5. \nImpact as stated by the Foundation can be found here:https://bit.ly/4f2s3bW\n\nAdditionally, we exceeded our mandate by crafting the proposal of a Mission Request, providing feedback for Optimism\u2019s Decentralization Milestones, Optimism\u2019s Product Vision, Backstopped Grants and Round 6; extending our work into early October.\nFeedback led to:\n1. Changes in the scope of Round 6 and it\u2019s sub-categories\n2. Increase in the resources provided by the Foundation for context setting for the Decentralization Milestones such as: explainer post, loom video, additional frameworks.\n3. Feedback on the Product Vision led to \u201cmoderate edits\u201d and was \u201cvery useful\u201d to demonstrate opportunity areas in the communications from the Foundation.\n\nBased on the impact generated, the Commission will become a permanent structure:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CJs7\n\nReward split:\nhttps://bit.ly/4h6CugH\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xfab7555676a987efaf5fc958a4c20d0799c5179b7e635899fb2edb5f8416a87c",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728751056,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x077495"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x2376b1b9dc761898ad7e28dae33f738e016d5c8a284626ac9e468538596aa069",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmTHLZmtdhk4UXomtCMxtxxHzmGMADAbbebacuNnuhXJzp",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "We developed Pairwise for RF3, and introduced category voting to make the impact measurement in the Retro Funding more organic and manageable.\n\nIn RF3, 185 users engaged, 27 badgeholders using their key.\n\nIn RF4, we expanded into a community experiment using pseudonymous voting with zk-tech. This allowed all stakeholders\u2014badgeholders, token holders, recipients, and delegates\u2014to participate freely without pressure and promote project discovery. We also distributed 4,000 OP as rewards, a 100OP to 40 lucky winners. Here you can find the [final results](https://www.pairwise.vote/rf4-results), and our [blog conclusions](https://paragraph.xyz/@pairwise) for more details on our outcomes.\n\nThe feedback from RF4 was very positive, leading to an invite to build with Optimism for RF5. For this round, we developed a star rating system, enabling participants to assign stars to projects before comparing them. This system grouped projects into tiers, significantly reducing the number of comparisons."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The main target when developing the product were badgeholders, who can use Pairwise, to rank Retro Funding projects in a fun way that promotes project discovery.\n\nHowever, the entire Optimism community that used the app discovered impactful projects, bringing more visibility to emerging initiatives.\n\nProjects benefited from this increased exposure to potential users. Pairwise also sparks discussions by comparing its results to official ones, fostering deeper insights and driving more meaningful participation and progress to decentralization.\n\nThe foundation\u2019s implementation of RetroFunding was clearly informed by our work and [feedback](https://gov.optimism.io/t/retropgf-round-3-feedback-thread/6177/150?u=griff). Enabling categorical voting, and ranking projects then adjusting percentages were done in Pairwise before they were considered to be implemented in RF5&RF6. Subtracting grant amounts and soliciting comments from badgeholders were also inspired by our work, but cut from scope."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xfad2fe7dfad93d2d3f25f8a92ab06713b0019a1d009632ae9ae1ff52c785f843",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728856212,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x47d7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x5a63077cabc930af1ed712abc7e2e00d5badb61588076819ba5b193ecb0599f9",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmYu8bbrp8w8VeVfrvFhSm23bZyQmAenSodKuqUPYSbtXe",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of govNERDs was to enhance governance accessibility by taking on key responsibilities that streamline the proposal process, such as guiding proposals through feedback, approval, and voting stages. We facilitated collaboration among proposers, ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods, and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work aimed to ensure high-quality engagement in the governance forum while reducing the administrative burden on the Optimism Foundation, thus enabling a smoother and more inclusive governance process. \n\nFoundation Mission Request: Season 5 govNERDs\nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "During Season 5, govNERDs eased the Foundation's workload by handling essential governance tasks, including managing Voting Cycle Roundups, drafting vote copy, and coordinating voting and veto announcements. We ensured Citizens' awareness of veto periods and maintained onboarding hubs for both Token House and Citizens' House. Our work in forum moderation, responding to community questions, and gathering feedback offered valuable insights for the Foundation, paving the way for an open contribution path in Season 6 and surpassing our mandate through targeted actions:\n\nCreated a tracker for Missions v2.\nManaged over 25 voting cycle announcements, ensuring all Token House proposals met quorum.\nFor more, check the Impact Evaluation made by the Foundation: \nhttps://github.com/ethereum-optimism/ecosystem-contributions/issues/114#issuecomment-2091050734\n\nReward Split: \nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1zzsd7p2ECdHBnQQhWMt8ivArqfUIXNv713FjrCQ51mE\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xfc0aebfa670b825823a459ed9c18f73b22361db3e7337c508ee480ba887f1860",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728928053,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0503e7"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xbf24079801bd761ca016dc0d1b4d744a07630cff8dd6359b594c885b38b42405",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/Qmb4hSm7cASU2DVDDusg6mM2N2xBLwGZVMmy31myKZYi3K",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Infra & Tooling",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance Infrastructure::Technical infrastructure which powers the voting process within Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "How did your infrastructure or tooling support Optimism Governance?",
          "answer": "Did you know that the Retro Funding application process is currently centralized and relies on trust in the application UI provider (Agora)? This is because there is no way to verify the relationship between a wallet address and a Farcaster ID on-chain. Farcaster Attestation solves this by enabling the verification of wallet addresses and Farcaster IDs on Optimism Mainnet, making the Retro Funding application process decentralized and permissionless."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from your infrastructure and tooling?",
          "answer": "The Optimism Foundation has benefited from Farcaster Attestation for decentralizing the Retro Funding EAS Schemas, making them permissionless.\n\nGovernance tooling builders gain from the permissionless Retro Funding EAS Schema, powered by Farcaster Attestation, as it allows anyone to build project management and application UIs for Retro Funding, not just Agora.\n\nThis opens the door to many creative ideas in the Retro Funding space."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xfc63c4c6e040a13e4d7204f42730a2fa9434894a159ae0db4a61ec5c64e84e0b",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728837854,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x2d4c"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xd49c243da1d2fff2fb2f1f17d995618be347db868c680efc1551171b625aec5c",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmcU98foDukmLPBHusGAy53yL9NMCaLqVVakYCLL23btog",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The mandate of the Token House Collective Feedback Commission (CFC) is to formalize the process of gathering high-context feedback from engaged community members during the design phase, rather than after designs are finalized. By consulting the Foundation on early-stage drafts, we ensure that input from top delegates and governance leads directly shapes decisions as they are being developed. CFC members provided feedback on any drafts shared by the Optimism Foundation. This approach marks a significant first step toward deeper community involvement in the governance design process, aligning with the long-term goal of increased community ownership. \n\nMore details can be found here:\n- Introducing the Collective Feedback Commission\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/introducing-the-collective-feedback-commission/7863\n- The Path to Open Metagovernance\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/the-path-to-open-metagovernance/7728\n"
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "The CFC Token House achieved its mandate by providing high-context feedback on 15 documents during Season 6, aligning with the Optimism Foundation's goal of reducing dependency on the Foundation in governance design. \n\nKey impacts include:\n- Eliminated Trust Tiers from Season 6 grant applications.\n- Implemented a 72-hour response SLA for the Developer Advisory Board (DAB).\n- Clarified retro reward eligibility and expanded \u201cstakeholders\u201d scope.\n- Strengthened Chain Delegation Program with clearer criteria.\n- Refined the Superchain strategy, leading to the Vision AMA.\n\nBased on this success, the Commission will continue into its next iteration. More details here:\nhttps://gov.optimism.io/t/collective-feedback-commission-pilot-retrospective/8970\n\nReward split:\nThe rewards split for CFC members was based on the number of reviews each completed.\nhttps://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Ptp8e3G5IfJi62aStBjOvNoJnH69glley_qWa3L6j-0/edit?usp=sharing\n"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xfd75371205dbd6965f801fa6bdca339717779cbaea8ff0190caaabc8a28bdcf5",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728887024,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x0e98"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x14afcfca7a32226f8e993fefc5ee3f4ac3ae1c62a03486ed213faadc8b30fb45",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmNuWiTBzH2SJM9gbKMEVNQfsDw6bFnoUrbmBNafi5QT1v",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 6: May 9th - September 18th 2024 (up until Voting Cycle #28)"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "The Security Council carried out its role of signing protocol upgrades approved by the Token House in accordance with the Internal Operating Procedures set out by the council. In Season 6 the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1, where the Foundation multisig was removed from the Upgrade multisig, and the Security Council became the sole signer. "
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "In Season 6, the Optimism Security Council progressed from Phase 0 to Phase 1. A requirement for Phase 1 is that a 75% signing threshold is met for all upgrades. This requires 10 out of 13 signatures. Security Council members continued to engage swiftly when action was required. The following upgrades were signed during Season 6:\n\n### Protocol Upgrade 10 \u2014 Granite Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: September 6 - September 10\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed September 11 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 9 \u2014 Fjord Network Upgrade\n\u2705 SC signing: June 26 - July 2\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed July 10 with 12/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 8 \u2014 Changes for Stage 1 Decentralization\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures\n### Protocol Upgrade 7 \u2014 Fault Proofs\n\u2705 SC signing: June 5 - June 8\n\ud83e\udd73 Status: Executed June 10 with 10/13 signatures"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xfe7ff4fdea762f9e8f25d7f6fa788fe1f4b5c3e786d42083c5d8b46452a1aee7",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728888492,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x20f4"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0x4776c7cc4b248472758e9f111d0f705d4cc7042d9dea575bb53e6da9419a3c0d",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmVnnoeQDwF7fpR5yM9cRGpwHEb61xY52MkiY1C8Eu2q7c",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Analytics",
      "subcategory": [
        "Governance facilitation of critical governance processes and/or experiments such as community calls, proposal creation or review sessions, deliberations or similar::",
        "Governance Tooling::Tools which are used by Delegates or Citizens participate in Optimism Governance  tools which are used by Delegates and/or Citizens asuch as voting clients. Tools which support delegates and citizens insights into governance performance and history",
        "Optimism Metagovernance research::Research that has provided relevant insight into the design of Optimism Governance"
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "What aspects of Optimism Governance is your analytics work measuring?",
          "answer": "- Data interoperability and transparency within the Collective: The Optimism Collective is one of the largest DAOs, with new artifacts being released continuously. This includes information on committees & councils, list of important initiatives, links to governance, list of voters, etc. Through EIP-4824, we have created an on-chain (and off-chain) source of truth on the Optimism Collective. New artifacts can be continuously added to the Collective's daoURI, making it comprehensive over time. \n\n- Better visibility for DAO-related EAS schemas on Optimism: Currently, there is no place where DAO-related EAS schemas can be listed and indexed, along with a description and additional context. We built a proof-of-concept DAO Schema Registry.\n\n- Visibility into grants. Working with OSO and Gitcoin, we have developed an initial data lake for grants across Web3, including Optimism's grants, combating grant farming and double dipping across ecosystems."
        },
        {
          "question": "Who has benefited most from the analytics work you have produced?",
          "answer": "- Governance tooling providers: More transparency and interoperability of data direclty benefit Snapshot, Snapshot X, and a variety of other governance tools, who utilize EIP-4824 to publish and handle DAO metadata.\n\n- New participants of the OP Collective: the daoURI is a useful piece of infrastructure for anyone who'd like to find info at a single location.\n\n- Delegates: More data transparency and standardization makes it easier for even high-context individuals to assess changes across the scope of a wide, decentralized organization."
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "id": "0xffc5f0d74c0f9ea73e6305809a5e6cf0612d2186ba7d7d4902f28aa7f8a8bb86",
    "attester": "0xF6872D315CC2E1AfF6abae5dd814fd54755fE97C",
    "recipient": "0x0000000000000000000000000000000000000000",
    "timeCreated": 1728674196,
    "round": "6",
    "farcasterID": {
      "type": "BigNumber",
      "hex": "0x16fa"
    },
    "metadataSnapshotRefUID": "0xe66570625a364a1034d5c976d3db963bdc0e225072ce2a203716c316674b6553",
    "metadataType": 0,
    "metadataUrl": "https://storage.retrofunding.optimism.io/ipfs/QmfZP2N4VFTQaZZaUf78VdFSKEvxdtV23dapnDZu7Qk9Pe",
    "metadata": {
      "round": 6,
      "category": "Governance Leadership",
      "subcategory": [
        "Councils, Commissions and Advisory Boards; NERD programs focused exclusively on core governance responsibilities (GovNERDs)::This includes Security Council, Grants Council, Developer Advisory Board, Code of Conduct Council, Anticapture Commission, Collective Feedback Commissions and GovNERDs."
      ],
      "impactStatement": [
        {
          "question": "In what season did your work take place",
          "answer": "Season 5: Sept 28th 2023 - May 8th 2024"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the mandate of your Governance Leadership function?",
          "answer": "There were three goals for the DAB in Season 5, as laid out in the [initial forum post](https://gov.optimism.io/t/developer-advisory-board/6892):\n\n1) Assess and approve Delegate Mission Request 13 drafts based on their technical merits \n2) Aid the Grants Council in assessing approved Delegate Mission Requests and Mission Applications 13 under Intent #1\n3) Advise the Grants Council in assessing the completion of technical milestones\n\nAdditionally, there was one implicit goal:\n\n4) Act as a test run to determine whether the DAB is a useful part of Optimism Governance, explore additional ways to help, and formalize processes for future seasons."
        },
        {
          "question": "How did your work achieve or exceed the mandate of your Governance Leadership Function?",
          "answer": "On the explicit goals:\n- All Mission Requests were reviewed by multiple DAB members, who provided that input to the community in order to determine the right MRs to fund.\n- All applications to the Grants Council under Intent #1 received feedback from 2+ DAB members to help better allocate funds. \n- Additionally, the DAB expanded our scope to provide input on all requested applications, not just Intent #1, a learning that has carried over to future seasons.\n- The DAB also began to give feedback on the funding amount, which resulted in 100k+ OP being saved by governance due to more appropriate funding.\n\nAdditionally, on the implicit goal, the experiment of having a Developer Advisory Board was a great success. It was renewed for Season 6 with an expanded scope, and has continued to deliver important results."
        }
      ]
    }
  }
]